<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Heautonaparnumenos: or A treatise of self-denyall. Intended for the pulpit; but now committed to the presse for the publike benefit.</title>
            <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2649</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E336_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18443</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860405</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860405</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112525</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86527)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E336[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Heautonaparnumenos: or A treatise of self-denyall. Intended for the pulpit; but now committed to the presse for the publike benefit.</title>
                  <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>70, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Wilson, for Richard Royston, at the Angel in Ivy-lane.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Hooker by Wing.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 6th".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy:"May 6th".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Self-denial --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112525:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>HEA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TONAPARN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MENOS:</hi> Or a Treatiſe of SELF-DENYALL.</p>
            <p>Intended for the Pulpit; but now committed to the Preſſe for the PUBLIKE BENEFIT.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Inutilis olim</l>
               <l>Ne videar vixiſſe. —</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 COR. 2.6, 7, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But we ſpeake wiſdome among thoſe that are perfect: but not the wiſdome of this world, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by W. WILSON, for RICHARD ROYSTON, at the Angel in Ivy-Iane. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:112525:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:112525:2"/>
            <head>A Treatiſe of Self-Denyall.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>MATTH. 16.24.</bibl>
                  <p>If any one will come after me, let him deny himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>(BUt in the firſt place, let us with all thankfulneſſe adore the Divine Bounty for this ineſtimable Jewell of His moſt Holy VVord, revealed to us; and with all humility implore the light and aid of his moſt Bleſſed Spirit, that we, who can doe nothing without Him, may with Him be able to ſee His Truth, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, ſell all we are worth to purchaſe it: To this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone Glory, in our Eternal Good, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>)</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Occaſion</hi> of theſe words will be the beſt key to our Diſcourſe: And that was this. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour now drawing faſt upon the <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> of His Life, and being in the <hi>laſt Act</hi> thereof, to expreſſe the Perfection of <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> that the ſuddenneſſe of the <hi>Tragedy</hi> might not drive his Diſciples into an unwonted extaſie,<note place="margin">Verſe 21.</note> 
               <hi>acquaints</hi> them often with it before-hand, well knowing, that the blow foreſeene in time, when it came, would make the leſſe impreſſion. Yet <hi>Peter,</hi> it ſeemes,<note place="margin">Verſe 22.</note> ſomewhat mov'd above the reſt, whether by the inſtinct of fleſh and bloud, or the ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of the Devill, or both, which is moſt likely, <hi>taking him aſide,</hi> began to <hi>rebuke</hi> Him, ſaying; <hi>Sir! favour your ſelfe, this barme ſhall not befall you.</hi> Moſt ſtrange audaciouſneſſe in a Diſciple to his Maſter,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112525:3"/>whether we looke at his words, or his behaviour! <hi>No ſuch thing ſhall befall you;</hi> and yet but juſt then, He had flatly affirmed the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary? What elſe was this, but, with the <hi>Devill</hi> in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> to oppoſe <hi>his owne infallibility</hi> to his <hi>Maſters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.4. Jer. 5.12.</note> that is (in plaine <hi>Engliſh</hi>) to give Him the <hi>Lye?</hi> An intolerable preſumption. And yet, thereupon to inferre, He ought to <hi>favour,</hi> that is, <hi>make much of,</hi> or <hi>ſeek Himſelfe;</hi> this was no other, but a downe-right Devilliſh <hi>Temptation:</hi> A true, but ſlyer, <hi>Copy</hi> of that <hi>Originall</hi> one of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> who tempted our firſt <hi>Parents,</hi> by <hi>ſelf-love,</hi> to affect a <hi>Deity.</hi> But laſtly, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to perſwade this,<note place="margin">Gen 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>to take Him aſide,</hi> to put Him beſide His courſe, and there earneſtly <hi>to adviſe Him;</hi> this was juſt like the Devils <hi>tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Adam</hi> from his <hi>Worke,</hi> to the <hi>fatall Tree</hi> of Perdition. All which ſeriouſly conſidered, we cannot but (though with no ſmall admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) aknowledge <hi>Peter</hi> but even now made a <hi>Claviger</hi> of the Heavenly Kingdome,<note place="margin">Verſe 19.</note> was herein the Devills <hi>Spokes-man.</hi> Such was the daring boldneſſe, that by long practiſe he was growne to: No leſſe <hi>Inſtrument</hi> could ſerve him to fruſtrate the <hi>Second Covenant,</hi> then the <hi>Senior Diſciple</hi> of our Saviour's, who us'd but a deſpicable <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> to doe as much to the <hi>Firſt.</hi> All that can bee ſaid in <hi>Peters</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe is, <hi>he meant no harme</hi> to our Saviour in thoſe words; but <hi>good</hi> rather: the reaſon, as I ſuppoſe, why he made ſo bold with Him, as he did. But this, though the common pretence of <hi>blinde zeale,</hi> is not enough to <hi>excuſe</hi> it; the <hi>Devil,</hi> to be ſure, meant <hi>harm</hi> enough, who in thoſe words of his had no leſſe matter in deſigne, then the <hi>irrecoverable Deſtruction of all Man-kinde:</hi> the reaſon, as it may ſeem, why our Saviour <hi>check'd</hi> not him,<note place="margin">Verſe 23</note> but <hi>Satan ſpeaking in him.</hi> The beſt of it was this: Our Saviour, <hi>the Second Adam, being the Lord Himſelf from Heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.17.</note> did not, like that <hi>Firſt Adam, form'd out of the earth, give way</hi> to this temptation, <hi>no not for a moment;</hi> but forthwith repelled it; bid <hi>Satan, be gone.</hi> And whereas <hi>Peter</hi> endeavoured, in a ſort, to <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi> Him, He <hi>converted</hi> Himſelfe into His <hi>courſe</hi> againe, bids <hi>Peter</hi> not <hi>ſtand</hi> like <hi>Satan,</hi> thus <hi>before</hi> Him, to <hi>oppoſe</hi> Him; but, <hi>get him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde Him</hi> rather, and become His <hi>follower in this,</hi> though never ſo hard, <hi>enterpriſe of Self-denyall.</hi> Which that <hi>Peter</hi> might <hi>reſent</hi> more kindly, and not conceive himſelfe hardly dealt with, as if <hi>evill</hi> had been return'd him for his <hi>good,</hi> our Saviour to <hi>undeceive</hi> him, vouchſafes a <hi>Reaſon</hi> of his <hi>Reproofe: Becauſe he ſavourd not the things of God,</hi> meaning this great matter of <hi>Self-denyall;</hi> but onely <hi>the things of men,</hi> to wit, that <hi>traiterous</hi> ſin of <hi>Self-love.</hi> And not content
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112525:3"/>with this, that He might the better ſet <hi>Satan packing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 24</note> and yet keep <hi>Peter</hi> by Him; by way of <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> He layes here the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> of what <hi>Peter</hi> went about to <hi>deſtroy,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Schools</hi> or <hi>Sect</hi> of men, as ſhould <hi>ſavour the things of God,</hi> and not <hi>the things of men:</hi> that is, a <hi>Sect of Chriſtians, or ſelf-denyers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this was the ſole Deſigne of theſe words we are now upon, will evidently appeare from the <hi>formoſt</hi> of them, <hi>If any one will come after Me,</hi> rightly underſtood; for they being a <hi>Si quis of Invitation</hi> of any man to this <hi>Schoole,</hi> import no more but this; <hi>If any one will become my Diſciple,</hi> or <hi>a Chriſtian.</hi> 'Tis true, the Name of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> was not then taken up; but here was the <hi>Foundation</hi> layd thereof. For as the <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> were ſo called from the firſt <hi>Author</hi> of their <hi>Sect, Pythagoras;</hi> and the <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans,</hi> from the firſt <hi>Author</hi> of theirs, <hi>Epicurus;</hi> ſo were the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples,</hi> from their firſt <hi>Author, Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 11.26.</note> at length in <hi>Antioch firſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſtians. Diſciples</hi> then and <hi>Followers,</hi> in this ſenſe, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming termes <hi>Synonymous,</hi> this <hi>comming after</hi> muſt not be ſo <hi>lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> underſtood, as if the <hi>Diſciple</hi> were continually to <hi>tread</hi> in his <hi>Maſters ſteps;</hi> but that, if he did <hi>jurare in verba,</hi> that is, take upon him to defend his <hi>Maſters ſingular Dogmata,</hi> or <hi>Opinions,</hi> though he ſeldome or never bare him company, 'twas ſufficient. Thus a <hi>Metempſychoſis,</hi> or <hi>Tranſanimation,</hi> being the <hi>ſingular Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> it became the <hi>Characteriſtick</hi> of the <hi>Pythagore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> who, in purſuance of it, abſtain'd the eating <hi>Fleſh.</hi> Thus an <hi>Acatalepſia,</hi> or <hi>Incomprebenſibility</hi> of all things, being the <hi>ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Dogma</hi> of <hi>Arceſilaus,</hi> it became the <hi>Characteriſticke</hi> of the <hi>Academicks,</hi> who, in purſuance of it, call'd all <hi>Sciences</hi> in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thus, the maintaining <hi>Pleaſure</hi> to bee our <hi>Summum Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> being the <hi>ſingular Dogma</hi> of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> it became the <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteriſtick</hi> of the <hi>Epicureans,</hi> who, in purſuance of it, deny'd <hi>Gods Providence in ſublunary matters.</hi> And thus, this <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall</hi> being the <hi>ſingular Dogma of Chriſt,</hi> above all others, He would have it here become the <hi>Characteriſtick</hi> of all <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who, in purſuance of it, ſhould become <hi>Crucigeri,</hi> or <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciani,</hi> as anciently they were called, that is, <hi>Croſſe-bearers,</hi> yea <hi>takers of it up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>difference,</hi> though, wee may obſerve betwixt theirs and this <hi>Dogma</hi> of our Saviours: theirs had no neceſſary influence on whatſoever elſe they taught, but ſo has this <hi>Dogma</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:112525:4"/>being the very <hi>Foundation</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> yea the <hi>Grand Deſigne</hi> of all <hi>Theologie.</hi> The <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> that which was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam's Rule</hi> in <hi>Innocency,</hi> did not deſigne this, but ſuppoſe it. There was no ſuch thing then in the world, as our <hi>Selfe, contradiſtinct from God.</hi> So that had <hi>Adam</hi> perſevered in his <hi>Integrity,</hi> our <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> had been <hi>Geneticall</hi> altogether, that is, by the <hi>Progreſſive me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi> of <hi>Workes of the Law,</hi> not the <hi>Regreſſive method</hi> of <hi>Faith and Mortification,</hi> we ſhould have attain'd, after a perpetuall tenour of liquid <hi>Happineſſe</hi> here, the <hi>eternall Fruition</hi> of it hereafter. But now, by the <hi>Intruſion</hi> of our <hi>Self</hi> into the world upon <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam's Fall,</hi> our <hi>Theologie</hi> is turn'd <hi>Analyticall</hi> altogether; St. <hi>John</hi> plainly telling us,<note place="margin">1 John 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>our Saviour appeared,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that be might analyſe, or diſſolve the works of the devill.</hi> What thoſe <hi>Works</hi> were is evident, their ſole <hi>Foundation</hi> being that <hi>worke</hi> of his on <hi>Adam,</hi> whom he tempted to <hi>ſeeke himſelf,</hi> yea ſo far to <hi>ſeek himſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.5.</note> as to become <hi>Aemulus to God Himſelf,</hi> the <hi>Naturall</hi> and laſt aime of <hi>Self-love,</hi> if it never receive <hi>check.</hi> This was the Devills firſt <hi>Handſale,</hi> his <hi>Maſterpiece,</hi> that <hi>Grand Fundament all Deſigne,</hi> on which he ha's built his <hi>Kingdome</hi> ever ſince. That therefore our Saviour might <hi>diſſolve all his works</hi> as <hi>compendiouſly</hi> as might be, He, by this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> ſtrikes at the <hi>Foundation,</hi> knowing, if that were undermin'd, the whole <hi>Building</hi> would ſoon totter. By this He <hi>layes the Axe to the Root of the Tree,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 3.10.</note> knowing, if that were up, the <hi>Branches</hi> would ſoon come to the ground.</p>
            <p>But, that He might doe this the better, and to provide leſt His <hi>Poſtulata</hi> ſhould not be <hi>granted,</hi> neceſſary it was, <hi>Mankinde</hi> ſhould be throughly <hi>convinc't</hi> of theſe <hi>Particulars.</hi> That there was ſuch a thing as our <hi>Selfe</hi> crept into the world: That it was <hi>utter enmity with God:</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ly, that it was beyond our <hi>Hability</hi> to remove it. A <hi>Glaſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> might reflect theſe <hi>Particulars</hi> to our <hi>view,</hi> was wantin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a more commodious one could not poſſibly be found, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t old, almoſt obliterated, <hi>Law of Nature, retriv'd.</hi> Hereupon the <hi>Divine Majeſty (Himſelfe)</hi> committed that <hi>Law</hi> to <hi>writing:</hi> which, though it were, to prevent the like <hi>obliterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for the future, done in <hi>Tables of ſtone</hi> yet, could not have ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected it, had not <hi>Moſes</hi> beſide <hi>recorded</hi> it in his <hi>Pentateuch;</hi> a farre more laſting <hi>Monument;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5.18.</note> for, when <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, that Record ſhall not,</hi> but continue to a <hi>tittle,</hi> as our Saviour tells us. Now by this <hi>Glaſſe</hi> was ſoone diſcovered, what a <hi>Maſſt</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:112525:4"/>of <hi>Selfe-love</hi> we were buried in: How <hi>irreconcileable enmity</hi> God conceiv'd thereat: Laſtly, our owne utter <hi>Imbecillity,</hi> to ſubdue it. This was plaine. No longer then might we flatter our ſelves with a conceite of our <hi>ſtill continuing Innocency.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.9.</note> Nor could wee ſtill pretend in our <hi>excuſe</hi> any <hi>Ignorance</hi> of our <hi>miſery,</hi> either from our <hi>Guilt,</hi> or our <hi>Imbecillity.</hi> But, of neceſſity we were forc't to pray in aide of ſome <hi>Saviour</hi> beſide, yea <hi>above,</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> to <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> us out of it.</p>
            <p>The World now being <hi>by this meanes</hi> made ripe for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, (for ſo <hi>John B.</hi> had made ſufficient diſcovery) the <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time</hi> then came, wherein our Saviour was to <hi>appeare,</hi> to take this <hi>Worke</hi> in hand <hi>Himſelfe,</hi> and ſo put the laſt <hi>Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to our <hi>Theologie.</hi> This He did <hi>at large</hi> in His <hi>Sermon on the Mount,</hi> but <hi>briefly</hi> in this <hi>Text,</hi> the <hi>Epitome</hi> of that; And, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Method</hi> of <hi>teaching</hi> is, both more <hi>ſhort,</hi> and more <hi>effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious</hi> by <hi>Example</hi> then by <hi>Precept,</hi> He ha's left us in His <hi>Life,</hi> but eſpecially in His <hi>Death, The Conſummatum eſt</hi> of all, as perfect a <hi>Patterne</hi> of this <hi>Precept,</hi> as <hi>Mortality</hi> can reach to. By which <hi>Death</hi> making a <hi>full Satisfaction</hi> for us, in a moſt admitable <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium,</hi> He ha's likewiſe obtain'd of His <hi>Father, for thoſe that live by His Faith:</hi> Firſt, a <hi>Pardon</hi> for <hi>Adam's ſelfe-love imputed to us:</hi> Secondly, <hi>ſufficient Grace</hi> to enable us <hi>(ſincerely)</hi> to <hi>deny</hi> it in <hi>our ſelves:</hi> And laſtly, a <hi>Pardon</hi> for all our owne <hi>Defaults</hi> therein, and <hi>Frailties, repented of.</hi> Upon all which neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followes, our <hi>Adoption</hi> firſt into God's <hi>Favour by Him:</hi> And then our <hi>Re-admiſſion</hi> into that <hi>Patrimony</hi> we <hi>forfeited</hi> in <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Self-denyall</hi> being thus, as we ſee, the <hi>Catholique Deſigne</hi> both of <hi>Law</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">See below in the fift Point in the Margent.</note> and <hi>Goſpel,</hi> it muſt needs have ſome <hi>Influence,</hi> more or leſſe on every <hi>Vertue</hi> we can practiſe. 'Tis no marvaile then, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our makes it here the onely <hi>Fundamentall,</hi> or, if ye will, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Probatum eſt</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> ſince,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 12.13.</hi> Quod caput eſt rerum quas lex praeſcripſit <hi>Jë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu?</hi> crucem ſubire, ſemet a ſe abdicere. <hi>H. Grot. in Inſtit. puer.</hi>
               </note> as the <hi>Wife-man</hi> ſaid of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Law, we may well ſay of this Doctrine, It is <hi>totum homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, Amans whole Duty,</hi> to fulfill it. Wherefore elſe is it, that all things, now under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> goe ſo by <hi>Contraries?</hi> To <hi>Exalt,</hi> we muſt <hi>abaſe</hi> our ſelves: To be the <hi>Firſt,</hi> we muſt become <hi>laſt</hi> of all: To be <hi>ſtrong,</hi> we muſt become <hi>weak:</hi> To be wiſe, we muſt become <hi>Fooles:</hi> To ſubdue our <hi>enemies,</hi> we muſt <hi>love</hi> them: To <hi>ſave</hi> our <hi>Lives,</hi> we muſt <hi>lose</hi> them, with many ſuch like. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112525:5"/>I ſay is it, but becauſe we are now to <hi>worke out our ſalvation</hi> by <hi>Self-deniall;</hi> that is, by ſuch a way as <hi>pulls</hi> downe our <hi>high thoughts,</hi> that thwarts our <hi>perverſe Principles,</hi> that ſo <hi>God onely</hi> may be <hi>exalted,</hi> and as at firſt he was ſo, may at laſt become <hi>All in all?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.28.</note> Wherefore was it, that all the <hi>Precepts</hi> of the <hi>Decalogue</hi> were penn'd in a <hi>Negative</hi> forme, none in the <hi>Affirmative,</hi> but the <hi>two Middle ones,</hi> the more <hi>ſtrictly</hi> to oblige us to them, but becauſe they were <hi>calculated</hi> for our <hi>Lapſt eſtate?</hi> For hereby God taught us, that our <hi>Obedience</hi> to it now was to proceed (not as formerly:) firſt <hi>via remotionis,</hi> then <hi>via poſitionis:</hi> Firſt by way of the <hi>Removall</hi> of <hi>Self-love,</hi> before it could proceed to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of <hi>works of Love:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſaline 34.14.</note> firſt by <hi>flying</hi> that which is <hi>evill,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can come to <hi>doe</hi> that which is <hi>good.</hi> Whereupon we may well <hi>conjecture</hi> that, had <hi>Adam</hi> perſevered <hi>Innocent,</hi> and the <hi>Morall Law</hi> then been <hi>written,</hi> as it was ſince, all its <hi>Precepts</hi> had beene penn'd in the <hi>Affirmative.</hi> Does not <hi>Eſay</hi> tell us, <hi>Chap.</hi> 27. <hi>Ver.</hi> 9. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>This is all the fruit, to take away our ſinne?</hi> If then no <hi>ſinne,</hi> but proceeds out of <hi>Self-love,</hi> as is moſt certaine, and ſo no <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> to ſupplant it, but proceeds from <hi>ſelf-denyall,</hi> then is this <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> the onely <hi>fruit</hi> of our <hi>Religion.</hi> And ſo much appeares in the words next following in that place: for how does he meane our <hi>ſinnes</hi> ſhould be <hi>taken away,</hi> but when even the Holieſt <hi>ſtones of the Altar ſhould become as Chalke-ſtones</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>pulverizated</hi> or beaten aſunder; that is, by this <hi>Vertue</hi> of <hi>Self-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all analyz'd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth 7.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or reduc't to <hi>Atomes?</hi> Our <hi>Saviour</hi> too, much to the ſame purpoſe, tells us, <hi>This is all</hi> the fruit <hi>of the Law and the Prophets,</hi> what? <hi>Self-denyall?</hi> no, but <hi>one branch</hi> of it, <hi>Equanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to doe as we would be done to.</hi> If that <hi>Vertue</hi> then were the <hi>Summe</hi> of the <hi>whole Old Teſt.</hi> what may wee thinke of this <hi>Precept</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> that goes farre beyond it, but that it is the <hi>Summe</hi> alſo of the <hi>New?</hi> And ſure our <hi>Fore-fathers</hi> were <hi>all</hi> of the ſame Opinion, as appeares by the <hi>Primitive, Conſtant, Neceſſary Forme</hi> of <hi>Baptiſme;</hi> wherein <hi>we ſtipulate</hi> with God, to <hi>Deny</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Devill;</hi> and that wee may doe ſo, <hi>manfully to fight under the Croſſe,</hi> which is, <hi>Chriſts Banner, wherein to continue Chriſts faithfull Souldiers, and Servants to our lives end.</hi> So that as long as we live in the <hi>Church Militant,</hi> and that is even untill we arrive unto the <hi>Church Triumphant,</hi> ſo long muſt we be <hi>Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers exercis'd</hi> in this ſpirituall <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>ſelf-denyall,</hi> and the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112525:5"/>
               <hi>Croſſe.</hi> If then this be to be <hi>Baptiz'd into,</hi> &amp; <hi>conformed unto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.3. Phil. 3.10, 11, 12, 14.</note> 
               <hi>the death of Chriſt;</hi> if it be to <hi>arrive unto the Reſurrection of the Dead,</hi> as it, no queſtion, is<note n="*" place="margin">Compare that place with <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> 6.3, 4, 5, 6 verſes, and it will appeare plainly; Beſides the word there <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeems to relate to the Ancient manner of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing in hot climats where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the party baptized roſe againe out of the water, as if from the Dead. Rom. 15.3.</note>, then this is the <hi>Prize of the High calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> that <hi>Marke</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> did, and every <hi>true Chriſtian</hi> ought, to <hi>propound</hi> unto himſelfe in all his Actions.</p>
            <p>But let us not thus reſt in <hi>Generalls,</hi> but deſcend to more <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</hi> We hold that the <hi>Summe</hi> of the whole both <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpel</hi> is comprehended in thoſe three <hi>Theologicall Vertues Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi> Now let us ſee what <hi>dependance</hi> each of theſe have on <hi>Self-denyall.</hi> Firſt, for <hi>Faith,</hi> the moſt <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall Vertue</hi> of them, 'tis plaine, it is imply'd in this <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Precept</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> by the ſame reaſon that our <hi>Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitours</hi> ſay, the <hi>Affirmative Precepts</hi> are imply'd in the <hi>Negatives of the Decalogue.</hi> 'Tis true; to <hi>Deny our ſelves</hi> is <hi>formally</hi> an <hi>Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> action, but <hi>materially</hi> 'tis a <hi>Negative,</hi> it being no more but this, <hi>not to aſſent unto our ſelves.</hi> Hee then that, by <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> would raiſe an <hi>Affirmative</hi> thereunto, muſt acknowledge it to be no other but this, to <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Adbere unto God.</hi> Now what elſe is this but <hi>Faith,</hi> which is no other but an <hi>Affiance plac't in God,</hi> whether it be by a <hi>ſimple Aſſent of the Minde onely,</hi> which is <hi>Faith ſtrictly</hi> taken; or by an <hi>Adberence alſo of the Will and Affections,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 15.6.</note> which is <hi>Faith truely Juſtifying and Evangelicall?</hi> This was that <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> when,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.18.</note> 
               <hi>not conſidering his owne and Sarah's ineptitude to be Parents, he had an immoveable reſpect unto the Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of God's Promiſe:</hi> And that <hi>Faith</hi> I'm ſure, was <hi>Juſtifying.</hi> This was that <hi>Faith,</hi> by reaſon of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Galar. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>Hee liv'd not, but Chriſt liv'd in him, and the life that be liv'd was by the Faith of the Son of God.</hi> So that, to preach this <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall</hi> is, not to preach up the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Workes</hi> again, but, cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, to preach the <hi>Goſpel</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>purely,</hi> and the <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Faith.</hi> For, beſides that our <hi>Saviour</hi> urg'd this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> never any more, and yet ſure was no Miniſter of the <hi>Law, as 'tis oppoſed to the Goſpel:</hi> The <hi>Jewes,</hi> by the <hi>Law of Workes,</hi> ſought to <hi>eſtabliſh their owne Righteouſneſſe, by their owne Strength, to their owne Glory,</hi> all which are utterly inconſiſtent with <hi>Self-denyall:</hi> Whereas we <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> by the <hi>Law of Faith, eſtabliſh,</hi> not our <hi>own,</hi> but <hi>God's Righteouſneſſe;</hi> not by our own, but <hi>by God's Strength;</hi> not to our <hi>owne,</hi> but <hi>to God's Glory.</hi> It muſt needs bee ſo where
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112525:6"/>
               <hi>Self-denyall</hi> takes place: it cannot be ſo, where it does not. We need no more proofe for the matter then that alone <hi>Text</hi> of St. <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 3.10. where the Apoſtle, having <hi>firſt Denyed his owne Righteouſneſſe,</hi> to wit, that of the <hi>Law,</hi> plainly deſcribes <hi>the Righteouſneſſe of God by Chriſt upon Faith, to bee a Righteouſneſſe</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>of Knowing Chriſt, and the Power of His Reſurrection, and the Fellowſhip of His ſufferings, and to be conform'd to Him in His Death.</hi> Now if this <hi>Conformity</hi> be the <hi>Fellowſhip of His Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,</hi> and that <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> be the <hi>Power of His Reſurrection,</hi> and that <hi>Power</hi> be the <hi>Experimentall Knowledge of Chriſt,</hi> to wit, <hi>Crucified within us,</hi> (all which is cleare) what elſe is that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi> and conſequently <hi>the Righteouſneſſe of Faith,</hi> but the <hi>Denyall of our ſelves,</hi> being a <hi>Conformity</hi> to that <hi>act</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> wherein Hee <hi>Deny'd Himſelfe moſt perfectly?</hi> Thus much for <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now for <hi>Hope,</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> of the <hi>Three Theologicall Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> there is more doubt of that indeed, whether that may be <hi>reconciled</hi> with this <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall;</hi> ſince that, having <hi>our owne Good</hi> for its <hi>Object,</hi> ſeemes to be a <hi>Self-ſeeking</hi> act procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>onely</hi> out of <hi>Self-love.</hi> But yet upon more ſerious examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the matter, we ſhall ſee, it will not prove ſo. For though <hi>Hope</hi> (ſuch onely I meane as is <hi>truely Chriſtian</hi>) have <hi>Good alone</hi> for its <hi>Object,</hi> and be a <hi>Self-ſeeking</hi> act <hi>(in effect)</hi> yet, is not built on <hi>Self-love,</hi> but wholly on <hi>Self-denyall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To cleare this ſeeming <hi>Paradox</hi> the better, we muſt lay down <hi>Three Grounds,</hi> all of them, as we conceive undenyable. Firſt, that <hi>God alone is good,</hi> as our <hi>Saviour</hi> plainly tells us, and ſo the <hi>onely Object</hi> of our <hi>Hope.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 19.17.</note> Secondly, that all <hi>love of our ſelves</hi> is not <hi>vitious:</hi> for certainly Hee that bids us <hi>love our Neighbour as our ſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. verſ. 19.</note> bids us <hi>love our ſelves</hi> in ſome ſort, otherwiſe that could not be the <hi>Rule</hi> of our <hi>love to our Neighbours,</hi> ſince wee cannot make a <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Nothing.</hi> Laſtly, that <hi>that love of our ſelves,</hi> which is <hi>terminated</hi> in our <hi>ſelves,</hi> is onely <hi>vitious,</hi> as ſuppoſing <hi>our ſelves,</hi> and not <hi>God alone,</hi> to bee <hi>Good;</hi> but that which <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes</hi> from, and may bee <hi>reſolved</hi> into, <hi>God,</hi> that <hi>onely</hi> is <hi>lawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now hence we argue thus; That <hi>Hope</hi> which aimes onely at the <hi>Fruition of God,</hi> and yet at <hi>our owne good,</hi> but onely in and from Him, muſt needs be both a <hi>Self-ſeeking</hi> act, and yet an <hi>act of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112525:6"/>Self-denyall,</hi> (for it <hi>ſeeks our good,</hi> though not <hi>as it is ours.</hi>) But ſuch is <hi>true Chriſtian Hope,</hi> as appeares from thoſe <hi>Three Grounds,</hi> I laid; <hi>Ergo.</hi> But, that this may be the more rightly underſtood, we muſt obſerve; ſuch <hi>Hope</hi> is a <hi>Self-denying act properly,</hi> and <hi>directly,</hi> but a <hi>Selfe-ſeeking</hi> act onely <hi>improperly</hi> and <hi>at ſecond hand;</hi> for it ſuppoſes <hi>our good</hi> to be <hi>finis rei,</hi> not <hi>agentis;</hi> not <hi>our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne,</hi> but <hi>our Felicity.</hi> Did it in every ſenſe <hi>Deny our ſelves,</hi> that is, no way <hi>conduce</hi> to <hi>our Good,</hi> it could not be ſo much as <hi>Hope:</hi> On the other ſide, Did it <hi>wholly ſeek our ſelves,</hi> and not <hi>deny our ſelves,</hi> it could not but be <hi>vitious,</hi> as appeares from the laſt <hi>ground;</hi> But thus <hi>coupling</hi> both theſe together, it deſervedly becoms the <hi>Second</hi> of thoſe <hi>Three Grand Theologicall Vertues,</hi> I ſpake of.</p>
            <p>By reaſon of this, ſure, it was, that <hi>God</hi> promiſed <hi>Abraham, the Faithfull: He would be his exceeding great Reward.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 15.1. Pſal. 71.5.</note> That <hi>David</hi> ſayes of <hi>God, Thou art my very Hope, ô Lord God; Thou art my Truſt even from my youth.</hi> And in another place, <hi>Whom have I in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but thee? and there is none upon earth that I deſire beſides thee</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">See a Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Texts for this, Pſal. 2.12. &amp; 34.10. &amp; 125.1. Prov. 16 20. Eſay 30.18. Jer. 17.7. &amp;c.</note>. And that we may not think the <hi>Goſpel</hi> behinde hand with the <hi>Law</hi> in this matter, becauſe it <hi>promiſes</hi> to us the <hi>Life Eternall,</hi> our <hi>Saviour,</hi> ſpeaking to &amp; of His <hi>Father,</hi> plainly tells us,<note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 17.3.</note> 
               <hi>This is Life Eternall, to know Thee, the onely true God, and whom Thou haſt ſent, Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Now the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, who they are alone that <hi>know God</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">So Jer. 22.16 And ſuch is God's Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of us, <hi>Gen</hi> 22.12. Matth. 7.23. Gen. 3.9 1 Joh. 5.3.</note>, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 8.3. <hi>If any one,</hi> ſayes hee, <hi>Love God, He,</hi> that is, <hi>God, is knowne of him.</hi> And ſo does St. <hi>John</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.3. <hi>In this,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>we know, we know Him, if we keep his Commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any one doubt, how this <hi>Hope</hi> can commend any <hi>Meanes</hi> to us in <hi>this life,</hi> proportionable to that <hi>end,</hi> the <hi>Fruition of God Almighty,</hi> let him conſider thoſe <hi>latter words</hi> of our Saviour's, That <hi>Eternall Life</hi> was, not onely to <hi>know God,</hi> but alſo, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to that,<note n="c" place="margin">Joh 14.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>to know, Him whom He had ſent, Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> So then, the way to <hi>enjoy God</hi> is to <hi>enjoy Chriſt, the bright ſplendour of His Glorie, and Character of His Perſon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> as the way for us to <hi>partake</hi> of the Sunne, is, to <hi>partake</hi> of his <hi>Rayes</hi> and <hi>Brightneſſe.</hi> But then what is it for us to <hi>know, Chriſt</hi> now, ſo that we may <hi>enjoy Him?</hi> Is it to <hi>know Chriſt onely in His Perſon?</hi> No, but <hi>alſo in His Example.</hi> For His <hi>Perſon</hi> is in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and ſo muſt be till the <hi>Laſt day,</hi> but His <hi>Example He hath left behinde Him for us.</hi> Many en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd His <hi>Corporeall Preſence</hi> upon Earth,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.21.</note> that are now in <hi>Eternall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112525:7"/>chains</hi> with the <hi>Devills;</hi> therefore <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> plainly tells us, <hi>If he did know Chriſt after the Fleſh, henceforward he knew Him ſo no more,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16. <hi>For,</hi> ſayes hee, <hi>every one that is in Chriſt is a New Creature.</hi> Hence it was, that he ſayes in another place,<note n="a" place="margin">Phil. 1.21</note> 
               <hi>To me to live is Chriſt.</hi> How ſo? why, becauſe<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>he liv'd not, but Chriſt liv'd in him:</hi> that is, he expreſt in <hi>his life</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>the Life and Dying,</hi> or the <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of the Life and Death, of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> Theſe <hi>Vertues</hi> then let us <hi>embrace</hi> and <hi>enjoy</hi> here, in order to the <hi>Fruition of God;</hi> And, that we may truely doe ſo, let it not be for their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile,</hi> if it be Poſſible, whatſoever we fancie it to be, but their <hi>Honeſtum</hi> onely: As for their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile</hi> feare it not, it will follow.</p>
            <p>Conſonant to this, <hi>the Wiſe-man</hi> affirmes, that not onely a <hi>Back-ſlider in heart ſhall be fill'd with his owne wayes,</hi> but alſo that a <hi>Good man ſhall be ſatisfied from himſelfe, Prov.</hi> 14.14. Conſonant to this,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.3, &amp;c.</note> our <hi>Saviour</hi> pronounces all his <hi>Beatitudes,</hi> yea in the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tenſe,</hi> on thoſe, who, but for that of <hi>God and Godlineſſe</hi> that is in them,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.19.</note> are the <hi>pittifulleſt men in the World.</hi> Conſonant to this too <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> affirmes, out of the <hi>Prophet;</hi> That <hi>neither eye hath ſeen, nor eare hath heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man to conceive, what God ha's prepar'd</hi> (and that in this life) <hi>for them that love him,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. This now is that <hi>Hope that maketh not aſhamed</hi> (of any <hi>Croſſes</hi>) <hi>becauſe of the love of God ſhed abroad in our hearts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.5.</note> This is that <hi>Hope</hi> whereby wee muſt be <hi>ſav'd:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.24.</note> And, if ye will receive it; This is that <hi>Spirituall,</hi> that <hi>better Hope of the Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.19.</note> 
               <hi>by the bringing in of which it leads us to Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> whereas the <hi>Carnall Hope</hi> of the <hi>Law could perfect nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus at length I have made appeare, how <hi>true Chriſtian Hope</hi> is ſo farre from being <hi>evacuated,</hi> 'tis onely <hi>ſolidly eſtabliſht,</hi> by this <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall.</hi> As for all <hi>ſenſuall Hope,</hi> let it goe and periſh for, what it is, a meere <hi>Cheat,</hi> and <hi>Lye,</hi> no better, for the <hi>Good,</hi> it aimes at is juſt like <hi>Adam's forbidden fruit,</hi> and indeed was <hi>repreſented</hi> by it, which in <hi>appearance</hi> promiſed the <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Good,</hi> but in <hi>effect</hi> perform'd nothing but the <hi>Experience</hi> of <hi>Evill.</hi> But as for thoſe that embrace the <hi>Commandements</hi> of God, onely out of <hi>Hope</hi> of the <hi>Promiſed Reward,</hi> as the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> condeſcending to our <hi>Infirmities,</hi> does encourage them ſo, I dare not by any meanes preſume to cenſure them. We condemne not <hi>Attrition,</hi> though wee commend <hi>Contrition</hi> above it; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe we condemne them that embrace <hi>Vertue</hi> for its <hi>Reward,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:112525:7"/>though deſervedly we commend them more highly, that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it <hi>for it ſelfe.</hi> With <hi>the Prophet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 4.10. Matth. 12.20.</note> we muſt <hi>not deſpiſe the day of ſmall things;</hi> and, with our Saviour, <hi>not breake the bruiſed reede, nor quench the ſmoaking flaxe.</hi> But yet theſe are to be admoniſht, that <hi>ſuch Hope</hi> is rather <hi>Legall</hi> then <hi>Evangelicall,</hi> therefore that they are not to <hi>reſt</hi> ſtill in their <hi>Minority,</hi> but to grow on to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Perfection;</hi> it being a ſhame to a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> not to aſpire to that, which even the <hi>Heathen</hi> by their <hi>ſpeculative Learning</hi> could deſcry, when one of them ſayes, <hi>Oderunt peccare Boni virtutis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> I have been the larger in this <hi>Point,</hi> leſt this <hi>Precept</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall</hi> ſhould ſeeme to want that maine <hi>Engine</hi> of <hi>Obedience Hope of a Reward.</hi> Indeed, this ſeemes to be the <hi>Reaſon</hi> why our <hi>Saviour</hi> no ſooner had delivered this <hi>Precept,</hi> with its <hi>Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants,</hi> but ſtraight in the <hi>next Verſe</hi> He prevents this maine <hi>Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> againſt it, ſaying, <hi>He that will ſave his life ſhall loſe it;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 25.</note> 
               <hi>but he that will loſe his life for my ſake, ſhall ſave it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to make amends in ſpeaking more briefly of the <hi>Third Theologicall Vertue,</hi> and that is, <hi>Love</hi> or <hi>Charity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the ſixth point below to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end.</note> That this <hi>Vertue</hi> is totally built on <hi>Selfe-denyall,</hi> if not the very <hi>ſame</hi> with it, appeares plainly from the <hi>Naturall effect</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> in <hi>Generall,</hi> which is to <hi>reſigne</hi> up its <hi>proper Intereſt,</hi> and place it in <hi>another:</hi> Hence we ſay, <hi>Animus eſt ubi amat, non ubi animat;</hi> The <hi>minde</hi> is where it <hi>loves,</hi> not where it <hi>lives.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.4 John 3.16.</note> Hence <hi>Love</hi> is called <hi>vinculum unionis,</hi> and to that <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> alludes, when he calls it the <hi>Bond of Perfectneſſe. God ſo loved the world,</hi> ſayes our Saviour, that <hi>Hee gave His onely begotten Son for us.</hi> He, as it were, <hi>gave up His Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in His Son,</hi> to procure an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with us. In another place, He ſayes, <hi>Greater love then this ha's no man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 15.13.</note> 
               <hi>then to lay down his life for his friends.</hi> May we not ſay, <hi>Greater Selfe-denyall then this no man can ſhew?</hi> ſurely, we may; for it appeares by that verſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing our Text, that <hi>to loſe ones life</hi> is one of the <hi>greateſt</hi> acts of <hi>Selfe-denyall.</hi> This then is the great commendation of <hi>Selfe-denyall,</hi> that it is, not <hi>Faith alone,</hi> nor <hi>Hope alone,</hi> but <hi>the love of God, the Bond of them;</hi> That <hi>Love</hi> of which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> gives ſo vaſt commendations, amongſt which one is, that <hi>it ſeekes not its own;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Corin. 13.5. Galat. 5.6.</note> That <hi>Love</hi> by means whereof <hi>Faith</hi> producing <hi>its works</hi> becomes <hi>to tum Chriſtiani,</hi> the <hi>Totall of a Chriſtians Dutie.</hi> By this meanes it is, that <hi>Love</hi> climbes up even into <hi>Heaven</hi> it ſelfe; whereas <hi>Faith,</hi> that, ſhall ceaſe, when once we come to <hi>Viſion; Hope,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:112525:8"/>that, ſhall be explete, when once we come to <hi>Fruition:</hi> But <hi>Self-denying Love is ſtrong as Death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant 8.6.</note> that therefore ſhall be <hi>perfected,</hi> not aboliſhed, when once we come to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> Then when our <hi>corrupt ſelves</hi> ſhall bee ſwallow'd up of <hi>Perfection,</hi> and <hi>God ſhall be All in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope, by this time it appeares fully of what <hi>Generall</hi> impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance <hi>this Vertue</hi> is to the <hi>whole Body of Theologie,</hi> all thoſe <hi>Three Theologicall Vertues</hi> being ſo immediately founded on it. Other <hi>Arguments</hi> might be us'd to this purpoſe: I ſhall onely produce one more, as <hi>irrefragable,</hi> as 'tis <hi>briefe,</hi> out of the <hi>Apoſtle's</hi> words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. <hi>I determined,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>to know nothing but Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and Him crucified in you;</hi> now when is <hi>Chriſt crucified in us,</hi> but when <hi>we</hi> are <hi>crucified to the World, the Fleſh, and the Devill, in conformity unto Him?</hi> Thus does St. <hi>Peter</hi> expound it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Chriſt therefore ſuffering for us in the fleſh, be yee alſo arm'd with the ſame minde: for he that ſuffers in the fleſh ha's ceaſt from ſinne.</hi> By this now it appeares,, that <hi>Selfe-denyall</hi> is not onely the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num,</hi> but alſo the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicum neceſſarium</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> which had the <hi>Corinthians</hi> but learnt, <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd <hi>no more</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>Here perhaps you will aske me. But does not our Saviour, even <hi>in this Text</hi> we entreat of, <hi>require more</hi> then ſo of us, to wit, that <hi>We ſhould take up our Croſſe,</hi> and <hi>that we ſhould follow his Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?</hi> Does he not uſher in <hi>theſe</hi> with the very ſame <hi>Siquis,</hi> Hee does that <hi>Precept of Self-denyall?</hi> 'tis plaine, he does. Why, then we may well conclude, that this <hi>Precept</hi> of <hi>Selfe-denyall</hi> ha's no <hi>preheminence</hi> above the others. No; the very <hi>poſiture</hi> of it in the <hi>firſt place,</hi> proves the contrary, and gives it the <hi>preheminence</hi> above them. For hereby, we being <hi>abſolutely</hi> in the <hi>firſt place</hi> obliged to that, whatſoever <hi>obligation</hi> the other faſten on us, either it muſt be <hi>Nothing</hi> and <hi>Void,</hi> if it <hi>contradict</hi> the firſt; or, if it doe not, but <hi>make for it,</hi> it muſt be ſubſervient to it. Now who ſees not that the <hi>two following Precepts</hi> are ſo farre from <hi>contradicting</hi> the firſt, that they <hi>make exceedingly for it?</hi> For firſt; if <hi>Self-denyall</hi> bee a <hi>Vertue</hi> of ſuch <hi>Generall</hi> importance, as we have prov'd, it cannot be, though a <hi>reflext act</hi> in it ſelfe yet, a meere <hi>immanent act,</hi> in its conſequence; it muſt be <hi>perfected</hi> without, though it be <hi>begun</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our ſelves; it muſt be <hi>expreſt</hi> and <hi>held forth</hi> to others; partly, to ſhew the <hi>ſincerity</hi> thereof to others:<note place="margin">Mat. 5.10.</note> that the <hi>Glory thereof
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112525:8"/>may be rendred to God our Father, which is in Heaven.</hi> Now what fitter <hi>expedient</hi> could poſſibly bee found to doe this, then the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> whereby the world is <hi>crucified to our ſelves,</hi> and <hi>our ſelves unto the World:</hi> whereby the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>Old Man,</hi> is <hi>crucified</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us? For, <hi>as our Saviour</hi> by His <hi>Croſſe was lifted up,</hi> like the <hi>Brazen Serpent in the Wilderneſſe,</hi> ſo our <hi>Selfe-denyall</hi> is, as it were, <hi>lifted up</hi> by that <hi>Croſſe</hi> we are to <hi>take up,</hi> and made <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is this <hi>Croſſe</hi> an <hi>Evidence</hi> onely of our <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a <hi>Meane</hi> to <hi>helpe</hi> us thereunto. Certainly, every <hi>Croſſe</hi> muſt be <hi>contrary</hi> to our <hi>ſelves,</hi> otherwiſe 'tis not a <hi>Croſſe;</hi> and as certain it is, our <hi>Self-denyall</hi> muſt be perform'd by the <hi>helpe of Contraries;</hi> No fitter <hi>Meane</hi> then can be imagin'd, to <hi>helpe</hi> it forward, then the <hi>Croſſe.</hi> For, if, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and all <hi>Phyſitians</hi> tell us, all <hi>Cures</hi> muſt be perform'd by <hi>Contraries,</hi> we may very aptly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Selfe-love</hi> to the <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> or <hi>Humour,</hi> that is to be <hi>purged out</hi> of us: the <hi>Croſſe</hi> to that <hi>Phyſick</hi> which muſt helpe to doe it; and <hi>Selfe-denyall</hi> to that <hi>expulſive Faculty,</hi> wherewith the <hi>Grace</hi> of God endues us.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe other words, <hi>and follow Me,</hi> they alſo have a plaine reference to this <hi>Precept</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall;</hi> as being not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our Saviour's <hi>Grant,</hi> wherein He gives <hi>full power, licence and authority</hi> to <hi>all</hi> that ſhall <hi>come</hi> to <hi>Him,</hi> with thoſe <hi>two precedent Qualifications,</hi> to become His <hi>Followers</hi> and <hi>Diſciples,</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> but alſo a <hi>Third Precept,</hi> enjoyning us, with <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy</hi> and <hi>Perſeverance,</hi> to imitate the <hi>Perfecteſt Pattern of Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall</hi> in our Saviours <hi>owne example,</hi> who, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.3.</note> 
               <hi>did not pleaſe,</hi> that is, <hi>Deny'd himſelfe.</hi> Whereas therefore, wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd the <hi>Croſſe</hi> to that <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> that muſt cure us of <hi>Self-love,</hi> we may compare this <hi>Precept</hi> to that <hi>Rule of Dyet,</hi> which muſt prevent our <hi>Relapſing.</hi> So then, notwithſtanding what can be alledg'd out of the words, <hi>Self-denyall</hi> muſt ſtill have the <hi>prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet this is not enough: for here ſome perhaps will flie to <hi>Argument,</hi> and wonder how all our <hi>Religion</hi> ſhould be built on <hi>Self-denyall.</hi> What? All of it <hi>Anaſceuaſticall,</hi> no <hi>Cataſceuaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> part thereof? All tending to <hi>Mortification,</hi> no part to <hi>Vivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication?</hi> All to <hi>doffe the Old Man,</hi> none <hi>doe on the New?</hi> I looke this ſhould be caſt in my way, by thoſe <hi>qui ad pauca reſpiciunt.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:112525:9"/>But 'tis nothing; Theſe <hi>Diſtinctions</hi> are but of divers <hi>Notions.</hi> not of divers <hi>Things:</hi> Our <hi>Deeds of Mortification</hi> are at once <hi>Deeds of Vivification:</hi> Our <hi>putting off the Old Man</hi> cannot bee without <hi>putting on the New:</hi> Our <hi>Averſion</hi> from the <hi>Creature,</hi> if <hi>regular</hi> and <hi>uniforme,</hi> is our <hi>Converſion</hi> unto <hi>God.</hi> It muſt needs be ſo, if <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Creature</hi> be (as to us) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> without any <hi>Meane</hi> imaginable betwixt them: for then he that <hi>forſakes</hi> the <hi>Creature</hi> muſt needs <hi>betake</hi> himſelfe to <hi>God:</hi> even as he that <hi>forſakes the Earth</hi> muſt needs <hi>goe towards Heaven.</hi> As for this <hi>preſent World,</hi> it is no other but our <hi>Exile,</hi> becauſe our <hi>Enemies</hi> are <hi>Maſters</hi> of it: Our <hi>Life</hi> is our <hi>Pilgrimage,</hi> our <hi>Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: Heaven,</hi> that is our <hi>Countrey;</hi> and our <hi>Religion</hi> is our <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> from the one to the other. Now this <hi>Motion</hi> you may terme as you pleaſe, according to its ſeverall <hi>Intentions,</hi> either a <hi>Flight</hi> from our <hi>Selves,</hi> or a <hi>Journey</hi> unto <hi>God;</hi> either <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> or <hi>Charity;</hi> either <hi>Hatred</hi> of the <hi>Creature,</hi> or <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> it matters not much which of them: The <hi>Motion</hi> is ſtill the ſame, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever <hi>Name</hi> you give it. But, if you <hi>joyne</hi> both theſe together, as our Saviour <hi>does</hi> in the next verſe, and ſtile this <hi>Motion Selfe-denyall for the Love of God,</hi> which is no other, but our <hi>Self-denyall here,</hi> in <hi>Precept,</hi> then all <hi>Objection</hi> is remov'd, and you have a compleat <hi>Epitome</hi> of <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To illuſtrate this ſomewhat further. We muſt conſider; Our <hi>Vertues</hi> (now under the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> not of <hi>Workes</hi>) are not to be lookt upon as Actions of men in <hi>perfect Health</hi> ſo, as they were in <hi>Paradiſe:</hi> but onely as on the way of <hi>Recovery,</hi> that is, mixt with much <hi>feebleneſſe</hi> and <hi>imperfection.</hi> As long as wee live here, <hi>the Fleſh does luſt againſt the Spirit, and the Spirit againſt the Fleſh: by reaſon of which contrariety wee doe not the things we would,</hi> as <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> tells us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. Therefore, as <hi>Plato</hi> conceiv'd of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> it was all but <hi>Memory,</hi> ſo, muſt we of our <hi>preſent Righteouſneſſe</hi> and <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> that 'tis all but <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then will not this make much for the <hi>diſparagement</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> though for the <hi>advancement</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> that our <hi>beſt Eſtate</hi> under it is but <hi>Recovery,</hi> wheras y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi> in <hi>Innocency</hi> was of <hi>perfect Health?</hi> No, it will not: For though our <hi>Vertues</hi> now conſider'd in <hi>Arithmeticall Proportion</hi> be <hi>inferiour</hi> to <hi>Adam's,</hi> yet conſider'd in their <hi>Geometricall Proportion,</hi> with reference to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112525:9"/>
               <hi>Naturall aukneſſe</hi> and <hi>weakneſſe of the Workman,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty</hi> of the <hi>Worke,</hi> thus, they are <hi>Superiour,</hi> and aske a greater meaſure of <hi>Grace</hi> to performe them. Briefely; compare our <hi>Workes</hi> with his, and they are <hi>Inferiour:</hi> compare our <hi>Working</hi> with his, and it is <hi>Superiour.</hi> We perceive the Sunnes heat farre <hi>more intenſe</hi> in the <hi>Summer,</hi> then in the <hi>Spring,</hi> and yet in the <hi>Spring-time</hi> it is in its <hi>Aſcent</hi> and acts <hi>more ſtrongly.</hi> What's the reaſon of it? One maine one ſeemes to be, the <hi>Winter's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Cold,</hi> which is his taske to <hi>Maſter:</hi> ſo <hi>Adam's Vertues</hi> in <hi>Innocency</hi> would have appear'd more <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>glorious,</hi> then <hi>ours</hi> doe <hi>now or can doe;</hi> and yet wee have a <hi>greater meaſure</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> by Chriſt's <hi>Redemption,</hi> then <hi>Adam</hi> had by <hi>Creation.</hi> What's the reaſon of it? Surely no other reaſon can be given but this, We have <hi>Self-love</hi> and <hi>Sin</hi> to <hi>maſter</hi> in us; <hi>Adam</hi> had not: Our <hi>Grace</hi> therefore acts more <hi>vigorouſly,</hi> though it be not ſo <hi>ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi> and ſo <hi>ours</hi> ha's more of <hi>Vertue, Adam's</hi> more of <hi>Felicity</hi> in it. <hi>Therapeuticall Phyſick</hi> is both more <hi>Difficult</hi> and more <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,</hi> then <hi>Prophylacticall;</hi> 'Tis farre more hard to <hi>recover</hi> our <hi>Health,</hi> then to <hi>preſerve</hi> it; Harder to <hi>recover</hi> the <hi>top</hi> of a <hi>Hill,</hi> as we are <hi>deſcending,</hi> then being <hi>at the top</hi> to keep our <hi>Station;</hi> ſo a farre greater meaſure of <hi>Grace</hi> is requir'd to <hi>recover</hi> our <hi>loſt eſtate,</hi> then was at firſt to have <hi>retain'd</hi> it. No <hi>Vertue</hi> ſhines ſo <hi>gloriouſly,</hi> as that which <hi>grapples</hi> with moſt <hi>Difficulty:</hi> No <hi>Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> is ſo <hi>Triumphant,</hi> as <hi>his</hi> whoſe <hi>Enemy</hi> was moſt <hi>Puiſsant;</hi> If then the <hi>Miniſtration of the Law</hi> had been <hi>glorious</hi> in <hi>Adam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering,</hi> it was <hi>Nothing</hi> to the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which excells it in <hi>our Recovering.</hi> For, though the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpel,</hi> both, drive at <hi>one and the ſame marke,</hi> yet, does the <hi>Goſpel</hi> by its <hi>Method</hi> attain that, which the <hi>Law</hi> could not <hi>retaine</hi> at firſt, nor <hi>re-attaine</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards by its <hi>Method,</hi> to wit, our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with God.</hi> According<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therefore the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> are more <hi>Glorious:</hi> The <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel promiſes a heavenly Paradiſe,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> but an <hi>Earthly one;</hi> The <hi>Goſpel promiſes</hi> it <hi>Eternally,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> but <hi>Temporally.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.40.</note> Theſe are thoſe <hi>better things,</hi> without which the <hi>Law</hi> could not be <hi>perfected,</hi> nor lead us to <hi>Perfection.</hi> And ſuch indeed it became the <hi>Son of God</hi> to beſtow, who, it's believ'd, never <hi>reſtor'd</hi> any to their former <hi>health</hi> and <hi>Limbes,</hi> but with far greater <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>Vivacity.</hi> We <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude</hi> then, notwithſtanding what ha's been alledg'd, <hi>Self-denyall</hi> is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Breviate</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:112525:10"/>
            <p>What <hi>Praiſe</hi> then in former time was given to <hi>Law-givers</hi> for the <hi>Abridgement</hi> of their <hi>Lawes,</hi> the ſame is moſt juſtly due to our <hi>Saviour</hi> for His <hi>Abridgement</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in this one <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall.</hi> For, if we eſteeme the ſumme of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Law,</hi> in thoſe <hi>Ten Words</hi> of the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> a moſt excellent <hi>Compendium,</hi> this muſt needs be more admirable, that ha's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted the <hi>whole</hi> both <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpel</hi> into theſe few words, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thy ſelfe.</hi> We know, the <hi>Benefit</hi> of that was, that the <hi>Law</hi> might be written on the <hi>Phylacteries</hi> of their <hi>Hands,</hi> and the <hi>Frontlets</hi> between their <hi>Eyes,</hi> that ſo, whatſoever they did, whether <hi>eate, ſit, walke,</hi> or <hi>meditate,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> might ſtill be in their <hi>ſight,</hi> to keep them from all evill. And may not then grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Benefit</hi> be made of this ſhort <hi>Precept,</hi> which even by the <hi>fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is in ſome meaſure <hi>written</hi> in every ones, not <hi>Head</hi> alone and <hi>Hands,</hi> but <hi>Heart</hi> alſo, that he may doe it? Surely, if the <hi>Heathen</hi> thought their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, worthy to be written in <hi>Gold</hi> on the <hi>Doores</hi> of their <hi>Temples,</hi> with much better reaſon may we engrave this <hi>Precept</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in <hi>Golden Letters</hi> on the <hi>Porches</hi> of our <hi>Churches.</hi> Or if we like the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Rites</hi> better, as is reaſon; wee may make this <hi>Precept</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Phylactery</hi> of our <hi>Hearts;</hi> That whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſinne the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> or the <hi>Devill</hi> tempt us unto, whether it be the <hi>luſt</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> or the <hi>luſt</hi> of the <hi>Eyes,</hi> or the <hi>Pride</hi> of <hi>Life;</hi> whatſoever <hi>Temptation</hi> God <hi>proves</hi> us with, to part with our <hi>Goods, Friends, Gifts of Body</hi> or <hi>Minde,</hi> yea our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> it ſelfe, we may reſiſt and overcome them all by this alone <hi>Delphick Sword</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, if we ſhall doe ſo, marke the <hi>Benefit</hi> will accrue to us thereby: This alone <hi>Precept,</hi> conſtantly attended to, will car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on the <hi>Generall Worke</hi> of our <hi>Regeneration</hi> in ſo <hi>Naturall</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niforme</hi> a <hi>Method,</hi> as no other <hi>Precept</hi> whatſoever can doe. The <hi>Workes</hi> of <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> differ mainly in this <hi>Point;</hi> that <hi>Nature</hi> working from an <hi>Internall Principle,</hi> carryes on its <hi>work uniformly,</hi> in all parts at once, in our <hi>Nouriſhment</hi> and <hi>Augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation:</hi> whereas <hi>Art,</hi> working from an <hi>Externall Principle,</hi> as we ſee in the <hi>Statuaries</hi> trade, is faine to <hi>frame</hi> one part <hi>after</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, untill at length the <hi>whole</hi> is finiſhed: Juſt ſo it is in the <hi>Forming</hi> of the <hi>New Creature</hi> in us; if our <hi>ſpirituall</hi> growth therein be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niforme,</hi> in all its <hi>Members</hi> alike, 'tis a figne it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112525:10"/>from this <hi>Internall Principle</hi> of the <hi>Divine Nature</hi> in us, whereby <hi>Denying</hi> and <hi>Forſaking our ſelves,</hi> we firmly <hi>depend</hi> on <hi>God:</hi> But if our <hi>Growth</hi> therein be <hi>Partiall,</hi> that is, if one <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of the <hi>New Creature</hi> in us runnes out into a <hi>Monſtrous</hi> exuberance, while <hi>many others</hi> fare the worſe for it, conſume, wither, and pine away to <hi>Nothing,</hi> 'tis a ſigne this <hi>Birth</hi> is, not the <hi>New Creature,</hi> but ſome <hi>New Monſter</hi> rais'd up in us, not by the <hi>Incorruptible ſeed</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> ſuch as this <hi>Precept</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall</hi> is, which is the firſt <hi>Principle</hi> our Saviour <hi>ſowes</hi> us with, but by I know not what <hi>Extrinſick Principle</hi> of that <hi>Art,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>Devill</hi> in an <hi>Angel of Light,</hi> ſeeks to frame his <hi>Image</hi> in us. If this may not be credited, the <hi>Event</hi> will prove it ſo: For obſerve it, if thoſe who have taken up their <hi>Religion,</hi> mov'd by ſome <hi>extrinſick Principle</hi> of <hi>Honour, Profit,</hi> or <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> when that <hi>Principle</hi> is remov'd, doe not ſuddenly make a <hi>Halt,</hi> and then turning <hi>faces about</hi> returne into their old <hi>Poſture;</hi> herein plainly proving that <hi>Maxime</hi> in <hi>Philoſophy</hi> true, <hi>Nullum violentum eſt permanens.</hi> But 'tis not ſo with thoſe that act out of this <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Principle</hi> we ſpeak of: for they taking their <hi>Religion</hi> from no <hi>Externall Accidents</hi> whatſoever, but meerely induc't by the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Native worth</hi> of it; marke it, if they will not <hi>ſuffer</hi> for it, and that, not out of <hi>ſpight</hi> &amp; <hi>ſtomach,</hi> but out of a true ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Patience,</hi> rather then they will forgoe it.</p>
            <p>Nor does this <hi>Vertue</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall</hi> contribute onely to the <hi>Duration</hi> of our <hi>Piety,</hi> but alſo to the very <hi>Eſſence</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of it. Other <hi>Vertues</hi> may ſuperinduce <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an empty, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent <hi>Vizour</hi> of <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> in our actions, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a true, ſubſtantiall, powerfull <hi>Forme</hi> they cannot. The reaſon of it is; Other <hi>Vertues</hi> not founded upon this, are not indeed, what they ſeeme, true, ſubſtantiall ſolid <hi>Vertues,</hi> but onely their <hi>Appearances,</hi> ſo that 'tis no marvaile, if they doe not contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to their actions what they never had in their Habi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s: But this <hi>Vertue</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall</hi> is the <hi>Subſtantiall Ingredient</hi> of all others, which as it <hi>enſtamps</hi> them with true <hi>Worth</hi> and <hi>Value,</hi> ſo <hi>infuſes Life</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> into them; it being,<note place="margin">Fortior eſt qui ſe quam qui fortiſſima vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Moenia. <hi>Horace. Rom. 1.16.</hi>
               </note> even in the <hi>Heathen</hi> mans account, the moſt <hi>Heroicall</hi> atchievement of <hi>Fortitude,</hi> to <hi>Overcome ones ſelfe.</hi> By this it is we truely ſhew the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to be the <hi>Power of God,</hi> that is, ſuch a <hi>Power</hi> as appeares, not in <hi>Sight,</hi> but by <hi>Faith;</hi> as conſiſts, not in our <hi>Arme of Fleſh</hi> but, in our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112525:11"/>owne <hi>weakneſſe;</hi> as makes, not for <hi>our owne,</hi> but for <hi>God's glory.</hi> Which <hi>Power,</hi> though to thoſe that walke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it ſeems to be <hi>Impotency, Folly,</hi> yea <hi>Madneſſe</hi> it ſelfe, yet is indeed to the <hi>Spirituall-ſighted man</hi> the <hi>Power of God,</hi> that is, by an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiſme,</hi> the moſt <hi>Excellent, mighty Power</hi> we can imagine.</p>
            <p>Upon the <hi>whole matter</hi> then; we may well affirme in that <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> of our Saviours, He that <hi>enters</hi> upon the <hi>Chriſtian profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> this way, (as our Saviour <hi>here</hi> calls upon <hi>every one</hi> to doe;) he, <hi>enters</hi> in by the <hi>Doore,</hi> and to him the <hi>Porter opens,</hi> he may goe in at <hi>liberty,</hi> and finde <hi>paſture;</hi> but hee that <hi>enters</hi> upon it <hi>elſe-where,</hi> as by <hi>being at many Sermons, long Prayer,</hi> or an <hi>ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded Zeale,</hi> he, <hi>clambers up elſewhere,</hi> he <hi>enters not</hi> by the <hi>Doore;</hi> and that with as manifeſt danger of his <hi>Ruine,</hi> as little hope of <hi>Proficiency.</hi> And accordingly, the <hi>Self-denying</hi> man, <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring</hi> the onely right way on his <hi>Religion,</hi> is ſo firme to it, that rather then forgoe it, he will forgoe his <hi>life</hi> firſt: but he that takes up this or that <hi>Vertue</hi> on ſome <hi>ſquint-ey'd by-reſpects,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but a <hi>Mercenary,</hi> no ſooner ſees the <hi>Wolf</hi> come, but inſtantly he <hi>flies</hi> for't.</p>
            <p>Or, we may compare one that is exercis'd in this <hi>Vertue,</hi> to him that built his <hi>Houſe</hi> opon the <hi>Rocke,</hi> which ſtood out all <hi>ſtormes</hi> and <hi>tempeſts</hi> that beat upon it: But thoſe that are <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> to it, to him that built his <hi>Houſe</hi> upon the <hi>Sands,</hi> which upon the firſt <hi>Tempeſt</hi> that beat upon it <hi>fell,</hi> &amp; that with a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Ruine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.32, 33.1 Cor. 3.11.</note> In a word; this <hi>Doctrine</hi> being that <hi>ſtumbling ſtone laid in Sion,</hi> muſt be that <hi>Foundation</hi> ſpoken of by <hi>the Apoſtle, other then which no man can lay.</hi> If any one having truely laid it, <hi>build</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Wood, Hay, and Stubble,</hi> his <hi>Worke</hi> indeed ſhall be <hi>burnt,</hi> and he thereby be <hi>damnifi'd:</hi> but <hi>himſelfe</hi> yet ſhall <hi>eſcape,</hi> howbeit ſo as <hi>through the fire.</hi> But, if any one ſay, he has <hi>laid this Foundation,</hi> when indeed he never did, he is a <hi>lyar, he</hi> and his <hi>Works</hi> both ſhall be conſum'd by <hi>unquenchable fire;</hi> for he <hi>knew his Maſter's will, but did it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have we ſeen the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Influence</hi> and <hi>Importance</hi> of this <hi>Precept,</hi> which leſt we ſhould thinke to be therefore of leſſe <hi>force</hi> and <hi>efficacy,</hi> we muſt furthermore obſerve, it comes as full home to every mans <hi>Severall,</hi> as what <hi>Precept</hi> ſoever is moſt <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</hi> And this is the admirable commendation of it, that its <hi>Generality</hi> hinders not its <hi>efficacy,</hi> for uſually 'tis otherwiſe. The
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112525:11"/>Sun-beams diffus'd at <hi>large</hi> rather <hi>cheriſh</hi> then <hi>offend,</hi> they <hi>burne</hi> not, till contracted into a <hi>narrow cone.</hi> Thunder remov'd at a <hi>far diſtance</hi> from us ſcarce <hi>moves</hi> us any whit, but a <hi>clap</hi> juſt in our <hi>Zenith</hi> makes us ſtartle. A piece of Iron that touches in many <hi>points</hi> at once, being <hi>blunt,</hi> does not enter, but make a <hi>bruiſe;</hi> but a <hi>Needle,</hi> touching but in one <hi>point, enters</hi> to the <hi>quicke:</hi> So <hi>Generall Precepts</hi> uſually make but <hi>ſuperficiall Impreſſions,</hi> a <hi>bruiſe</hi> at moſt: but thoſe that come home to mens <hi>Particulars,</hi> as that <hi>Prophet</hi> came to <hi>Jehu,</hi> with <hi>a Meſſage to thee;</hi> or as the <hi>Prophet Nathan</hi> did to <hi>David,</hi> with <hi>tues homo, thou art the man,</hi> theſe, have an <hi>edge</hi> ſet upon them, and ever make the deepeſt <hi>Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> Now this <hi>Precept,</hi> notwithſtanding it is of that <hi>Generall Importance,</hi> I have ſhew'd, yet comes home to <hi>All</hi> and <hi>every ones Particular ſelfe,</hi> and that puts <hi>force</hi> and <hi>power</hi> into it. The <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> of it is, not any thing <hi>above</hi> us, to wit, <hi>God,</hi> nor any thing <hi>beſide</hi> us, to wit, our <hi>Neighbour,</hi> but <hi>our owne particular ſelves;</hi> and therefore he that can, by <hi>Introverſion</hi> retiring into himſelfe, ſay, I <hi>am the man</hi> whoſe corrupt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> is to be reſigned up to the <hi>Faith of the Son of God;</hi> whoſe deprav'd <hi>Will</hi> is to be Regulated by <hi>Obedience</hi> to His <hi>Heavenly Example,</hi> he, and he onely, is the proper <hi>Subject</hi> of this <hi>Precept.</hi> In briefe: This <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept,</hi> being the <hi>Word of Faith,</hi> as I have made appeare, ſhewes the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to be that <hi>Word,</hi> which is neither <hi>too high,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.8.</note> nor <hi>too low for us;</hi> but <hi>very neare us,</hi> even in our <hi>mouth</hi> and in our <hi>heart,</hi> that we may <hi>doe</hi> it.</p>
            <p>THEN now at length let us proceed and ſee what this <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> is, we ſpeak of. The Words are, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: If any one will come after Me, <hi>Let him deny himſelfe.</hi> Words, you ſee, very briefe, and yet of moſt rich <hi>Contents;</hi> like <hi>Gold,</hi> containing much <hi>value</hi> in a ſmall <hi>quantity;</hi> or like <hi>Pythagoras</hi>'s <hi>letter Y, narrow</hi> at firſt ſight, but after a while of <hi>larger extenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> or rather like the <hi>Vertue</hi> it ſelfe of <hi>Self-denyall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 7.14.</note> which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour calls a <hi>ſtrait entrance</hi> into a <hi>ſpacious Kingdome.</hi> In hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of them therefore, I ſhall not be ſo <hi>preſſe</hi> as to inſiſt ſtrictly on the <hi>Words,</hi> leſt doing too much honour to the <hi>Cabinet,</hi> I prejudice the <hi>Jewel:</hi> But I ſhall take ſome liberty to my ſelfe, and, though I neglect not the <hi>Words</hi> yet, ſhall handle them <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-place-wiſe,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:112525:12"/>and ſo inſiſt upon this <hi>Method:</hi> Firſt, ſhew the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>full Meaning</hi> of this <hi>Precept:</hi> Secondly, its <hi>Poſſibility</hi> or <hi>Peiſableneſſe:</hi> Thirdly, its <hi>Congruity</hi> in <hi>Reaſon:</hi> Fourthly, its <hi>Neceſſity</hi> in <hi>Religion:</hi> Fiftly, its <hi>Excellency,</hi> above any <hi>Precept</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> whatſoever: And laſtly, its <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility</hi> to all thoſe that ſhall <hi>obey</hi> it.</p>
            <p>To ſhew then the <hi>Nature</hi> of this <hi>Precept,</hi> we muſt let you ſee, firſt what is <hi>meant here</hi> by our <hi>Selves:</hi> Then what is <hi>meant</hi> by <hi>Denying:</hi> Laſtly, what by <hi>Denying our ſelves.</hi> By ones <hi>Selfe here</hi> He meanes that, which the <hi>Stoicks</hi> call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: or rather that which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. That is, thoſe <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Opinions</hi> which by <hi>Nature,</hi> now <hi>corrupted,</hi> are in <hi>every one,</hi> and encline him to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh his own <hi>Independencie</hi> of <hi>any other</hi> whatſoever, yea even of <hi>God Himſelfe,</hi> and to <hi>crook</hi> every thing toward <hi>himſelf,</hi> ſo making <hi>himſelfe the ſole end of his thoughts, words and actions.</hi> In a word; <hi>Our Selfe</hi> ſtrictly taken is,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Baſ-Reſp. Interrog. ſextae, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>our owne Will to be or have any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Will of God.</hi> Our <hi>being</hi> any thing may well be ſtyl'd our <hi>Selves,</hi> there is no doubt of that: So may our <hi>having</hi> any thing too, for as much as we <hi>have</hi> and <hi>owne</hi> nothing, but what we <hi>adhere</hi> unto, and becomes a <hi>part of our ſelves</hi> by <hi>Love,</hi> which <hi>Love</hi> does intereſſe us therein.</p>
            <p>But that we may the better underſtand the true <hi>Nature</hi> of our <hi>Selves</hi> as contradiſtinct from God, wee muſt conſider, that the <hi>whole Syſteme</hi> of <hi>Ens</hi> conſiſts but of <hi>two parts, God</hi> and <hi>the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> as it were of the <hi>Sunne</hi> and its <hi>radius,</hi> its <hi>Beame</hi> or <hi>Ray.</hi> That <hi>God</hi> is <hi>of</hi> and <hi>by Himſelfe;</hi> or (to ſpeake more properly) <hi>not of nor by any other:</hi> Therefore, that <hi>He alone</hi> claimes <hi>Selfneſſe</hi> (as I may terme it) to <hi>Himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3.14.</note> becauſe <hi>He alone is what he is;</hi> His <hi>Eſſence</hi> and <hi>Exiſtence</hi> are <hi>both one,</hi> He is his owne <hi>baſis</hi> and <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</hi> Then we muſt conſider, that the <hi>Creature</hi> is no wayes <hi>of it ſelfe,</hi> but <hi>wholly of God,</hi> becauſe <hi>Exiſting eminently</hi> and <hi>radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally in Him. God</hi> therefore, He, <hi>cannot poſſibly Deny Himſelfe,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us; but as for <hi>the Creature,</hi> that, <hi>cannot but Deny it ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.13.</note> if it act as it ſhould doe.</p>
            <p>But then, ſurely you will aske: How comes it to paſſe, there is any <hi>Selfneſſe</hi> in the World, beſide that of <hi>God alone,</hi> that our Saviour ſhould ſpeak here of the <hi>Creatures Selfe?</hi> For this wee muſt know, that indeed and in truth, there is no ſuch thing <hi>in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112525:12"/>rerum naturâ</hi> as the <hi>Creatures Selfe,</hi> contradiſtinct from God, but onely in <hi>Corrupt Opinion</hi> and <hi>Deſire:</hi> And ſo even now I intimated, deriving its true <hi>Originall</hi> from our owne proper <hi>Will:</hi> And ſo much our Saviour <hi>intimates here</hi> to us, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our act of <hi>Denyall</hi> to attend it, the proper <hi>Adjunct</hi> of <hi>Non ens,</hi> of that which in very truth is <hi>nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this <hi>Opinfonate, affected Propriety</hi> or <hi>Selfneſſe</hi> comes about thus. God, having in the Beginning created the whole World <hi>for Himſelfe,</hi> and therein manifeſted His <hi>Power,</hi> in making all things to <hi>ſerve</hi> and <hi>feare</hi> Him, as their <hi>Lord,</hi> would alſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt his <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> and therfore made ſome things to <hi>love</hi> Him too, that is, to <hi>ſerve Him as a Father</hi> no leſſe then as a <hi>Lord.</hi> This that He might doe, 'twas fit His <hi>Service</hi> ſhould be <hi>Rationall;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> that is, proceed from a <hi>rationall Appetite,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Will</hi> infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> So then He made ſuch a <hi>Creature</hi> as was capable of ſuch an <hi>Appetite,</hi> and therewith He endu'd it. Now 'twas neceſſary this <hi>Appetite</hi> ſhould be <hi>free</hi> ſo, that it might <hi>love or not love</hi> God's <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> freely: The <hi>Reaſon</hi> is, Becauſe God is a <hi>Perfect Good,</hi> and ſo requires <hi>Perfect Love</hi> to attend it. But now <hi>Perfect love,</hi> as it <hi>caſts out Feare,</hi> according to the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 4.18.</note> ſo it <hi>caſts out Force</hi> too; as which would argue <hi>Imperfection</hi> in the <hi>Good</hi> it <hi>loves,</hi> that it could not, of it <hi>ſelfe,</hi> without the aid of an <hi>Extraneous force,</hi> attract <hi>love proportionable</hi> thereunto. For this cauſe He made the <hi>Apperite</hi> of the <hi>Will free,</hi> as by His <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> to continue in <hi>Obedience</hi> to His owne <hi>Will,</hi> ſo by its <hi>owne muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> to deflect from that, to deſire an <hi>Independent ſubss;iſtence, of it ſelfe,</hi> and thereto to bend its whole <hi>Activity.</hi> Being thus <hi>enfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed,</hi> it made uſe of its owne <hi>Freedome</hi> to the <hi>worſt</hi> part, and ſo <hi>rebel'd</hi> againſt <hi>God,</hi> its <hi>Maker,</hi> forgetting <hi>Him,</hi> and directing all things to it <hi>ſelfe.</hi> For ſo, (to omit the <hi>Sin</hi> of the <hi>Angels</hi> not revealed to us) we finde that <hi>Adam,</hi> not content with that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> wherein he was ſet by God, brake that <hi>Law,</hi> wherein he was to <hi>acknowledge</hi> his <hi>Dependence</hi> and <hi>Obedience;</hi> by which act of his he did <hi>interpretatively renounce</hi> God his <hi>Maker,</hi> and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſought</hi> and <hi>ſet up himſelfe.</hi> Here now came in our <hi>Propriety, Self-love, Self-will</hi> into the World, and therewith <hi>ſinne,</hi> the <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall</hi> of all <hi>evill;</hi> as well of that which is ſimply ſuch, <hi>ſinne,</hi> as of that which is ſuch to <hi>ſome things</hi> onely, and in <hi>ſome reſpects, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</hi> For, ſo we finde in the <hi>ſtory,</hi> that <hi>Adam,</hi> thus <hi>ſeeking him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112525:13"/>found himſelfe</hi> indeed, but to his owne <hi>Deſtruction:</hi> Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to ſpeak more truely, did not <hi>ſinde,</hi> but quite <hi>loſe himſelfe,</hi> as will appeare out of God's words concerning him. For, when hee had done that, for which hee was ſo <hi>aſham'd</hi> and <hi>afraid</hi> together, that hee was faine to hide <hi>himſelfe, God</hi> comming into the <hi>Garden</hi> askt, <hi>Adam where art thou?</hi> Not but that He knew very well <hi>where he was,</hi> but, that <hi>Adam knew not, what he had made himſelfe,</hi> and ſo <hi>God</hi> askt the <hi>queſtion,</hi> meerely to ſhew he was <hi>no where</hi> or <hi>Nothing,</hi> at leaſt, <hi>in His Account.</hi> This, loe! had <hi>Adam</hi> gotten by his late <hi>Prevarication:</hi> that he, who by <hi>Creation</hi> was newly made <hi>like God Himſelfe,</hi> by <hi>Sinne</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> became the next degree to <hi>Nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by this we have already deliver'd may ſufficiently be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd what this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this ſame <hi>Selfe</hi> is, which our Saviour here ſpeaks of; that not our <hi>Selfe</hi> onely, that which here is to be <hi>deny'd,</hi> but the immediate <hi>conſequents</hi> of it, <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> are indeed, <hi>nothing in the World;</hi> to be ſure, not of <hi>God's making,</hi> but, if any thing, <hi>Creatures of our owne,</hi> and therefore <hi>evill, wholly evill, and that continually.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, more <hi>dictinctly</hi> to unfold the <hi>Nature</hi> of this <hi>Selfe</hi> we have brought into the world, we may obſerve <hi>three ſorts</hi> of things wee are bidden to <hi>Deny</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and in them a <hi>three-fold Selfe.</hi> They are either ſuch things as are <hi>abſolutely evill,</hi> and ſo to be Deny'd of us <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in all caſes</hi> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; or elſe they are <hi>evill onely reſpectively,</hi> and but in <hi>ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> to be <hi>Deny'd.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.12.</note> Of the <hi>firſt ſort</hi> are all <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſſe and worldly luſts,</hi> in the words of <hi>the Apoſtle:</hi> Which that they are our <hi>Selves</hi> yee may ſee by this alone, That whoſoever goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to <hi>Deny</hi> or <hi>reprove</hi> them in any one, when hee hits upon his <hi>peculiar darling luſt</hi> that which ha's moſt of <hi>himſelfe</hi> in it, hee <hi>Winches</hi> preſently, and <hi>Complaines,</hi> hee ſpoke againſt <hi>himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other ſort, which are evill onely in <hi>ſome caſes,</hi> are ſuch things as are either <hi>without us,</hi> as our <hi>Goods of Fortune,</hi> our <hi>Wealth,</hi> which we ordinarily terme our <hi>Selves,</hi> when we ſay, <hi>ſuch a man ha's undone himſelfe,</hi> meaning <hi>his eſtate;</hi> alſo our <hi>Friends, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Mother, Wife, Children, &amp;c.</hi> For theſe we uſe to call our <hi>Second ſelves:</hi> Or elſe thoſe things that are <hi>within us,</hi> as our <hi>Life,</hi> which, without any <hi>Trope,</hi> wee uſually terme our <hi>Selves,</hi> and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112525:13"/>our Saviour makes the higheſt <hi>Object</hi> of our <hi>Actual Self-denyall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John. 15.13.</note> then thoſe things that accompany it, the <hi>Goods of our Body</hi> and <hi>Minde,</hi> our <hi>Beauty, Strength, Learning, &amp;c.</hi> All theſe <hi>three ſelves</hi> are comprehended here in the <hi>Text:</hi> for here we are bidden to <hi>Deny, non noſtra, ſed nos,</hi> not <hi>ours</hi> onely, but <hi>our Selves,</hi> without any <hi>Specification</hi> at all, and therefore to <hi>Deny</hi> what wee take to bee moſt properly our <hi>Selves,</hi> our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Livelihood;</hi> and that containes the other two <hi>Virtually</hi> in it.</p>
            <p>As for our <hi>Soule;</hi> though that be our better part, yet comes it not within the <hi>Precincts</hi> of our <hi>Text.</hi> For, if by it we meane its <hi>two eſſentiall Faculties,</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> and the <hi>Will,</hi> theſe ſo farre as they are <hi>corrupted,</hi> are <hi>Deny'd</hi> in that <hi>firſt ſort</hi> of things we ſpake of even now, which are <hi>abſolutely evill:</hi> and ſo our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> is to be <hi>Deny'd</hi> by <hi>Faith,</hi> ſtrictly taken; our <hi>Will</hi> by <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>will of God;</hi> and both together by that <hi>Faith</hi> which is <hi>truely Evangelicall,</hi> that which <hi>works by Love.</hi> But if by the <hi>Soule,</hi> we meane its <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Happineſſe</hi> in its conjunction with <hi>Gods favour,</hi> it is a great queſtion indeed whether that may be <hi>Deny'd</hi> of us, fince that conjunction cannot be <hi>violated,</hi> but by the commiſſion of ſome <hi>ſinne</hi> or other by us. And yet, ſeeing we have <hi>two famous examples</hi> of it in <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> that really <hi>wiſht</hi> it might be done, could it have conſiſted with <hi>God's glory,</hi> and never were <hi>reprov'd</hi> for't, we may admit it may be done <hi>Voto,</hi> in <hi>Wiſh,</hi> (if it might ſtand with <hi>God's Honour</hi>) howbeit, that ſo it is not required of us. But that this was ever done <hi>de facto</hi> is hard to ſay; though ſome have adventured to affirme,<note place="margin">Se <hi>Calvin Inſt. cap.</hi> 16. <hi>Sect.</hi> 10., 11, 12. <hi>Perkins</hi> on the Creed. The Conſeſsion of Faith Printed <hi>cum Priviligio</hi> 1629. And <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> againſt <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> An. 1600.</note> it came to paſſe once, to wit, in our <hi>Saviour Himſelfe,</hi> who ſuffered, and ſubjected His Soule to the <hi>Sorrowes of Hell</hi> and <hi>Eclipſe</hi> of <hi>God's Favour</hi> towards Him, for certaine <hi>houres,</hi> upon the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> for our <hi>Sinnes:</hi> But that indeed His<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 2.27.31.</note> 
               <hi>Soule was not left therein,</hi> becauſe in ſo <hi>ſhort a ſpace</hi> Hee made an <hi>Infinite Satisfaction.</hi> But I dare not preſume to dogmatize in ſo <hi>Dangerous</hi> a <hi>Point.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we ſee, in the <hi>Generall,</hi> here is a <hi>double Self</hi> to be <hi>deny'd</hi> of us; One <hi>abſolutely evill,</hi> and <hi>ever</hi> to be <hi>Deny'd;</hi> the other <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill</hi> onely <hi>in ſome caſes,</hi> and but at <hi>ſometimes to be Deny'd; That</hi> therefore is to be <hi>Deny'd for it ſelfe, this for that.</hi> For had not the <hi>Firſt Adam</hi> brought <hi>that</hi> into the World, he had never been brought to <hi>Deny this:</hi> And yet for all that the <hi>Second Adam</hi> came to <hi>thruſt that</hi> out of the World, Hee was brought to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112525:14"/>
               <hi>Deny this,</hi> but then it was for our <hi>Selfe-love imputed to Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And thus we have ſeen what is here meant by our <hi>Selves.</hi> Next ſee we what it is to <hi>Deny;</hi> and then laſtly, what to <hi>Deny our ſelves.</hi> To <hi>Deny;</hi> we know what that is, either when we <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradici</hi> what is <hi>affirm'd,</hi> and <hi>affirme</hi> the <hi>contrary:</hi> or elſe when we <hi>refuſe</hi> to grant ones <hi>Requeſt,</hi> and <hi>neglect</hi> or <hi>oppoſe</hi> it. The firſt is <hi>Logicall,</hi> in <hi>words;</hi> the other <hi>Morall,</hi> in our <hi>actions</hi> of commerce one with another. For the <hi>Word</hi> here, it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and that, they ſay comes of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to take away,</hi> ſo that it is the ſame, upon the matter, with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and then it ſeems our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours <hi>meaning</hi> was, <hi>firſt</hi> that we ſhould <hi>take away</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> then <hi>take up the Croſſe;</hi> or rather <hi>take up this,</hi> to <hi>take away that.</hi> In the <hi>Latin</hi> it is <hi>abneget,</hi> which ſignifies to <hi>deny</hi> one, and <hi>denying him,</hi> to <hi>thruſt him from one,</hi> ſo that it is a <hi>Verball</hi> and <hi>Reall denyall,</hi> both. Howbeit <hi>nego,</hi> if we look at the <hi>Originall,</hi> is to deny <hi>Really</hi> too, comming of <hi>ne</hi> and <hi>ago,</hi> to <hi>doe nothing</hi> for one: Therefore <hi>nego</hi> is to deny <hi>Morally,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Logically.</hi> This for the <hi>Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the <hi>Meaning</hi> of it, it is not amiſſe to conſider thoſe other <hi>termes,</hi> wherby cur Saviour was wont to illuſtrate this <hi>Denyall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 14 26.</note> in other places <hi>parallell</hi> hereunto. In one place, He bids us <hi>Hate all,</hi> even our very <hi>Lives,</hi> to be His <hi>Diſciples.</hi> Now he that <hi>Hates</hi> one will never <hi>conſent</hi> or <hi>yield</hi> to him in any thing, but ever <hi>denyes</hi> what hee deſires. Our Saviour therefore deſiring we ſhould <hi>Deny our ſelves,</hi> not <hi>formally</hi> in <hi>Word,</hi> but, <hi>really</hi> in <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Deed,</hi> bids us doe it out of the <hi>Affection</hi> of <hi>Hatred</hi> to our <hi>Selves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, becauſe our <hi>Selves</hi> (in ſome ſenſe) and every thing that <hi>belongs</hi> to our <hi>ſelves,</hi> are not alwayes <hi>bad</hi> and to be <hi>Hated,</hi> as I have ſaid: And it were <hi>Incivility,</hi> contrary to the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> to <hi>hate</hi> our <hi>Parents,</hi> or goe about to <hi>make away</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> therefore muſt we take <hi>Hating</hi> for <hi>loving leſſe.</hi> And ſo in another place our Saviour <hi>expounds</hi> it,<note place="margin">Mar. 10.37, 38</note> ſaying, <hi>He that loves Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Mother more then Me,</hi> (or <hi>ſo much</hi> either) <hi>is not worthy of Me.</hi> So then thus wee are to take it;<note place="margin">Deur 20.16, 17, 18.</note> We are to <hi>Hate</hi> our <hi>ſelves</hi> and <hi>ours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deur. 20.10, 11, 12, &amp;c.</note> when they are <hi>Contrary</hi> to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> when not, yet to <hi>love</hi> them <hi>leſſe,</hi> that is, <hi>onely in Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laftly, Becauſe <hi>Love</hi> is the <hi>Affection of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, Hatred</hi> of <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and wee uſe to <hi>ſeparate</hi> our <hi>Selves</hi> from what wee <hi>Hate,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:112525:14"/>therefore in <hi>Denying</hi> of our <hi>Selves,</hi> He bids, <hi>forſake all we have,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 14.33.</note> that is, as uſually 'tis expreſt, to <hi>come out</hi> of our <hi>Selves,</hi> as <hi>Abram</hi> out of <hi>Chaldaea, Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodom, Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> The word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and that is contrary to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, therefore it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, we ſhould not <hi>ſubordinate</hi> our <hi>owne</hi> things to our <hi>ſelves,</hi> not make our <hi>ſelves</hi> the <hi>Determinate end</hi> of them, but, though they be <hi>ours</hi> and <hi>God</hi> ha's given us them, yet wee ſhould be <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam non habentes, uſe them as though we us'd them not.</hi> For thus we muſt diſtinguiſh between <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> in locum cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> betweene <hi>Renouncing</hi> and <hi>Forſaking</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> as <hi>Beda</hi> well obſerves.</p>
            <p>Now, if we joyn theſe <hi>two</hi> in <hi>one,</hi> we ſhall plainly ſee what <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> it is to <hi>Deny our ſelves.</hi> It is not onely to breake our <hi>ſelves</hi> of our <hi>Naturall, Wild, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntam'd Wills,</hi> that is, to <hi>mortifie our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſſe and Worldly luſts,</hi> thoſe eſpecially we are <hi>moſt</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to, as which have <hi>moſt of our ſelves</hi> in them; but alſo to <hi>eſteeme</hi> of our <hi>Selves, Friends, Goods,</hi> yea and <hi>Life</hi> too, as <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> in reſpect of <hi>God</hi> and His moſt <hi>bleſſed Will;</hi> therefore not to <hi>humour</hi> our owne <hi>Wills,</hi> unleſſe they bee <hi>conſonant</hi> to, and <hi>proceed from God's;</hi> but to <hi>Deny</hi> them <hi>heartily,</hi> therefore to <hi>Hate</hi> them, when <hi>contrary,</hi> yea when <hi>conſonant</hi> to God's Will to <hi>love</hi> them but <hi>a little,</hi> that is, <hi>onely in Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is to <hi>forſake</hi> and <hi>come eat</hi> of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> that is, to become <hi>contrite, humble,</hi> and <hi>obedient,</hi> like <hi>little children,</hi> to be of <hi>Saul's</hi> minde, when he cry'd, <hi>Lord! what wilt Thou I ſhall doe?</hi> and <hi>His Will</hi> to doe, and none but His, what e're it coſt us. And, becauſe theſe <hi>Outward things</hi> ſometimes <hi>follow</hi> us, even when we, <hi>ſeek</hi> not but, <hi>forſake</hi> them, yet to behave our ſelves, <hi>as if we had them not,</hi> or <hi>they were none of ours,</hi> that is, to behave our ſelves as <hi>Stewards,</hi> not as <hi>Owners</hi> of them. This if we ſhall doe; If we ſhall, not <hi>acknowledge</hi> onely but, <hi>love</hi> our owne <hi>Abjection, Contempt,</hi> and <hi>Nothing;</hi> If we ſhall no <hi>longer live, but Chriſh live in us;</hi> If we ſhall make it <hi>our Meat and Drinke to doe the Will of God our Father;</hi> If we ſhall be to <hi>God</hi> as the <hi>Clay</hi> to the <hi>Potter,</hi> as a <hi>Hand</hi> to him <hi>whoſe</hi> hand it is; then we may not doubt but we are good <hi>Followers</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that we are comne to <hi>apprehend that for which we are apprehended of Him,</hi> to a perfect <hi>Denyall of our Selves, a full <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But muſt we then indeed <hi>Deny our ſelves?</hi> muſt we become, not onely <hi>Vile</hi> but, <hi>Nothing</hi> in our own eyes? then I doubt not but it will be ſaid of moſt of us, as once it was by the <hi>Diſciples;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112525:15"/>Here dur us eſt hic ſermo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marth 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5</note> 
               <hi>quis poteſt ſervari? This is ſo hard a ſaying, ſcarce any man can be ſav'd.</hi> And indeed we may better complain of <hi>this ſaying</hi> of our Saviour's, then the <hi>Diſciples</hi> could of <hi>that</hi> He then ſpake to them: for there He onely ſpake of <hi>Denying</hi> their <hi>Wealth;</hi> here He ſpeaks of <hi>Denying</hi> their very <hi>ſelves;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>durior his ſermo,</hi> this is the <hi>harder ſaying</hi> of the twaine by far. But, as our Saviour <hi>then anſwerd</hi> them, ſo may I any that ſhal <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure now,</hi> and tell them, that, <hi>though with men this be impoſſible, yet with God it is not; for with him all things are Poſſible,</hi> &amp; therfore <hi>this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why, me thinks this were enough to ſhew its <hi>Poſsibility,</hi> that 'tis here <hi>enjoyn'd</hi> us by our Saviour, which ſhewes, not onely a bare <hi>Poſſibility,</hi> but ſo high a <hi>modus</hi> of it, as amounts to little leſſe then a <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> as hereafter I ſhall ſhew you. The plain truth is, to acknowledge it <hi>commanded,</hi> and yet maintain it <hi>impoſſible</hi> to be obeyed, muſtargue either <hi>injuſtice</hi> in God, to command it, when <hi>impoſſible,</hi> or <hi>ignorance,</hi> not to know it <hi>impoſſible,</hi> when <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded;</hi> either of which to ſay were <hi>Blaſphemy, deſerving the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of cloathes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did there not goe <hi>power</hi> with the <hi>Word of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3</note> in the <hi>Creation</hi> of things? why may not then <hi>power</hi> as well goe along with <hi>His Word</hi> in the <hi>Gubernation</hi> of things? I'm ſure, when <hi>Moſes</hi> hop't to <hi>excuſe himſelf</hi> from <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>Gods Command</hi> by reaſon of his <hi>Impotency,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 4.10, 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> anſwers him with no other <hi>Reaſon</hi> but that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from His <hi>Creating Power.</hi> Nor is it any maryaile; for indeed there is a <hi>ſtrait affinity</hi> betwixt them, ſince it were a great diſparagement to the <hi>Creation,</hi> if any <hi>Creature</hi> ſhould not be endu'd with a <hi>ſufficient Capacity</hi> to attaine its <hi>end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Gods commanding Word</hi> does not ever obtaine its <hi>Prime</hi> intended <hi>End,</hi> that is, <hi>Obedience</hi> thereunto, as His <hi>Creating Word</hi> ever did, makes nothing at all againſt this. For that may proceed from the <hi>Diverſity</hi> of <hi>Subjects;</hi> (not the want of <hi>Power</hi>) that of the <hi>Creation</hi> being meerely <hi>Naturall</hi> and <hi>Paſſive,</hi> whereas that of Gods <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Commands</hi> (ſuch I meane as are <hi>Morall</hi>) is <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary</hi> and <hi>Active;</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, left <hi>in manu conſilii ſui,</hi> and ſo ha's power of <hi>Reſiſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor does it make anything againſt this; that <hi>now</hi> we are not able to <hi>fulfill</hi> the <hi>Law of God.</hi> For, if we underſtand it, of fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it in the <hi>Rigour,</hi> 'tis true, we are not <hi>now able to doe it;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither is it <hi>now ſo required</hi> of us. But, when it was, as it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112525:15"/>was <hi>before our Fall,</hi> then, no man doubts but, we had <hi>ſufficient a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> to doe it: If we underſtand it of fulfilling it in <hi>Sincerity,</hi> ſo indeed it is <hi>now</hi> required of us, and ſo to fulfill it we have now <hi>ſufficient ability:</hi> He that denyes it is a <hi>Lyer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.14. Rom. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>and the Truth is not in him.</hi> Now, I ſay, eſpecially in theſe dayes of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">John 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>is the power of God to every one that beleeves;</hi> Now, that our Saviour ha's brought with Him that <hi>Grace and Truth</hi> which the <hi>Law of Moſes</hi> could not; Now,<note place="margin">Acts 2.16.17.</note> that <hi>God powres forth of his Spirit plentifully upon all Fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, if any one be yet ſo hardy as to deny it, let him recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile his Denyall with that Aſſertion of our Saviour's,<note place="margin">Matth. 10.30. 1 John. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>My Yoak is eaſie, and my Burthen is light:</hi> Or with that of St. <hi>John, Verily, His Commandements are not grievous.</hi> For ſure His <hi>Yoak</hi> muſt needs <hi>pinch</hi> and <hi>gall us,</hi> in which we cannot <hi>ſtirre</hi> our <hi>Necks,</hi> to <hi>draw</hi> in it: His <hi>Burthen</hi> cannot but be <hi>heavy,</hi> to thoſe that have <hi>no abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> to lift, much leſſe to <hi>beare</hi> it; And His <hi>Commandements</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be <hi>grievous</hi> to thoſe that are allow'd <hi>no manner of Grace</hi> to performe them.</p>
            <p>Were not this to make <hi>God</hi> as <hi>tyrannicall</hi> as <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> to ſet us a <hi>taske</hi> and afford us no <hi>Straw</hi> to doe it? or as <hi>Auſtere</hi> as that <hi>Maſter,</hi> that lookt to <hi>reap where be never ſow'd?</hi> No,<note place="margin">Mich. 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſhew'd thee, O Man, what is good, and what the Lord requireth of thee,</hi> ſayes God by His <hi>Prophet.</hi> And the <hi>Wiſe man</hi> askes the <hi>queſtion</hi> (thereby leaving every <hi>Foole,</hi> as <hi>without all anſwer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 17.6.</note> ſo without all <hi>excuſe:</hi>) <hi>Wherefore is there a Price in the band of a foole, to get Wiſedome, ſeeing he hath no heart to it?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 13.12. &amp; 25.29. Luke 8.18.</note> Does not our Saviour tell us, in more places then one, that every man is <hi>habens,</hi> that is, <hi>ha's the grace of God,</hi> as well he <hi>from whom it was taken,</hi> as he <hi>to whom more was given?</hi> I'm ſure, He ſayes, <hi>every Servant had his Talent and Pound,</hi> as well he that <hi>laid it up,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 19.20.] Luke 12.48.</note> as he that <hi>improv'd it double.</hi> If that bee not enough, He tells us, <hi>He looks for mens ſervice proportionable to His Grace and their abilities;</hi> for much where he beſtowes <hi>much;</hi> for <hi>little</hi> where <hi>little:</hi> And where there is <hi>none at all</hi> (as ſometimes poſſibly it happens) Hee will accept of the <hi>Will</hi> for the <hi>Deed.</hi> In one place <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8, 12.</note> 
               <hi>God accepts every one according to that he hath, not according to that he hath not.</hi> In another, <hi>That no man is tempted above that he is able,</hi> and the like. All which ſhewes us the <hi>Truth</hi> of,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note> what <hi>God Himſelfe</hi> told St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his <hi>Extremity, His Grace, His Strength,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note> that Hee
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112525:16"/>affords us, is <hi>ſufficient</hi> for us; as alſo that of <hi>Baſil the G.</hi> in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Homil. 28.</note> where ſpeaking of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the perſon of that <hi>Compaſſionate Father</hi> meeting his <hi>Prodigall Sonne returning,</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently affirmes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. If we doe but <hi>ſeriouſly will</hi> and <hi>reſolve to returne</hi> (as we may, though not <hi>as of our ſelves) God will prevent and meet us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, to ſpeak <hi>more preſſely</hi> to our <hi>Text,</hi> and this action of <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> I hope plainly to make it appeare, to any <hi>Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous</hi> man, and that out of the <hi>Text</hi> it ſelfe, that God affords <hi>any man ſufficient grace</hi> to doe it. The words are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (to give you the full <hi>Grammar</hi> of the word) is the <hi>third Perſon of the firſt Aoriſt</hi> of the <hi>Imperative Mood,</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> An <hi>Imperſonall</hi> it is not, nor of the <hi>Paſſive voice,</hi> but the <hi>middle</hi> ſo, that, although no <hi>Perſon</hi> in the <hi>Originall</hi> be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt yet, of neceſſity, it muſt be <hi>underſtood,</hi> by that <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fubintelligitur non deeſt.</hi> Accordingly therefore, our <hi>Engliſh</hi> truly ſupplyes the <hi>Perſon</hi> wanting, but <hi>underſtood,</hi> rendring it, <hi>Let him deny himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Queſtion is, what our Saviour meant by this <hi>him,</hi> which in every man is to <hi>Deny himſelfe.</hi> That <hi>himſelf</hi> is <hi>wholly</hi> to be <hi>Deny'd</hi> for God, I have ſhew'd you, nor doe <hi>the word</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port any whit leſſe: this <hi>Him</hi> therefore muſt be ſomething in <hi>Man</hi> differing from <hi>himſelfe:</hi> and ſo much our Saviour ſeems to intimate, making <hi>him</hi> the <hi>Subject,</hi> and <hi>himſelfe</hi> the <hi>Predicate,</hi> as we ſpeak, therby plainly diſtinguiſhing the one from the other. Nor was this any more then needs; for <hi>him</hi> is here the <hi>Agent, himſelfe</hi> is the <hi>Patient,</hi> and theſe two muſt neceſſarily be diſtinguiſht; Nothing can be <hi>Agent</hi> and <hi>Patient, Cauſe and Effect,</hi> both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of it <hi>ſelfe,</hi> ſince every <hi>Paſſion</hi> is an <hi>Alteration,</hi> and nothing can <hi>alter</hi> that which is but <hi>like</hi> it <hi>ſelfe,</hi> much leſſe its <hi>owne ſelfe;</hi> for a <hi>Generall Rule</hi> it is, impoſſible to be contradicted, <hi>Idem quà idem, femper facit idem; the ſame Cauſe, as it is the ſame, alwayes produces the ſame effect:</hi> Therefore nothing, continuing the <hi>ſame</hi> it was, can produce an <hi>Alteration</hi> in it <hi>ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, This is true indeed, of <hi>tranſient,</hi> but not ſo of <hi>immanent</hi> actions; we anſwer, It cannot but be true of all <hi>actions</hi> whatſoever: For nothing what ſoever, whether by an <hi>immanent</hi> or <hi>tranſient,</hi> whether by a <hi>reflext</hi> or <hi>direct</hi> action, can truely and properly, of it ſelfe <hi>melierate</hi> it <hi>ſelfe,</hi> though by reaſon of its
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112525:16"/>
               <hi>Mutability,</hi> it may <hi>corrupt</hi> it <hi>ſelfe,</hi> that is, <hi>decline</hi> from its <hi>Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> The Reaſon of it is, that <hi>Generall Principle of Nature, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil dat quod non habet, nothing can give that it ha's not.</hi> For nothing can be <hi>Meliorated</hi> or better'd, but by the <hi>Addition</hi> of what <hi>Good</hi> it wants unto it ſelfe: And that nothing can <hi>adde</hi> unto it <hi>ſelfe</hi> (for then it ſhould <hi>have</hi> that it <hi>ha's</hi> not, which were a <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi>) therefore nothing can <hi>meliorate</hi> it <hi>ſelfe.</hi> Now this <hi>denyall</hi> of our <hi>ſelves</hi> for the <hi>love of God,</hi> though it ſeemes to our <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected</hi> eyes a <hi>Corrupting</hi> act, yet indeed is an act of <hi>meliora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> for it drawes up both our <hi>Soule</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> to the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation</hi> of a <hi>Higher Nature,</hi> as will appeare more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>So then 'tis plaine, this <hi>him</hi> that here is <hi>Agent,</hi> is ſomething different from <hi>himſelfe,</hi> that here is <hi>Patient,</hi> and muſt <hi>Deny</hi> him. And yet ſomething <hi>without himſelfe</hi> it is not, for it muſt <hi>Deny the whole Man,</hi> every <hi>high Thought,</hi> every <hi>ſtrong hold,</hi> every <hi>power</hi> and <hi>faculty</hi> in him, not onely the <hi>errors</hi> of his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> but alſo the <hi>contumacy</hi> of his <hi>Will,</hi> and the <hi>Pravity</hi> of his <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections;</hi> and all this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformely,</hi> without any <hi>Partiality</hi> at all: But this it cannot doe, unleſſe it be <hi>within our Inmoſt parts,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be <hi>intus &amp; in cute,</hi> as neare us as our very thoughts; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an <hi>Angelick Nature</hi> it cannot be, for to our <hi>Thoughts</hi> they are all <hi>ſtrangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can it be any <hi>Nature beneath</hi> our <hi>Selves;</hi> for, ye ſee, <hi>him</hi> is here the <hi>Agent,</hi> our <hi>Selfe</hi> is the <hi>Patient,</hi> that muſt be <hi>Deny'd:</hi> Now, as the <hi>Greater</hi> muſt <hi>Bleſſe,</hi> ſo muſt it <hi>Deny</hi> the <hi>Leſſer</hi> too,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.7.</note> (eſpecially this <hi>Denyall</hi> being no other, but, as I ſaid, an act of <hi>Melioration</hi> or a <hi>Bleſſing</hi>) for 'tis a <hi>generall</hi> and <hi>true Rule, Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid patitur, patitur à fortiori, The weakeſt ever ſuffers and goes to the Wall.</hi> Here then ſure it muſt be ſo, for, I ask, How if it ſhould happen, that the <hi>Patient,</hi> being the <hi>ſtronger,</hi> ſhould <hi>refuſe</hi> to be <hi>Deny'd,</hi> and, like a <hi>ſturdy Begger,</hi> turne the <hi>Denyall</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the <hi>Agent,</hi> as ſurely it would doe? ſhould it then bee <hi>Patient</hi> and the other <hi>Agent</hi> any longer? No ſure, the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall</hi> would be fruſtrate, it would be but <hi>formall,</hi> at the moſt, it could not be reall.</p>
            <p>It followes then; this <hi>Him</hi> muſt be ſomething in us, <hi>above</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> yea <hi>above</hi> any <hi>Angelick Nature</hi> whatſoever: and what is that but <hi>God alone?</hi> You will ſay perhaps; That's true indeed,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112525:17"/>
               <hi>God is every where, fills Heaven and Earth,</hi> and all things, as well as <hi>Man,</hi> yet does not this enable them to <hi>Deny themſelves.</hi> It may be ſo; But then it is, becauſe <hi>nothing</hi> but the <hi>Intelligent, Rationall Creature</hi> is diſpos'd for ſuch an <hi>Ability</hi> or <hi>Aſſiſtance,</hi> and ſo that alone is thereby enabled to this <hi>great worke. Man</hi> therefore (and we may ſay no leſſe of <hi>Angels</hi>) is onely properly <hi>furniſht</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpos'd</hi> thereto, ſeeing he ha's an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> to be <hi>enlightned,</hi> he ha's a <hi>Will,</hi> to be <hi>excited and ſuſtain'd</hi> in the performance of it, which <hi>Will,</hi> though <hi>Dead</hi> and <hi>deprav'd before</hi> yet, by this <hi>exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, aſſiſting,</hi> and <hi>ſubſequent Grace of God</hi> in us being <hi>quickned,</hi> is elevated and rais'd <hi>above</hi> it ſelf, and ſo becomes this <hi>him,</hi> or <hi>Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Nature,</hi> in us, that is to <hi>Deny our Selves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it is, that, though this <hi>whole Action</hi> proceeds from that <hi>Partickle of God</hi> in us yet, it is not entitl'd here to <hi>God</hi> directly, or <hi>His Grace</hi> in us, but ſaid, <hi>Let him,</hi> that is, <hi>any Perſon that ſhall deſire to come after Me,</hi> thus <hi>actuated</hi> and <hi>renovated</hi> by the <hi>Grace</hi> of God <hi>with him, Deny himſelfe.</hi> The Reaſon of it is this; This <hi>Grace</hi> of God, though <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4. that is, <hi>exceeding or Divinely powerfull</hi> yet, does not work af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an <hi>Omnipotent</hi> manner in us, but <hi>ſe decenter &amp; creaturae conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienter, in a manner befitting it ſelfe, and convenient for the Creature,</hi> ſo, as neither it is <hi>deficient</hi> in <hi>neceſſary</hi> power to <hi>aſſiſt</hi> us againſt all <hi>Difficulties;</hi> nor yet ſo <hi>violent,</hi> as to alter the <hi>Nature</hi> of that it is but to <hi>aſſiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, that God affords this <hi>Grace</hi> of His to <hi>every one</hi> invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to this <hi>Duty</hi> by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> is plaine, by thoſe <hi>Generall words</hi> of <hi>Invitation,</hi> in the Preface to our <hi>Text,</hi> for to that our <hi>Precept</hi> muſt be <hi>adequat.</hi> St. <hi>Matthew</hi> indeed ſeems to reſtrain them one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the <hi>Diſciples:</hi> But not onely St. <hi>Mark,</hi> in his <hi>parallel, Chap.</hi> 8.34. aſſures us, they were meant as well to the <hi>whole multitude,</hi> but alſo <hi>the Words themſelves</hi> plainly involve a <hi>Generality.</hi> For 'tis certaine this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>If any man will come after Me, is an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Invitation;</hi> and, 'tis plaine, to that muſt this <hi>him</hi> in the <hi>Text,</hi> be <hi>commenſurate. If any man will, &amp;c. let any man deny himſelfe:</hi> What fuller <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall</hi> then can we wiſh for, then that <hi>any man</hi> ſhould, not onely be <hi>able</hi> but, <hi>be call'd</hi> to doe it? The word <hi>any</hi> indeed <hi>includes</hi> none, but it <hi>excludes</hi> not <hi>any:</hi> It ſuppoſes <hi>all will not,</hi> yet implyes <hi>any one may,</hi> Deny himſelfe, if at leaſt he be one of thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe that have a <hi>Will or deſire to come after Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:112525:17"/>
            <p>And this, I ſuppoſe, is ſufficient to have ſhewne, that this <hi>Adjutorium Dei,</hi> as the <hi>Fathers</hi> call'd it, this <hi>Aſſiſtent Grace</hi> of God is not wanting to all thoſe that doe what lyes in them to <hi>Deny themſelves</hi> ſo, that by the <hi>helpe</hi> thereof it becomes a thing <hi>feiſable</hi> unto them. But yet, that wee may conceive the <hi>manner</hi> of this more diſtinctly, both what this <hi>Denyer</hi> in the <hi>Text</hi> is, and what the <hi>Denyed,</hi> likewiſe the <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>Denyall:</hi> It will be very <hi>expedient</hi> to conceive of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> as <hi>Origen</hi> following St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Theſ. 5.23. Heb. 4.12.</hi> Orig. lib. <hi>1.</hi> in Rom. Eraſ. in Enchir. pag. <hi>57.</hi> Edit. Lugd. Bat. An. <hi>1624.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Eraſmus Origen,</hi> repreſent our <hi>ſelves</hi> to us. For they tell us, <hi>Man</hi> is ſaid to conſiſt of <hi>Spirit, Soule, and Body:</hi> and that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is ſaid, <hi>The Fleſh luſteth againſt the Spirit, and the Spirit againſt the Fleſh;</hi> the <hi>Soule</hi> muſt needs be ſuppos'd to ſtand <hi>indifferent</hi> betwixt them ſo, that, if it reſts it ſelfe in the <hi>deſires</hi> of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſoliciting</hi> her on the one ſide to <hi>Vertue,</hi> it becomes <hi>one Spirit with it;</hi> but if it joyne it ſelfe to the <hi>Fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.16, 17</note> 
               <hi>ſoliciting her</hi> on the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide to <hi>naughtineſſe,</hi> it becomes <hi>one Body with it,</hi> in the luſts and pleaſures of it. That all this is but meere <hi>ſolicitation,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of <hi>force</hi> on either ſide, that ſo the <hi>ſoule</hi> may be left at <hi>liberty</hi> to make her <hi>free-choice,</hi> whether of the two ſhe will ſide with: Howbeit the <hi>Power of God</hi> is ready to attend the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> when the <hi>Soule</hi> cleaves unto them. But <hi>no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> accompanies the <hi>motions</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>Soule</hi> being too <hi>able</hi> to embrace thoſe <hi>Motions</hi> of it <hi>ſelfe,</hi> through its owne <hi>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, after we have firſt conſider'd, what St. <hi>Paul</hi> mindes us of, that <hi>that which is Naturall is firſt, then that which is Spirituall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.46.</note> that is, that the <hi>ſoule</hi> is firſt <hi>polluted</hi> by cleaving to the <hi>corrupt Nature</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> before it can be <hi>purifi'd</hi> by cleaving to the <hi>Celeſtiall Nature</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> we ſhall eaſily conceive, that this <hi>him,</hi> we ſpake of, or the <hi>Denyer</hi> in the <hi>Text,</hi> is the <hi>ſoule united</hi> to the <hi>Spirit,</hi> of which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſayes, <hi>If ye walke in the Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>ye ſhall not fulfill the luſts of the Fleſh.</hi> That <hi>our ſelves,</hi> or he that is <hi>Deny'd</hi> in the <hi>Text,</hi> is the <hi>Soule</hi> (earſt-while) cleaving to the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> of which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.8.</note> 
               <hi>They that are in the Fleſh cannot pleaſe God.</hi> Laſtly, that the <hi>Denyall</hi> is no other, but the <hi>Soules Converſion</hi> from the <hi>Fleſh</hi> to the <hi>Spirit, renouncing</hi> its former cleaving to the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Repenting</hi> of it: And, for the time to come, <hi>covenanting</hi> and <hi>reſolving,</hi> never more to have to doe with it, but <hi>henceforward for ever,</hi> to perſevere in the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:112525:18"/>
            <p>I have been the larger on this, becauſe a <hi>Point</hi> of much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to all <hi>Piety;</hi> for who ſees not, that in the <hi>Feiſableneſſe</hi> of God's <hi>Precepts</hi> is laid the <hi>firſt ſtone</hi> of its <hi>Foundation,</hi> ſeeing no man will but <hi>offer</hi> to attempt that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he cannot phantſie to be <hi>Poſſible?</hi> Accordingly therefore the <hi>Devil</hi> ſeeks mainly to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it, having had ſuch good <hi>ſucceſse</hi> on the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſſe;</hi> who, giving more credit to the <hi>perfidious ſpies</hi> then to <hi>God's,</hi> not <hi>Pramiſe</hi> onely but, <hi>command,</hi> were <hi>overthrowne,</hi> and could not,<note place="margin">Heb. 3, 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>a Man of them, enter that good land,</hi> not for their <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency,</hi> but <hi>Diſobedience</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeliefe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides; It much concernes us we agree amongſt our ſelves, againſt the <hi>Common enemy:</hi> when we are to deale <hi>with them</hi> wee hold, <hi>neceſſaria manifeſta;</hi> have we not then as good reaſon to hold <hi>amongſt our ſelves, Neceſſaria poſſibilia;</hi> that <hi>neceſſary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts</hi> (and ſure <hi>this</hi> is a <hi>Chiefe</hi> one) <hi>are as Poſſible</hi> as <hi>neceſſary Truths</hi> are <hi>manifeſt?</hi> ſurely we have, and better. For of the two, <hi>Practice</hi> is more <hi>neceſſary</hi> then <hi>Knowledge</hi> to <hi>Salvation,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Knowledge puffeth up,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.1.</note> 
               <hi>but 'tis onely Charity that edifies;</hi> And, for our part, we are <hi>naturally</hi> as deſtitute of the <hi>one</hi> as of the <hi>other,</hi> being no leſſe <hi>Blinde</hi> then <hi>Impotent,</hi> to all <hi>ſaving Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again; were it not <hi>abſurd</hi> to think the <hi>God of Nature</hi> leſſe <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident,</hi> then that <hi>Nature</hi> He created? now that is <hi>deficient</hi> to Nothing in things <hi>neceſſary</hi> to attaine its and, and therefore ſure <hi>God</hi> is not <hi>deficient</hi> in things <hi>neceſſary</hi> to attaine <hi>His,</hi> Farre beyond that of <hi>Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet further; Were it not <hi>more abſurd,</hi> to make the <hi>Word of God</hi> leſſe <hi>Potent</hi> then the <hi>word of an earthly King?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eceleſ. 8.4.</note> and yet <hi>with the word of a King there is Power:</hi> but ſo there is not <hi>with the Word of the King of Kings,</hi> if we deny His <hi>Precept feiſable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, more; Were it not <hi>moſt of all abſurd</hi> to make the <hi>Word of God</hi> leſſe <hi>Potent</hi> then the <hi>Word of the Devill?</hi> And yet we doe it by this <hi>Tenet</hi> of ours: for, if he bids <hi>his Creatures,</hi> beſotted <hi>Inamoradoes,</hi> Covetous <hi>Miſers,</hi> or Ambitious <hi>Aſpirers, Deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> in <hi>ſome things,</hi> to <hi>enjoy themſelves</hi> in <hi>others,</hi> we ſee, they doe it, even to <hi>admiration;</hi> and then ſhall we affirme it <hi>impoſsible</hi> to <hi>Deny our ſelves</hi> in <hi>all</hi> things, to <hi>enjoy our God?</hi> What a <hi>Soleciſme,</hi> what a <hi>Shame</hi> were it, that the <hi>Devills ſervants</hi> ſhould be more active, to their <hi>Perdition,</hi> then <hi>God's ſervants</hi> to their <hi>Salvations?</hi> Pray God, that one day they riſe not up in <hi>Judgment</hi> againſt us.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:112525:18"/>
            <p>Finally, that 'tis generally beleev'd, this <hi>Precept</hi> ha's been <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd</hi> by <hi>few</hi> or <hi>none</hi> in its <hi>Perfection,</hi> is not preſently to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to its <hi>Impoſſibility,</hi> but, with more reaſon, to our <hi>wayward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of the <hi>Meanes, Prayer, Faſting, and a firme Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution</hi> to fulfill it. For, if it ha's not yet been perform'd in its <hi>utmoſt perfection</hi> (as I believe it has not by any <hi>Viator,</hi> any <hi>living Man</hi>) it followes not therefore, 'tis <hi>impoſſible.</hi> Will any reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able man ſay, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> could not have <hi>entred</hi> the <hi>land of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> becauſe they <hi>did not?</hi> If ſo, then certainly <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> hit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>wrong Cauſe,</hi> imputing it, not to their <hi>want of ſtrength</hi> but, to their <hi>want of Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3.18, 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, becauſe this <hi>Vertue</hi> is <hi>Impoſſible</hi> now to us in its <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Perfection,</hi> ſhall we therefore conclude it in any <hi>degree Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible?</hi> What a <hi>Paralogiſme</hi> is this? 'tis all one, as to ſay, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we cannot ſtraight be <hi>Angels,</hi> therfore we wil not be ſo much as <hi>Men.</hi> No, if we cannot attaine the <hi>Perfection of Degrees,</hi> let us labour for the <hi>Perfection of Parts,</hi> that is, <hi>Deny our ſelves ſincerely, with all our Hearts; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformely, without connivence.</hi> When we have done that, let us make on towards the <hi>Perfection of Degrees;</hi> for he cannot be ſo much as <hi>Good,</hi> that labours not to be <hi>Perfect.</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he wrote to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> could not ſay,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.12. &amp;c.</note> that he was <hi>Perfect,</hi> or had <hi>attain'd the Prize.</hi> What? did he therefore ſet him downe, and give o're the <hi>purſuit</hi> of it? No, but this one thing he did; <hi>Forgetting what was behinde, he preſt onwards to that that was before him, making his Aime at the Prize of the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And <hi>the ſame minde</hi> ought to bee in <hi>every one</hi> of us; for ſo there it followes in his <hi>words, As many of us,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>as are perfect,</hi> that is, make towards Perfection, <hi>let us be thus minded: And if any one be otherwiſe minded,</hi> God ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale this alſo to him.</p>
            <p>And let thus much ſuffice to have ſhewne the <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/>
               <hi>Selfe-denyall,</hi> that 'tis a thing <hi>Feiſable</hi> and may be <hi>done</hi> of us. But, becauſe this is not ſufficient (for ſhould we undertake e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>Poſſible</hi> thing we might ſinde worke enough) the next thing we intend to ſhew you is the <hi>Congruity</hi> of it, that 'tis ſit in <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>Equity</hi> to be done. In <hi>Reaſon,</hi> I ſay, for this is ſo unkind a piece of worke to the <hi>common courſe</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> that ſhe is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe from it; and <hi>Senſe,</hi> that, <hi>abborres</hi> it; No, nothing but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112525:19"/>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> is capable of doing it, and that too not, unleſſe <hi>actuated</hi> and <hi>elevated</hi> by <hi>Divine Aſſiſtance.</hi> So that, to perſwade you to take it ſeriouſly in hand, we had need muſter up in vincible <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for it,</hi> elſe our <hi>Text</hi> may be in danger to be <hi>inverted,</hi> and that <hi>Patient,</hi> we ſpake of, become <hi>Agent,</hi> and the <hi>Agent Patient,</hi> and be <hi>Deny'd</hi> of him.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.29.</note> I'm ſure, <hi>at firſt,</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>God made us upright, multa ratiocinia, many Reaſonings and Inventions</hi> were muſtered up by the <hi>Devill,</hi> by our <hi>Selves,</hi> to overthrow <hi>this Truth:</hi> Theſe now, we are to ſhew you, were but <hi>Paralogiſmes</hi> and <hi>Falſe reaſonings,</hi> by bringing you into the <hi>Sanctuary of God's Word,</hi> which affords us abundant <hi>Reaſon</hi> to the <hi>Contrary,</hi> why we ſhould <hi>renounce</hi> and <hi>forſake</hi> our <hi>ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This that we may doe, you may remember, what I told you even now, that to <hi>Deny our ſelves</hi> in <hi>Logick</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> was to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict</hi> our <hi>Being: tollere,</hi> to <hi>avoid</hi> and <hi>take it away.</hi> Not that we are to endeavour our owne <hi>Annibilation,</hi> for beſides that that were <hi>Impoſſible</hi> for us, to that nothing is more <hi>contrary</hi> then <hi>Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyall,</hi> but to endevour to diſannuall our <hi>Self-being,</hi> &amp; totally to <hi>depend</hi> upon <hi>God.</hi> So then in our <hi>Self-denyall</hi> we are <hi>wholly</hi> to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce</hi> and <hi>abjure</hi> the <hi>Being of our owne:</hi> and, if we be not <hi>our own,</hi> whoſe elſe ſhould we be, but <hi>Gods? His</hi> then we are by <hi>two main Titles;</hi> Our <hi>Creation,</hi> and <hi>Re-creation</hi> or <hi>Redemption,</hi> which is the <hi>Title</hi> of our <hi>Creation re-inforc't.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Title</hi> of our <hi>Creation;</hi> That plainly demonſtrates <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> this <hi>Nullity</hi> of <hi>Being our owne,</hi> and our <hi>Totall dependance</hi> upon <hi>God.</hi> For I told you what <hi>Creation</hi> was; <hi>Such an act of God, whereby the Creature is wholly and ſolely of and from Him, and of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe in the World.</hi> So then no <hi>Creature</hi> is of <hi>it ſelf;</hi> and if not of <hi>it ſelfe,</hi> it is not <hi>its owne,</hi> but anothers, to wit, <hi>God's for Him;</hi> therefore it muſt be <hi>made:</hi> whence <hi>Reaſon</hi> argues thus. No <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> is by <hi>God</hi> made for it <hi>ſelf:</hi> But <hi>Man</hi> is one of <hi>God's Creatures, Ergo.</hi> The <hi>Minor</hi> we take to be confeſt on all hands. The <hi>Major</hi> is to be prov'd: And firſt that <hi>de facto, it is ſo,</hi> then that <hi>de jure, it ſhould be ſo.</hi> For the firſt, in the <hi>Creation</hi> of things we finde, that <hi>All</hi> things were by <hi>God</hi> made, not <hi>for themſelves</hi> but, for ſome higher end, which <hi>End, the Wiſe man</hi> tells us, was no other but <hi>Himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 43.7.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>hath made all things for himſelfe, Prov.</hi> 16.4.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:112525:19"/>
            <p>But this is not to be underſtood of all things in the <hi>ſame</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; for ſome things he made <hi>more immediately for Himſelfe,</hi> as <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> other things <hi>more mediately for Himſelfe,</hi> but <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately</hi> for <hi>Man.</hi> We finde in the <hi>Story</hi> of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to <hi>other</hi> things but of His <hi>Being,</hi> but to <hi>Man</hi> He gave His <hi>Image alſo;</hi> therefore to <hi>Man</hi> He gave the reſt of the <hi>Creatures,</hi> that they might <hi>ſerve Him</hi> for food and other purpoſes, the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> yea the very <hi>Angels</hi> themſelves not excepted; But <hi>Maus ſervice</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> He reſerv'd by a ſpeciall <hi>Command</hi> unto <hi>Himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet, though all things were made for a further <hi>End</hi> then <hi>themſelves,</hi> this hindred not, but they might lawfully <hi>provide</hi> for <hi>themſelves;</hi> for, that they might ſerve <hi>that End,</hi> neceſſary it was, their ſeverall <hi>Beings</hi> ſhould be <hi>preſerv'd,</hi> and that as well in their <hi>Kindes,</hi> as in their <hi>Individualls.</hi> Hence every thing by <hi>Nature</hi> was inclin'd to the proper place of its moſt happy <hi>being, Heavy</hi> things tending towards the <hi>Earth, Light</hi> things towards <hi>Heaven.</hi> Hence, every <hi>Creature</hi> was endu'd with a ſtrong <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite</hi> of its <hi>Nouriſhment,</hi> likewiſe of its owne <hi>Multiplication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe <hi>Appetites,</hi> though put into them for their owne <hi>Preſervation</hi> yet, ſhew them not made <hi>ultimately</hi> for <hi>themſelves;</hi> ſo much appeares plainly by, that they call, the <hi>Motion</hi> of <hi>Nexe,</hi> or <hi>ne detur vacuum,</hi> wherein the <hi>Nature</hi> of moſt <hi>ſenſeleſſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> diſpenſes with their, <hi>neceſſary</hi> but, <hi>Private Appetites,</hi> for the <hi>Continuation</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe.</hi> So much <hi>Nature</hi> teaches thoſe <hi>Inanimate Creatures</hi> by her <hi>occult,</hi> but <hi>uncontrowled Law:</hi> But us <hi>men Religion</hi> further and more manifeſtly inſtructs, to <hi>Deny</hi> the <hi>Appetite</hi> of our <hi>Nouriſhment</hi> by <hi>Faſting,</hi> of <hi>Multiplication,</hi> by <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity,</hi> yea of <hi>Life</hi> it ſelfe by <hi>Selfe-denyall,</hi> when the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God</hi> requires it. And let this ſuffice to have ſhewne that <hi>de facto,</hi> no <hi>Creature</hi> was made <hi>terminatively</hi> for it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now that <hi>de jure, it ought to be ſo,</hi> will appeare, if we conſider that, <hi>God</hi> being the <hi>Summum,</hi> yea the <hi>ſolum Bonum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 19.17.</note> the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> and <hi>Onely Good,</hi> as our Saviour tells us, <hi>Selfe-love</hi> is <hi>His alone Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative,</hi> He alone <hi>may,</hi> He alone <hi>ought</hi> to <hi>Love Himſelfe.</hi> Which, if it be ſo, then how can it ſtand with His <hi>Nature</hi> &amp; <hi>Prerogative,</hi> to make ſuch a <hi>Creature</hi> as, in its <hi>Energie,</hi> ſhould proceed dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly <hi>forward,</hi> that is, worke only <hi>for it ſelfe,</hi> but no wayes <hi>reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procate</hi> any <hi>Good</hi> to <hi>Him,</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> of its <hi>Being?</hi> Certainly, it
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112525:20"/>cannot;<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.13.</note> For, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, <hi>God cannot deny Himſelfe,</hi> therefore muſt needs make all things <hi>for Himſelfe,</hi> for <hi>His owne Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it is, that all things which any way <hi>ſavour</hi> of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependency</hi> on that <hi>ſupreme end</hi> of all, by being done to <hi>no end,</hi> but meerely <hi>for themſelves,</hi> become, to the judgment of <hi>Right Reaſon, abſurd, odious, monſtrous;</hi> ſuch is its <hi>Loyalty</hi> ſtill towards its <hi>Creator.</hi> In <hi>Logicke,</hi> we call it the <hi>womans Syllogiſme</hi> to prove a <hi>Queſtion</hi> by it <hi>ſelfe,</hi> without a <hi>Third Argument, It is ſo, becauſe it is ſo,</hi> and accompt it <hi>Ridiculous.</hi> We do no leſſe in <hi>Morality;</hi> but dubb him for a <hi>Foole,</hi> and laugh at him for his paines, that does a thing <hi>in vaine,</hi> or to <hi>no End</hi> and <hi>Purpoſe.</hi> In <hi>Policy;</hi> we <hi>hate</hi> thoſe <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> as <hi>Tyrannous,</hi> that are <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> and directed by <hi>no Law,</hi> but <hi>Will;</hi> where <hi>ſtar proratione voluntas,</hi> the <hi>Command</hi> ha's no <hi>aim</hi> or <hi>limit,</hi> but the meere <hi>luſt</hi> of the <hi>Commander.</hi> And have we not then good reaſon to beleeve, that, in <hi>Theologie,</hi> that <hi>Monſtrous ſin</hi> is moſt diametrically oppoſite to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>His Holy Spirit</hi> (and ſo the <hi>ſinne unpardonable</hi>) which is committed <hi>for it ſelfe,</hi> that is, not for any <hi>ſeeming</hi> either <hi>Profit, Pleaſure</hi> or <hi>Prefement</hi> that it preſents but, meerely for its <hi>Obliquity</hi> and <hi>Contrariety</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe?</hi> for my part, I think, we have. For what <hi>ſin</hi> can we imagine to be more <hi>ſinfull</hi> and <hi>malicious?</hi> what <hi>ſin</hi> to be more likely the <hi>ſin</hi> of the <hi>Devills,</hi> who, as they ſinn'd without a <hi>Tempter</hi> ſo, ſinn'd without any hope of <hi>Pardon</hi> or a <hi>Saviour?</hi> what <hi>ſin</hi> to be more likely that <hi>ſin unto Death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 5.16.</note> St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of, then this?</p>
            <p>In a word; Tis ſo conſonant to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that every thing ſhould bee made, not <hi>for it ſelfe</hi> but, for ſome <hi>Higher End,</hi> that <hi>Reaſon</hi> it ſelfe is taken from the ſeverall <hi>Ends</hi> of Things and their <hi>Affections</hi> to each other. For the <hi>Object</hi> of <hi>Logicke,</hi> or the <hi>Art of Reaſon</hi> is, not the T <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (that belongs to <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicks</hi> and <hi>Metaphyſicks</hi>) but, the T <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Creature,</hi> that whereby it <hi>relates</hi> to its <hi>Neighbours;</hi> and therefore <hi>Argumentum</hi> is well <hi>defined</hi> to be, <hi>quod ad aliquid arguendum affectum eſt,</hi> which we ſhall finde true of all the <hi>Topick Heads</hi> of <hi>Logick,</hi> if we exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min them. Hence too it is, that in our <hi>Naturall Logick</hi> and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> we call the <hi>end</hi> of a Thing its <hi>Reaſon;</hi> for ſo, when we aske the <hi>Reaſon, why</hi> ſuch a Thing was done, wee aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne the <hi>end</hi> or <hi>Deſigne</hi> thereof as the onely <hi>Reaſon</hi> for it.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:112525:20"/>
            <p>What <hi>Reaſon</hi> then can <hi>Man</hi> poſſibly phantſie to himſelf, why he ſhould be exempted from the <hi>common Condition</hi> of all <hi>Creatures,</hi> and flatter himſelfe to be made <hi>for no end,</hi> but <hi>himſelfe,</hi> ſince that is indeed to be made to <hi>no end at all?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 10.1.</note> Certainly he has no <hi>Reaſon</hi> for it. Nay, he ha's ſo much the leſſe <hi>Reaſon</hi> for it, by how much he is endued with <hi>Reaſon,</hi> above all other <hi>Creatures;</hi> for that ſhews us, even <hi>Logick</hi> it ſelfe cannot finde a <hi>Reaſon,</hi> why any <hi>Creature</hi> ſhould be made <hi>for it ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely then, ſo it is; <hi>Man</hi> cannot claime any <hi>Title</hi> to <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe;</hi> not to his <hi>Hands,</hi> to <hi>doe</hi> what he pleaſes; not to his <hi>Tongue,</hi> to <hi>ſpeake</hi> what he pleaſes: No, not to his very <hi>Heart,</hi> to <hi>thinke</hi> what he pleaſes: But acknowledge he muſt <hi>God</hi> to be the <hi>Lord Paramount</hi> of them all, and eſteeme <hi>himſelfe</hi> but as <hi>His Steward,</hi> to render an <hi>Accompt</hi> of them. Since then wee <hi>are</hi> and <hi>have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of our ſelves,</hi> but what we <hi>receiv'd</hi> from <hi>Him;</hi> if He require them (all) of us againe, let us by no meanes <hi>grutch</hi> them Him: We give Him but of <hi>His owne,</hi> and may He not <hi>doe what he pleaſes in ſuo,</hi> with that which is <hi>His owne? We</hi> thinke it good <hi>Reaſon</hi> in our <hi>owne caſe.</hi> But yet, if by His <hi>Grace</hi> wee can but doe this <hi>willingly,</hi> which is all we can pretend to, we ſhall in no wiſe faile of our <hi>Reward,</hi> ſeeing wee beſtow our <hi>Selves</hi> on <hi>Him,</hi> who is the <hi>Lord God of Recompences,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 51.56.</note> as Hee is ſtyl'd in the <hi>Prophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this may ſerve for a kinde of <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> which may <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſtop up the mouthes</hi> of all <hi>Gain-ſayers:</hi> But now to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thoſe that are more <hi>Equitable</hi> to this <hi>Duty,</hi> this perhaps may be ſufficient: That we ſee nothing made by any one, but who expects ſome <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Service</hi> from it. Indeed a thing may <hi>come from</hi> and <hi>breake out of one,</hi> which he will not <hi>owne,</hi> but be glad to be <hi>rid</hi> of; as <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> meaning to diſavow <hi>Julia</hi> for her lewdneſſe, would ſay, ſhe was, not his <hi>Daughter</hi> but, an <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume</hi> broken out from him; But <hi>make</hi> a thing one will not, but we will <hi>owne</hi> and be <hi>glad</hi> of it. And therefore <hi>God</hi> having <hi>made</hi> us by <hi>Creation, ownes</hi> us all for His <hi>Sons,</hi> as 'tis in the third of <hi>Luke</hi> and the laſt; but this is ſo long as we are <hi>Sons</hi> indeed, that is, ſuch as <hi>He made us, very good</hi> and <hi>ſerviceable</hi> to Him. Now <hi>ſerviceable</hi> to Him we cannot be, but by <hi>manifeſting</hi> His Glory; and manifeſt his <hi>Glory</hi> we cannot, but by manifeſting our owne <hi>Vileneſſe, Emptineſſe,</hi> and <hi>Nothing,</hi> which is to be done by <hi>Selfe-denyall;</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:112525:21"/>this <hi>Service</hi> therefore His <hi>making</hi> of us <hi>for Himſelf,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges us unto. If then we refuſe to performe it, and become a <hi>refractory Generation,</hi> then he diſavowes his owne <hi>Workmanſhip;</hi> ſayes, <hi>You are of your Father the Devill; your Father was an</hi> Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, <hi>your Mother an Hittite:</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 8.44. Ezek. 16.3.</note> Then He will not owne us for His <hi>Sons,</hi> as we would not Him for our <hi>Father,</hi> but proſcribe us for <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Darkneſſe, Sons of Belial,</hi> of the <hi>Devill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Title of <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Making</hi> we may ſee in things <hi>Ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate.</hi> Shall the <hi>Pot</hi> lift up its ſelfe againſt the <hi>Potter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 45.9.</note> ſayes the <hi>Prophet?</hi> that were <hi>monſtrous,</hi> ſeeing it is <hi>wholly his,</hi> and <hi>from him, Matter, Forme, and all,</hi> therefore in <hi>Reaſon,</hi> it ſhould be none but <hi>his,</hi> if for his turn, <hi>to uſe;</hi> if not, <hi>to breake it.</hi> Somewhat appeares in things animated with <hi>Senſe;</hi> though they be, not <hi>Makers</hi> but, <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of their Young ones Making yet, we ſee, ſo long as their <hi>Young</hi> are not able to ſhift for <hi>themſelves,</hi> they are in a kinde of <hi>Subjection</hi> to their <hi>Damme.</hi> But more may we ſee it in <hi>Men,</hi> who are preſum'd to do nothing without <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> We know, no title of <hi>Government</hi> is more juſt then of a <hi>Parent:</hi> no tye of <hi>Subjection</hi> more ſtrict, then of a <hi>Childe.</hi> Laſtly, wee may ſee it in matters <hi>Civill;</hi> If any one <hi>make</hi> a man in the World, as we terme it, we look, he ſhould be our <hi>Creature,</hi> our <hi>Servant</hi> for it. If he be not, what think wee of him? but that hee is <hi>uncivill, ungratefull,</hi> yea worſe then a <hi>Beaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hencethen we may ſee the <hi>Bond,</hi> that obliges him, and the reſt, to ſuch <hi>Obſervance;</hi> It is no other but that of <hi>Gratitude</hi> and <hi>Thankefulneſſe;</hi> A Vertue never ſufficiently to be <hi>commended;</hi> as the <hi>contrary, unthankfulnes,</hi> is never ſufficiently to be <hi>condemned.</hi> We ſay, <hi>Ingratum dixeris, omnia dixeris;</hi> and the <hi>Heathen</hi> man could ſay, <hi>In hoc Vitio nihil non mali ineſt,</hi> that 'tis the <hi>worſt</hi> of <hi>Vices,</hi> and contains <hi>all</hi> in it. What ſhould be the <hi>Reaſon?</hi> Surely, 'tis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but a <hi>Reſult</hi> of this <hi>Principle</hi> we pleade for; for <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> being an <hi>Acknowledgement of Dependance,</hi> is no ſmall part of <hi>Selfe-denyall,</hi> the <hi>root of all Vertue; Ingratitude</hi> being a <hi>diſavow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Dependance,</hi> is an <hi>Attributing all to our ſelves,</hi> the <hi>root of all evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, an <hi>Appendix</hi> to this <hi>Title</hi> of our <hi>Creation</hi> is that of Gods <hi>Preſervation</hi> of us; for that is no other but the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Creation</hi> continu'd and ſuſtain'd by that <hi>Word of God,</hi> whereby at
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112525:21"/>firſt He <hi>enacted the Law of Nature.</hi> And indeed, if we conſider the <hi>Creatures Mutability,</hi> from one thing into another, by reaſon it is <hi>Contiguous</hi> with, and <hi>conſiſts</hi> of, the <hi>Elements,</hi> that are <hi>alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> every moment by the <hi>Heavens,</hi> and everie moment <hi>alter</hi> and <hi>impaire</hi> us, more or leſſe, it will appeare, that God's <hi>Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of us is, though not <hi>formally</hi> yet, <hi>materially</hi> as <hi>benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> to us as our <hi>Creation,</hi> and therefore ought to inferre the ſame <hi>Right</hi> in us, and involve us in the ſame <hi>Obligation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this eſpecially, if we conſider 'tis ſuch a <hi>Preſervation</hi> of <hi>us,</hi> as withall includes a <hi>Benigne Providence</hi> in it: Such as, beſides our <hi>Being,</hi> provides for our <hi>well-being, well-being</hi> for our <hi>Bodies,</hi> in the things of <hi>this Life,</hi> and <hi>well-being</hi> for our <hi>ſoules,</hi> in the <hi>better things</hi> of the <hi>Life, to come.</hi> And this may lead us to that <hi>Other Title,</hi> whereby <hi>God</hi> claimes us to be, not <hi>our owne</hi> but, <hi>His,</hi> the <hi>Title</hi> of our <hi>Redemption.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt way God gave us a <hi>Perfect Being,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Pet. 2.25. Heb. 2.16.</hi> Qui curat eſſe, niſi propter Te, pro nihilo eſt, &amp; nihileſt. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nique quid-eſt homo, niſi quia Tu innotuiſti ei? Propter te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met ipſum, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, feciſti om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, &amp; qui ſibi eſſe vul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, non ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi, nihileſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit, inter om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia. Deum ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, &amp; mandata Ejus obſerva: hoc eſt, inquit. Omnis homo. Ergo, ſi hoc eſt omnis homo; abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hoc nihil Omnis homo. <hi>Bern. 20<hi rend="sup">0</hi>
                  </hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Cantic. Can. Luke 23.43.</hi>
               </note> by this he He <hi>reſtores</hi> it: We were all <hi>loſt</hi> in <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo loſt, that we declin'd and were falling away to <hi>Nothing:</hi> But then He that was the <hi>Good Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard and Biſhop of our ſoules,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to uſe the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles phraſe, caught hold of man,</hi> as he was even going, brought him <hi>backe againe</hi> and reſtor'd him to his firſt Perfection. For indeed our <hi>Redemption</hi> is nothing elſe but a <hi>Bringing of us backe</hi> to the firſt <hi>Point</hi> of our <hi>Creation,</hi> a <hi>re-inſtating us</hi> in the <hi>Condition</hi> of the <hi>Protoplaſts.</hi> So much is plainly intimated in thoſe words us'd by the <hi>Goſpel, Redemption, Renovation, Regeneration, Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and the like, all which argue a <hi>Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition</hi> of an act, a <hi>Returning</hi> to the <hi>Firſt Point.</hi> For what was that <hi>firſt Point,</hi> but <hi>Paradiſe?</hi> But that was the <hi>laſt Point</hi> of our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> our Saviour never making the leaſt mention of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe,</hi> till he was <hi>Sacrific'd</hi> on the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and then too He did not promiſe it till after <hi>all was fulfill'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The<note n="*" place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.29.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſe Man</hi> tells us, <hi>God at firſt made us upright,</hi> that is, in ſuch an eſtate wherein had we perſever'd, we had been <hi>happy:</hi> But then we <hi>ſought out many Inventions; We</hi> would needs take upon us to be <hi>ſeeking</hi> of our owne heads; and ſeeking <hi>many Inventions,</hi> therefore ſure not the <hi>Will of God,</hi> which, beſide that it was <hi>moſt One</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niforme,</hi> was <hi>obvious</hi> too, needed no <hi>ſeeking,</hi> being in our <hi>mouthes,</hi> yea in our <hi>hearts</hi> to <hi>doe it.</hi> Thus <hi>ſeeking theſe Inventions,</hi> and our <hi>Selves</hi> in them, we <hi>forſook God</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:112525:22"/>our <hi>Maker,</hi> and betook our <hi>Selves</hi> to His <hi>Enemy the Devill,</hi> by which <hi>ſeeking</hi> we even <hi>loſt</hi> our <hi>Selves,</hi> and ſo had <hi>periſhed</hi> for ever. But <hi>God</hi> was too <hi>mercifull</hi> to behold ſo great <hi>miſery</hi> without <hi>Pitty;</hi> out of His abundant <hi>Compaſſion</hi> therefore Hee ſent His <hi>Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 9.10.</note> 
               <hi>to ſeek and ſave that which was loſt.</hi> To ſeek us, He came into the <hi>World;</hi> and, to <hi>ſave</hi> us, He <hi>preacht ſalvation</hi> by His <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Doctrine,</hi> the <hi>Foundation</hi> whereof He laid in this <hi>Precept</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 4.2.</note> The <hi>Example</hi> of His <hi>Life</hi> began with a <hi>Faſt,</hi> and a large one, that of <hi>Forty dayes;</hi> His <hi>Doctrine</hi> began upon this <hi>Text,</hi>
               <note place="margin">&amp; 17.</note> 
               <hi>Repent for the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand:</hi> Now <hi>Faſting</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> are the <hi>Principall</hi> acts of <hi>Self-denyall</hi> and <hi>Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus doing He did, that which the <hi>Prophets</hi> foretold He came to doe:<note place="margin">Daniel 9.24. Amos 9.8.</note> 
               <hi>Finiſh the tranſgreſſion, and make an end of ſinnes:</hi> Or, as <hi>one of them</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>deſtroy the Kingdome of Sin from off the face of the earth.</hi> Whereas therefore the <hi>Devills Method</hi> in erecting this <hi>Kingdome</hi> was, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to <hi>ſcatter</hi> and, as I may ſay, <hi>rout</hi> the <hi>orderly works of God;</hi> whence it is, we read of ſome that were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.2.</note>, <hi>out of their places, others</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">&amp; <hi>verſes</hi> 6, 7, 11.</note>, <hi>out of their rankes</hi> and <hi>orders:</hi> Our <hi>Saviour,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 12.2. &amp; 2.110.</note>; The <hi>Leader Generall</hi> of our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> comming to <hi>ſet in order the Works of God</hi> againe, did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">1 John 3.8.</note>, as I told you out of St. <hi>John,</hi> in like manner <hi>ſcattered</hi> and <hi>rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> the <hi>workes of the Devill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 1.10.</note> that he might <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as another <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>recapitulate</hi> and <hi>ſet in ranke,</hi> under their proper <hi>Heads, all things in Heaven and Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee then, this Title of our <hi>Redemption,</hi> is that of our <hi>Creation re-inforc't,</hi> and therefore muſt needs argue <hi>Gods Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in us no leſſe then that, nay more by farre, becauſe a <hi>worke more Difficult;</hi> For in our <hi>Creation,</hi> God found no <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> and therfore by His <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> all things were made, as I may ſay, <hi>liquidly.</hi> It was not ſo in our <hi>Redemption:</hi> No, there He found great <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> ſuch as requir'd, not onely His <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> but, <hi>Sweating, Sighes, Groans,</hi> yea His very <hi>Death</hi> to Maſter.</p>
            <p>Now by His <hi>Death</hi> He laid downe a <hi>Price,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Price</hi> as <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd</hi> and <hi>purchac'd</hi> to Him all <hi>man-kinde</hi> ſo, that having <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd</hi> us by a <hi>Price,</hi> by the <hi>Law</hi> of all <hi>Nations,</hi> we ought to be,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:112525:22"/>not our owne but, His that bought us. And thus much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, in ſo many words: That <hi>we are,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.20.</note> not our own but, <hi>God's, becauſe redeem'd by a Price:</hi> whereupon he ſtraight infers, <hi>We ought to ſerve,</hi> not our ſelves but, <hi>God with our Bodies and our Soules, ſeeing they are His.</hi> If then we muſt <hi>ſerve Him</hi> with them both, certainly we muſt <hi>Deny our ſelves.</hi> For in all <hi>Reaſon,</hi> we ought to <hi>obey His Will,</hi> whoſe <hi>Servants</hi> we are; but, we ſee, our Text tells us, 'tis His <hi>Will,</hi> wee ſhould <hi>Deny our Selves;</hi> therefore <hi>Deny our Selves</hi> we muſt, becauſe of our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet, becauſe <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>Command</hi> of <hi>Him</hi> who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> of His <hi>Father;</hi> and our <hi>Deſigne</hi> in this <hi>Point</hi> is, not to <hi>Draw</hi> but, <hi>Lead</hi> men to this <hi>Duty:</hi> Neceſſary it is we ſhew you the <hi>Equity</hi> thereof: That the <hi>Injunction</hi> of this <hi>Duty</hi> flowes, not from the <hi>meere Will</hi> of our <hi>Redeemer</hi> but, from the <hi>Nature of our Redemption,</hi> which exacts no leſſe at our hands, if we meane to be <hi>Partakers</hi> of it. That we may <hi>partake</hi> of the <hi>Redemption</hi> wrought by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 'tis neceſſary we be in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as to <hi>partake of Adams Curſe,</hi> 'tis neceſſary, we be <hi>reputed in Him.</hi> But <hi>in Chriſt</hi> we cannot be otherwiſe then by <hi>Repreſentation,</hi> ſo therefore, and no otherwiſe are we <hi>reputed in Him.</hi> For, amongſt other things He is <hi>likened</hi> unto for this <hi>purpoſe,</hi> as <hi>a Head,</hi> a <hi>Root,</hi> an <hi>Elder Brother,</hi> one <hi>notable reſemblance</hi> of <hi>Him</hi> is to the <hi>Firſt Fruits;</hi> therefore more then once he is called the <hi>Firſt Fruits from the Dead,</hi> by vertue of whom wee <hi>partake,</hi> not the <hi>Corporall</hi> onely but alſo, the <hi>Spirituall Reſurrection:</hi> Now, we know, the <hi>Firſt Fruit</hi> is the <hi>Maſſe</hi> meerely by a <hi>Repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of it, as we may ſee in the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Fruits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15, 20, 21.</note> Lev. 23. 10, 11. but more plainly by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.14.18.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. <hi>If the firſt fruit,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>be holy, the Maſſe is alſo holy. Repreſented</hi> then we are <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Maſſe</hi> in the <hi>Firſt Fruit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.17.</note> and ſo in <hi>Him God is well pleaſed with us.</hi> But now <hi>repreſented</hi> we cannot be without ſome <hi>Similitude</hi> and <hi>Conformity;</hi> as a <hi>Picture</hi> cannot <hi>repreſent</hi> a <hi>Man,</hi> if it be no wayes like him. Accordingly, therefore, the <hi>Maſſe</hi> is ever like the <hi>Firſt fruits,</hi> the <hi>Firſt fruit</hi> being nothing elſe, but, as the <hi>Name</hi> imports, a certaine <hi>portion</hi> taken out of the <hi>Comon Maſſe</hi> or <hi>Heap:</hi> And ſo the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſayes, there muſt be a <hi>Conformity</hi> betwixt us and <hi>Chriſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.49.</note> that as <hi>we have borne the Image of the earthly Adam, ſo we muſt beare the Image of the Heavenly.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:112525:23"/>
            <p>Now to what <hi>Image</hi> of Chriſt muſt wee be <hi>conform'd?</hi> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> tells us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. to the <hi>Image of his ſuffering,</hi> that ſo He may be, as the <hi>Firſt fruits</hi> ſo, the <hi>Firſt born amongſt many Brethren.</hi> As He, <hi>being in the form of God, and accompting it no robbery to be equall to Him,</hi> yet <hi>tooke upon Him the Image of a ſervant; humbled, emptied, diſpleaſed,</hi> that is, to uſe his own term here, <hi>Denyed Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi> for our ſakes, that were his <hi>Enemies:</hi> ſo we, who moſt tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are <hi>Nothing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 6.3. Eſaiah 40.17.</note> yea <hi>leſſe then Nothing and Vanity,</hi> of our ſelves, ſhould in acknowledgment thereof, <hi>humble, empty, diſpleaſe, yea crucifie our ſelves</hi> for His ſake, who <hi>firſt loved us,</hi> and gave Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for us.</p>
            <p>To this, ſayes St. <hi>Paul,</hi> we are <hi>predeſtinated</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note>; and in another place, he ſayes, <hi>we are appointed</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.3.</note>. To this, ſayes St. <hi>Peter, we are called</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1 Peter 2.21.</note>. Hence proceede thoſe frequent <hi>Axiomes</hi> of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; If we be planted into the Likeneſſe of His Death, we ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the Likeneſſe of His Reſurrection</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Romans 6.5.</note>. <hi>If we ſuffer with Him, we ſhal Reigne with Him</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Rom 8.17.</note>. <hi>If we Dye with Him, we ſhall live with Him. If we Deny Him, He will Deny us</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.11.12.</note>; and the like. Hence alſo thoſe that are His <hi>true Brethren,</hi> are ſaid to <hi>beare about with them, the Brands</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Gal. 6.17.</note>, <hi>the Dying of the Lord Jeſus</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.10.</note>, <hi>to be crucified together with Him</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note>; yea <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>viciſſim replere,</hi> that is, <hi>by way of corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence, to fill up againe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Leavings,</hi> as I may ſay, <hi>of the afflictions of Chriſt in their own fleſh</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.24.</note>.</p>
            <p>And this, one would thinke, might be ſufficient to ſtop the mouth of all <hi>falſe reaſoning;</hi> But yet we cannot expect it ſhould doe it ſo, but that <hi>Nature,</hi> not yet ſatisfied in the <hi>Point,</hi> will ſet <hi>Reaſon</hi> on worke to confute what ha's been ſaid; And at length, it is conceived, enough may be bolted out of <hi>Scripture</hi> it ſelfe to doe it.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.29.</note> For does not St. <hi>Paul</hi> make the <hi>Love of our ſelves,</hi> our <hi>motive</hi> to love our <hi>wives,</hi> becauſe <hi>no man ever yet bated his owne fleſh?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 19.19.</note> And does not our Saviour, <hi>out of the Law,</hi> make it the <hi>Rule</hi> of our <hi>Love to our Neighbours,</hi> commanding us to <hi>love them, as we ſhould doe our own ſelves?</hi> Now, if it be ſo, then certainly we are not to <hi>Deny our ſelves,</hi> for to <hi>love</hi> and to <hi>Deny</hi> our <hi>ſelves</hi> are <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariant</hi> acts; <hi>Love,</hi> that, tends to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion; Denyall,</hi> to <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this we anſwer <hi>fully,</hi> (having ſomewhat toucht it before) that ſo much of us is in this place term'd <hi>our ſelves,</hi> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo much of us, &amp; no more to be <hi>Denyed,</hi> as is <hi>Contrary</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:112525:23"/>to the <hi>Will of God.</hi> Now the <hi>Will of God</hi> is,<note place="margin">In this Point.</note> as I ſhewed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven now, that we ſhould <hi>preſerve our ſelves,</hi> our <hi>Being,</hi> and our <hi>Wel-being</hi> too, by all <hi>Meanes</hi> poſſible; But <hi>ever provided</hi> thoſe <hi>Meanes</hi> be <hi>Honeſt,</hi> that is, ſuch as <hi>He bath ſet us out plainely in His Word,</hi> which is <hi>His will.</hi> Now this makes nothing againſt <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> for here we muſt obſerve, that in <hi>loving</hi> our <hi>ſelves</hi> ſo only and no more, we are to <hi>Deny our ſelves,</hi> ſeeing this we are not to do in love and obedience to our <hi>ſelves,</hi> but only to the <hi>Will of God.</hi> Thus much, I ſay, of neceſſity we muſt <hi>note</hi> for this; Becauſe if, whenſoever it ſhall pleaſe <hi>God</hi> to make an <hi>extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry exception</hi> to thoſe <hi>Ordinary Meanes,</hi> as ſometime he ha's done, and does ſtill to the <hi>Martyrs</hi> and <hi>Witneſſes</hi> of His <hi>Trueth,</hi> if then, we ſhall <hi>love</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> our <hi>Lives</hi> or any thing that we have, we take the ready way to <hi>loſe</hi> them for ever; but if we <hi>loſe</hi> them, we ſhall indeed <hi>ſave</hi> them, as our Saviour tells us. So then,<note place="margin">Verſe 25.</note> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> can object, it remaines a firme <hi>Concluſion,</hi> we muſt <hi>Deny our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo, we hope, enough hath beene ſaid, to convince any <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/>
               <hi>Reaſonable</hi> man of the <hi>Equity</hi> &amp; <hi>Congruity</hi> of this <hi>Precept</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall.</hi> But yet, becauſe there are many <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable</hi> men in the world, that will not live by <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but by <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Experience,</hi> and therefore will nor doe nor beleeve what they finde to offend their <hi>ſenſes;</hi> for theſe 'tis fit we uſe ſome <hi>forcible Club-Logicke,</hi> that may <hi>cogere intrare,</hi> in a ſort, <hi>compell them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in</hi> and <hi>obey</hi> it.</p>
            <p>Now this we cannot better doe, then by laying before them the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Selfe-denyall.</hi> But this, not a <hi>Categoricall</hi> or <hi>Fatall</hi> one but, an <hi>Hypotheticall, Conditional</hi> one, one that may very well be <hi>Voluntary</hi> too. For 'tis true, this <hi>Precept linckt</hi> with the <hi>Precedent words,</hi> by that <hi>vinculum connexivum, If</hi> and <hi>then; If any one will come after Me, then let him Deny himſelfe,</hi> makes but a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexe Axiome,</hi> and ſo it requires not <hi>trueth of parts; No man may come after Him,</hi> and ſo, <hi>no man may Deny himſelfe;</hi> this, to ſpeake <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is <hi>poſſible.</hi> The <hi>Neceſſity</hi> therfore of this <hi>Precept</hi> riſes, not from its <hi>truth of parts</hi> but, from the <hi>Neceſſary Connexion of its parts;</hi> That, if the <hi>Antecedent</hi> be <hi>granted,</hi> the <hi>Conſequent</hi> cannot be <hi>denyed,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Neceſſary dependence</hi> that is betwixt them; the one being of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> (commonly) the other of the <hi>Effect,</hi> and no ſtronger <hi>dependence</hi> then of the <hi>Effect</hi> upon the <hi>Cauſe;</hi> For
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:112525:24"/>the <hi>Cauſe</hi> gives it <hi>exiſtence,</hi> and therefore, if the <hi>Cauſe</hi> be and be <hi>Operative,</hi> (as it ſhould be) the <hi>Effect</hi> muſt <hi>follow</hi> thereupon. Now who is there, at leaſt what <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> but will <hi>grant</hi> the <hi>Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent part</hi> to be <hi>true,</hi> That <hi>We ought to come after Chriſt?</hi> if he will not,<note place="margin">John 6.68.</note> that of <hi>Peter</hi> muſt <hi>compell</hi> him, <hi>Whither ſhall we go from Thee? Thou haſt the words of eternall Life. Thou,</hi> and <hi>Thou onely,</hi> ſo he afterwards expounded it:<note place="margin">Acts 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>There is no other Name,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>under Heaven, whereby we can be ſav'd, but by the Name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus onely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then, if we grant the <hi>Antecedent neceſſary,</hi> we muſt not hold the <hi>Conſequent</hi> a matter of <hi>Indifferency,</hi> as the <hi>Maſters</hi> of our <hi>Logick</hi> tell us. No, we ſee, theſe <hi>Parts</hi> ſtand not together up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on termes of <hi>Indifferency,</hi> but of plaine <hi>Neceſſity:</hi> 'Tis not, <hi>If any one will come after Me,</hi> 'tis <hi>expedient,</hi> he <hi>Deny himſelfe,</hi> but he <hi>muſt Deny himſelfe;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>let him Deny himſelfe.</hi> which <hi>let</hi> we muſt not take to be a word of <hi>Permiſſion,</hi> as if for this matter Chriſt did <hi>let</hi> us'doe as we pleas'd, that's the <hi>Poverty</hi> of our <hi>Language,</hi> but (as it is in the <hi>Originall) Imperativè,</hi> hee <hi>muſt Deny himſelfe,</hi> 'tis ſo <hi>commanded,</hi> ſo <hi>decreed.</hi> Now any <hi>Decree</hi> or <hi>Command</hi> are manifeſt arguments of the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of the thing <hi>Commanded,</hi> either in reſpect of the <hi>Commanders</hi> Will, or the <hi>Importance</hi> of the <hi>Thing commanded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt; As in <hi>Nature</hi> there is no greater obligation then <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> which therefore is ſaid to be <hi>ſtronger then any Law,</hi> becauſe it cannot be <hi>bound</hi> by any, ſo in <hi>Policy</hi> there is no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Charge</hi> then a <hi>Command,</hi> and, that which ever ſhould attend it, the <hi>effectuall proſecution</hi> of it. And then certainly the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God,</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> muſt needs impoſe on us the <hi>greateſt Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> that can be. For we ever meaſure the force of a <hi>Command</hi> by his <hi>Authority</hi> that <hi>Commands</hi> it, by his <hi>Power</hi> to <hi>Reward</hi> it, if <hi>obey'd;</hi> or <hi>Puniſh it,</hi> if <hi>neglected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for <hi>Gods Authority,</hi> He is our <hi>Creator,</hi> we His <hi>Creatures;</hi> He our <hi>King,</hi> we <hi>His Subjects;</hi> He our <hi>Lord,</hi> we His <hi>Vaſſals;</hi> He our <hi>Father,</hi> we His <hi>Sonnes;</hi> yea, He is <hi>every thing</hi> to us, that may challenge either <hi>Soveraignty</hi> in Him to <hi>Command,</hi> or <hi>Humility</hi> in us to <hi>obey:</hi> Therfore we ought to <hi>obey</hi> Him in this <hi>Precept,</hi> were it for nothing elſe but for thoſe ſo many and ſtrict <hi>Relations</hi> betwixt Him and us.</p>
            <p>But, alas! if this were all, there were but ſmall hold to be taken
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:112525:24"/>of us; theſe are but weake <hi>Motives,</hi> and farre in feriour to the <hi>force</hi> of a <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> eſpecially to a mind void of all <hi>Ingenuity;</hi> therefore, to theſe, God ha's a <hi>two-fold Power,</hi> which indeed are the maine <hi>ſinewes of Government</hi> and <hi>cart-ropes of Obedience: Power</hi> on the one ſide to <hi>Reward</hi> and <hi>allure</hi> us; on the other ſide, to <hi>Puniſh</hi> and <hi>affright</hi> us. His <hi>Reward,</hi> the <hi>greateſt</hi> that can be imagin'd, the <hi>Eternall Fruition of Himſelfe,</hi> and therewith <hi>Everlaſting Happineſſe;</hi> His <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> the terribleſt that can be devis'd, <hi>Exile for ever from his Preſence,</hi> and therewith <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Miſery.</hi> I trow, theſe will, if duely ponder'd, impoſe on us a <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of <hi>obeying</hi> with a witneſſe, <hi>velfaciendo, vel pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo;</hi> either by <hi>doing</hi> His <hi>Will, of our ſelves;</hi> or by <hi>enduring it upon our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, were this a <hi>Precept</hi> of <hi>Peremptory Will</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> a <hi>Precept of meere Soveraignty,</hi> yet did it conclude us ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>neceſſitate Praecepti,</hi> by reaſon of that <hi>Neceſſity</hi> the <hi>Command</hi> of Chriſt impoſes on us. But this is, not ſuch a <hi>Precept</hi> but, as I ſhew'd you, impos'd upon us on <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rgent</hi> and <hi>Weighty Reaſon;</hi> It is the <hi>Conſequent</hi> to an <hi>Antecedent,</hi> and ſuch an <hi>Antecedent</hi> as is of the <hi>higheſt neceſſity</hi> that can be, therefore we muſt needs more ſtrongly be concluded under it <hi>neceſſitate Medii,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that <hi>Neceſſity</hi> that is in the <hi>Thing</hi> it ſelfe, for the <hi>obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that end</hi> for which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath <hi>preſcribed</hi> it.</p>
            <p>And indeed a <hi>plaine neceſſity</hi> there is, we ſhoùld <hi>Deny our Selves,</hi> on <hi>Suppoſition</hi> that wee meane to <hi>follow and come after Chriſt.</hi> For, we know, <hi>Two contrary Extreames</hi> cannot meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; but, if the one be <hi>approach't unto,</hi> the other muſt needs be <hi>forſaken:</hi> As for example, <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Canaan</hi> were <hi>two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Extreames</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> while they were paſſing from the <hi>one</hi> to the <hi>other,</hi> ſo that, to goe towards the <hi>Land of Canaan,</hi> they muſt needs goe out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and to return to <hi>Egypt,</hi> they muſt needs forſake the <hi>Land of Canaan.</hi> Now <hi>Chriſt</hi> and our <hi>Selves</hi> are two ſuch <hi>Extreames,</hi> and indeed were <hi>typified</hi> by them; <hi>Chriſt</hi> and His <hi>Kingdome</hi> by the <hi>Land of Promiſe;</hi> our <hi>Selves,</hi> and our <hi>owne Luſts</hi> and <hi>Wills</hi> by the <hi>Fleſh-pots</hi> of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi> Therefore as they could not tend to the <hi>one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ille negat Chriſtum qui ſe non abnegat ipſum. <hi>Geth.</hi>
               </note> but they muſt needs recede from the <hi>other,</hi> no more can we <hi>follow</hi> or <hi>come after Chriſt,</hi> but we muſt needs <hi>Deny, renounce</hi> and <hi>forſake our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Chriſt</hi> and our <hi>ſelves</hi> are two ſuch <hi>Contrary Extreames</hi> is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:112525:25"/>eaſie to ſee, from their <hi>Contrary Originalls, Contrary Effects.</hi> Our <hi>Selves</hi> are from the <hi>Earth, Earthly</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.47.</note>, <hi>Carnall, Senſuall;</hi> but <hi>Chriſt is a Spirit</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">&amp; Verſe 45.</note>, and that from <hi>Heaven, Heavenly.</hi> Our <hi>Selves me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate evill, nothing but evill, and that continually; we are all gone aſtray and become abominable, there is none that doth good, no not one</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 3.11, 12, 13, &amp;c.</note>: But <hi>Chriſt did all things well</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Mark. 7.37.</note>, <hi>there was no guile found in his mouth</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.22.</note>, in his hand much leſſe: <hi>he was without all Sin</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note>, <hi>all Spot</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note>, <hi>for He fulfilled all Righteouſneſſe</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Matth. 3.15.</note>. There is <hi>no Communion then between Light and Darkneſſe</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.14.</note>, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, betwixt <hi>Chriſt and Belial,</hi> that is, our <hi>Yoakleſse Selves,</hi> that wee ſhould ever hope <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as he there ſpeakes, to <hi>joyne two ſuch Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> and make them <hi>draw in the ſame Yoak together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this <hi>Contrariety</hi> it comes, that <hi>every one,</hi> that in any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>followes Chriſt,</hi> feeles a manifeſt <hi>conftict</hi> in himſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Himſelfe,</hi> the <hi>Old Man</hi> and the <hi>New;</hi> the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and the <hi>Spirit;</hi> the <hi>Seed of the Woman</hi> and the <hi>Seed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> drawing contrary wayes in him.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> Hence it is, Chriſt tells us, <hi>He came to ſend</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10.34.</note> 
               <hi>not Peace on Earth, but the Sword:</hi> What <hi>Sword?</hi> that <hi>devouring Sword of Warre,</hi> to maſter every one that is our <hi>weaker?</hi> God forbid we ſhould once thinke it: No, but the <hi>Sword of the Word of the Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.17 James 4.1.</note> to fight againſt our <hi>Luſts</hi> that make an <hi>irreconcileable War in our Members.</hi> For our <hi>Luſts</hi> like <hi>Sturdy Beggers,</hi> if <hi>Chriſt Deny them</hi> in us, <hi>fight ſtraight,</hi> and there begins the fray.</p>
            <p>This <hi>fight</hi> is more or leſſe, one time or other, in <hi>every one</hi> that hath any thing of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in him. He therefore that enjoyes <hi>perpetuall Peace</hi> within him, as the <hi>Heathen man</hi> ſaid of him that liv'd in perpetuall <hi>Solitude, aut Deus eſt aut Daemon;</hi> either he is a <hi>Saint in Heaven,</hi> or a <hi>Devill</hi> in <hi>Hell;</hi> either perfectly <hi>united to God and Chriſt</hi> and out of that <hi>World into which</hi> our Saviour ſaid, <hi>He ſent no Peace;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 2.16.</note> Or elſe he is <hi>wholly his owne ſelfe,</hi> his <hi>heart hardened,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5, 6. Eph. 2.1.</note> his <hi>Conſcience ſeared,</hi> and generally caſt into a <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſenſe,</hi> ſo that he may well be ſaid to be <hi>dead, while hee is alive, dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes,</hi> and in the very <hi>verge</hi> of that place, which is call'd the <hi>Second Death; from which, Good Lord! deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here ſome may likely interpoſe; Grant there bee ſuch a <hi>Contrariety</hi> betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and our <hi>Selves,</hi> that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be brought <hi>together,</hi> perhaps wee may runne a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:112525:25"/>
               <hi>Midle courſe</hi> though, may <hi>partake with either</hi> of them, and ſo <hi>forſake neither.</hi> No, by no meanes: This will not be taken for a <hi>Following</hi> or <hi>Comming after Chriſt,</hi> which is ſuppos'd to bee with <hi>Conſtancy</hi> and <hi>Reſolution,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 18.21.</note> but rather a <hi>Halting between two opinions.</hi> For what is <hi>Halting</hi> but a default of <hi>one</hi> of our <hi>legges,</hi> when we can uſe but <hi>one of them at once?</hi> when therefore we lend <hi>one legge to one Opinion, another to the contrary;</hi> one to <hi>God,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to <hi>Belial;</hi> one to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> another <hi>to our ſelves,</hi> muſt we not needs <hi>limpe</hi> there while, yea <hi>halt down-right?</hi> it muſt needs be ſo, it cannot otherwiſe chuſe. But, if we doe ſo, we cannot follow <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which he Himſelfe expounds here to be, not a <hi>Halting</hi> but, a <hi>Comming after Him,</hi> with <hi>uprightneſſe</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance.</hi> For indeed <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>jealous</hi> of any <hi>Partner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20.5.</note> muſt have <hi>all</hi> or <hi>none,</hi> becauſe <hi>all</hi> is but <hi>too little for him,</hi> both our feet too <hi>weak</hi> to <hi>follow</hi> Him.</p>
            <p>Hence it was He forbad <hi>mongrell Procreations, Miſcellany Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,</hi> and <hi>Lintſie-Woolſie Garments,</hi> under the <hi>Law;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 19.19.</note> that He threatned ſo many <hi>woes</hi> againſt <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> under the <hi>Goſpel;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 23.13. Rev. 2.15.16.</note> that He exclaim'd on <hi>Laodicea</hi> for her <hi>Luke-warmeneſſe,</hi> and, as if he had been <hi>ſick at ſtomach</hi> of her, threatned he would <hi>Spue her out of his mouth,</hi> the effect of <hi>luke-warme water.</hi> Hence he found fault with <hi>Peter,</hi> becauſe <hi>comming to Him,</hi> he did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Matth. 14.31.</note> 
               <hi>looke two wayes,</hi> or <hi>aſquint,</hi> as proceeding from a ſmall <hi>Faith</hi> (and <hi>Love</hi> too or <hi>Self-denyall.</hi>) By all which it manifeſtly appeares, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> &amp; our ſelves are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Contraries</hi> without any <hi>Meane</hi> at all betwixt them: that which our Saviour <hi>Himſelfe</hi> tells us, ſaying, <hi>Whoſoever is not with me is</hi> contra,<note place="margin">Matth. 12.30. Mark 9.39.</note> 
               <hi>Contrary to Me.</hi> And likewiſe, <hi>Whoſoever is not contrary to Me is with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhewn the <hi>Poſſibility, Congruity,</hi> and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> our <hi>Obedience</hi> to this <hi>Precept of Self-denyall.</hi> And this indeed ſeemes enough to <hi>elicit</hi> our act of <hi>Obedience</hi> thereunto: But yet, becauſe 'tis not <hi>one act or two</hi> that can entitle us to a <hi>vertue,</hi> but <hi>many Acts</hi> are requir'd to the begetting of a <hi>Habit;</hi> and <hi>many Acts</hi> cannot be exercis'd without they be done <hi>cheerfully,</hi> which is the <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that in all our <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> God more eſpecially <hi>requires the Heart;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 23.26.</note> therefore yet have we <hi>two Arguments</hi> behinde, to win our <hi>Hearts,</hi> if it be poſſible, to doe, what <hi>muſt be done, cheerfully:</hi> And thoſe two are, firſt the <hi>Excellency of this Precept an it ſelfe;</hi> then its <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility,</hi> to all thoſe that <hi>practice</hi> it.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:112525:26"/>
            <p>That this <hi>Precept</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Underſtand this of this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept as it is purely Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall that is, enjoyning us the Denyall of things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Indirſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent.</note> is more <hi>Sublime</hi> and <hi>Excellent,</hi> then any in the <hi>Law,</hi> will appeare hence, That this <hi>Precept</hi> bids us <hi>Deny our Selves,</hi> yea even in that which the <hi>Law permitted</hi> to us, whereas <hi>the Law</hi> rather bade us <hi>ſeek our ſelves,</hi> what elſe is the deſire of a <hi>Temporall Reward</hi> but an effect of <hi>Self-love?</hi> Which, though it be not <hi>Vitious,</hi> being done in <hi>relation</hi> to a <hi>Promiſe</hi> yet, certainly cannot be ſo <hi>excellent</hi> as to embrace <hi>Vertue</hi> for it <hi>ſelfe.</hi> But now <hi>the Law,</hi> that, makes the <hi>Hope</hi> of a <hi>Reward</hi> the <hi>Chiefe Motive</hi> of <hi>Obedience;</hi> whereas the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> though it have its <hi>Reward,</hi> and a farre <hi>greater</hi> one then that of <hi>the Law:</hi> (for indeed this is the <hi>Subſtance</hi> whereof that was but the <hi>ſhadow</hi>) yet does it not bid us looke at the <hi>Reward</hi> as ſuch, but doe the thing <hi>for it ſelfe:</hi> or rather, to ſpeake more clearely, it tells us <hi>the Reward</hi> we are to doe the <hi>Duty</hi> for is <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o-incident</hi> with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Duty it ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 11. Rom 8 15.</note> as I ſhew'd you before out of <hi>John</hi> 17.3. Hence it is, <hi>the Law,</hi> according to the <hi>Apoſtles intimation,</hi> is by the <hi>Schooles</hi> truely call'd <hi>Lex timoris, the Law of Feare; Feare</hi> as well of <hi>loſing</hi> the <hi>reward,</hi> as of <hi>enduring Puniſhment:</hi> But the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> no leſſe truely,<note place="margin">1 John 4.18.</note> call'd <hi>Lex amoris, the Law of Love,</hi> of <hi>Love that once perfected caſteth out Feare,</hi> and, as <hi>Ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ard</hi> truely ſayes, <hi>Vires non ſumit de ſpe, is no whit fortifi'd by Hope of a Reward.</hi> Hence our Saviour call'd thoſe that obey <hi>meerly</hi> for <hi>Temporall Reward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 10.12, 13</note> 
               <hi>Mercenaries,</hi> (thereby intimating the <hi>Phariſaĭcal Doctors of the Law</hi>) and ſayes, <hi>thoſe,</hi> when the <hi>Wolfe</hi> came, <hi>would flee away,</hi> as loving <hi>themſelves</hi> more then their <hi>Flocke: But</hi> the <hi>Good Shepheard,</hi> ſaies he, that <hi>loves his Flocke,</hi> and is <hi>lov'd of them</hi> (ſuch as <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi> was) will dye firſt, before he will doe ſo.</p>
            <p>The plaine <hi>Truth</hi> is; if we <hi>love onely</hi> becauſe we are <hi>loved, obey God</hi> becauſe he obeyes our <hi>Deſires,</hi> and <hi>truſt Him,</hi> becauſe Hee gives us His <hi>Counterbond to ſave us harmleſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.46, 47.</note> I may well ask, with our Saviour, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>What extraordinary matter doe we?</hi> What more then <hi>Publicanes,</hi> then <hi>wicked men;</hi> yea then the very <hi>Brutes themſelves,</hi> whom yet we thinke our <hi>Inferiours?</hi> But if, out of the <hi>love of God,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe it ſelfe,</hi> we <hi>obey,</hi> for <hi>nothing elſe,</hi> then indeed, we doe ſomewhat <hi>worthy of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of our Maſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor 3.7, 8, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Perfection</hi> of His <hi>Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is it that made the <hi>Miniſtration of the Goſpell</hi> farre <hi>more glorious then that of the Law;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5.20.</note> this makes <hi>our Righteouſneſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:112525:26"/>that of,</hi> the <hi>Lawes</hi> ſtricteſt <hi>Sectaries, the Scribes and Phariſees.</hi> Whence come all thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe <hi>Tranſcendent Precepts,</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> but from this <hi>Precept of Selfe-denyall?</hi> How ſhould we come, not ſo much as to <hi>ſpeake haſtily to our Brother:</hi> not ſo much as to <hi>looke upon a woman to luſt after her:</hi> not ſo much as to <hi>affirme or deny any thing, more then by yea and nay,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we <hi>deny our ſelves?</hi> How ſhould we <hi>love our enemies;</hi> doe our <hi>Almes, Faſt and Pray,</hi> all in <hi>Private; Never Cenſure our Brother, never be ſollicitous for food or raiment,</hi> but <hi>wholly depend upon God for them,</hi> if ſhut up from the <hi>Meanes,</hi> without <hi>Selfe-denyall? Do theſe things,</hi> ſayes our Saviour, <hi>that ye may be perfect:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5.48.</note> A plain <hi>Argument,</hi> theſe <hi>Precepts</hi> are the <hi>Perfection</hi> of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> and the want of theſe, the <hi>Imperfection of the Law,</hi> which <hi>brought nothing to Perfection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.19.</note> as did the <hi>Goſpell</hi> by bringing in a <hi>Better Hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But meane time, that I may be rightly underſtood, I intend not this to <hi>diſparage</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> or its <hi>Work</hi> in any one whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; We acknowledge, the <hi>Law</hi> is <hi>holy, juſt,</hi> and <hi>good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.12. 1 Tim. 1.8. Gal. 3.24, 25.</note> ſo it be <hi>uſed lawfully:</hi> that is, as a <hi>Pedagogue,</hi> to <hi>bring Children on to Chriſt:</hi> not as a <hi>Doctor, to build up perfect men in Chriſt.</hi> We ſay further; It is, not onely <hi>Good</hi> but, <hi>Neceſſary</hi> for thoſe that would <hi>come after Chriſt;</hi> becauſe none can <hi>come to Him,</hi> much leſſe <hi>come after Him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 6.44.</note> 
               <hi>but thoſe whom God the Father drawes firſt by the Law:</hi> but <hi>thoſe that believe, God is, and is a Rewarder of them that ſeek Him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> and ſo conſequently a <hi>Chaſtiſer</hi> of them that <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Him.</hi> It muſt needs be then, thoſe that obey as <hi>Servants</hi> doe <hi>well,</hi> for they <hi>rebell</hi> not: but thoſe that obey as <hi>Sons,</hi> they do <hi>much better,</hi> for they obey <hi>indeed,</hi> with their <hi>whole Hearts</hi> and <hi>mindes,</hi> without reſpect to <hi>themſelves.</hi> What ſhall wee ſay then? but, that thoſe who are <hi>brought on</hi> by the <hi>Law,</hi> and ingraffed into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> may ſay to the <hi>law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.1, 2, 3, &amp;c.</note> as the <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes</hi> to that <hi>Woman,</hi> John 4.42. <hi>We do no longer believe now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of thy ſpeech; for we our ſelves have heard and ſeen that this is the Chriſt, the Saviour of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let this ſuffice to have ſhewn the <hi>excellency</hi> of this <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of it: But now to ſhew you the <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Excellency</hi> of it in the <hi>Practiſe</hi> and <hi>Exerciſe,</hi> we will in the <hi>laſt place</hi> lay before you briefely and ſuccinctly, the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility</hi> thereof. In which doing,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.22.</note> we ſhall <hi>become all things
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:112525:27"/>to all men, that ſo we may gaine ſome:</hi> we ſhall direct our ſpeech as well to thoſe that are but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as to thoſe that are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as well to the <hi>Hearers</hi> of the <hi>loweſt,</hi> as of the <hi>higheſt Fourm:</hi> For ſuch <hi>Auditors</hi> I'm ſure we have moſt cauſe to looke for in this <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>-Romuli</hi> we live in; at leaſt, to <hi>calculate</hi> our ſpeech to <hi>ſuch</hi> muſt needs be the ſafeſt way, becauſe then it may ſerve <hi>indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently</hi> for all <hi>Capacities</hi> whatſoever.</p>
            <p>But here I might well loſe my ſelf, ſhould I hoiſe up full ſaile, to paſſe through the <hi>Ocean</hi> of <hi>Particulars:</hi> Let it be ſufficient, if we can deſcry them <hi>afarre off,</hi> and ſo <hi>draw up</hi> all. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> that <hi>Godlineſſe is profitable for all things:</hi> which, if it be true, as it is moſt certaine, it muſt be as true of <hi>Selfe-denyall,</hi> ſince as we have ſhew'd abundantly, no <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> without it. The <hi>Truth</hi> then of both he ſhewes us in the <hi>ſure Foundation</hi> of <hi>Gods Fidelity,</hi> who hath <hi>promis'd to it all things,</hi> as well the things of <hi>this Life</hi> as of that <hi>which is to come.</hi> For the <hi>Promiſe</hi> we ſend you no whither, but to the tenth of St. <hi>Markes Goſpel,</hi> Verſe 29.30. Where <hi>for this Life,</hi> our <hi>Saviour promiſes, Whoſoever hath forſaken Houſes, or Lands, or Wife, &amp;c. ſhall receive an Hundred fold, with Perſecution:</hi> For that <hi>which is to come, and,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>in the World to come, Life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Fidelity</hi> of the <hi>Promiſer;</hi> we muſt conſider the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> is to be <hi>taken</hi> of us, as 'twas <hi>meant</hi> by him that <hi>made</hi> it: And how was that? <hi>literally?</hi> as if we ſhould receive the ſame things <hi>in ſpecie, in kinde, a Hundred fold?</hi> Surely it cannot be. For, beſides that we never read nor heard of any that <hi>receiv'd</hi> ſo much, it were <hi>abſurd</hi> to believe, He <hi>promis'd a Hundred wives for one, Polygamy</hi> never heard of, whereas even <hi>Bigamy</hi> is forbidden <hi>by the Goſpel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 19.9.</note> And ſure, that he meant it not <hi>literally,</hi> is more then evident by that <hi>Clauſe</hi> affixt unto the <hi>Promiſe, with Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</hi> For, did He meane it <hi>literally,</hi> what elſe were this but to give <hi>the thing Promiſed</hi> with one hand, and <hi>take it away</hi> with the other? it were like an <hi>Abatement</hi> in a faire <hi>Coat of Armes,</hi> yea it were <hi>Contradictio</hi> in <hi>Adjecto,</hi> and <hi>Additament Contradicting</hi> what before he <hi>Promis'd.</hi> I wonder, what are <hi>all this Worlds goods</hi> with <hi>Perſecution,</hi> when we can neither joy in, nor <hi>enjoy</hi> them, as dayly experience ſhewes us? What is <hi>meat</hi> to the <hi>Sick,</hi> that cannot <hi>eate</hi> it? what <hi>Muſick</hi> to the <hi>Deaf,</hi> that cannot <hi>hear</hi> it?
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:112525:27"/>or <hi>Beauty</hi> to the <hi>Blinde,</hi> that cannot <hi>behold</hi> it? Or ſhould we think, our Saviour meant us thoſe things, as <hi>Covetous</hi> men ſeek for <hi>Wealth,</hi> to <hi>keep,</hi> but not to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> them, (though <hi>Perſecution</hi> will not allow us that neither) yet were this but to <hi>delude</hi> us; For ſince all things here are given us, <hi>ut utamur, non fruamur,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we ſhould <hi>uſe,</hi> not <hi>enjoy,</hi> them, we could not but, with <hi>Covetou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men, want</hi> as well what we <hi>had,</hi> as what we <hi>had not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now taking this <hi>Promiſe ſpiritually,</hi> in an <hi>Anagogical ſenſe,</hi> we can eaſily reconcile it with <hi>Perſecution,</hi> were it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full here to ſhew it, ſo eaſily that, as we ſhall make appeare, it will be a hard matter not to ſuppoſe <hi>Perſecution,</hi> or that which is <hi>tantummount,</hi> to the <hi>right under ſtanding of it.</hi> Surely then our Saviour's meaning was, Thoſe that <hi>parted with</hi> thoſe things there reckon'd up, ſhould <hi>receive the ſame,</hi> not in <hi>Kinde</hi> but, in <hi>Worth</hi> and <hi>Value a Hundred fold,</hi> even that which every one <hi>aimes at</hi> in the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of thoſe things.</p>
            <p>For this is certaine; Every man, in the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of thoſe things, ſeeks for <hi>Good</hi> unto himſelfe: this <hi>Good</hi> he is never <hi>ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd</hi> with, till it become <hi>Summum,</hi> at the <hi>height</hi> and <hi>beſt:</hi> Now the <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> the <hi>Beſt Good</hi> is <hi>Happineſſe;</hi> Every one there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>enjoying</hi> thoſe, or ſuch like things <hi>uſes</hi> them as the <hi>Meanes</hi> whereby to obtaine their <hi>End, Happineſſe.</hi> But now, we have a <hi>Generall Rule, The Meanes are to be ſought after, not for themſelves but, onely for the End:</hi> It muſt needs therefore be, he that helps us to the <hi>end,</hi> though he does not withall to the <hi>Meanes</hi> yet, gives us the <hi>Meanes too,</hi> becauſe he gives us <hi>that</hi> for which one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Meanes are good</hi> and <hi>deſireable.</hi> If then Chriſt <hi>promiſes</hi> and <hi>gives</hi> us the <hi>end</hi> we <hi>ſeek</hi> for in <hi>thoſe things,</hi> (as He does, and that in this Life) to wit, <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> Hee muſt needs therewithall by <hi>conſequence give</hi> us the <hi>Meanes,</hi> the <hi>Things themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But does He, moreover and above, give us an <hi>Hundred fold</hi> in too? Yes, that he does, and more. For, we muſt know, that though <hi>we ſeek</hi> for <hi>Happineſſe</hi> by ſuch <hi>Meanes</hi> yet, they are not the <hi>true Meanes</hi> to obtaine it: for then ſome time or other, in <hi>them</hi> we ſhould <hi>finde</hi> it. But that no man ever yet could doe: but ſtill, having <hi>enjoy'd any</hi> or <hi>all</hi> of them, they were faine to complaine with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine, Cor irrequietum eſt, donec veniat ad Te,</hi> That <hi>Mans deſire cannot be ſatisfi'd</hi> in any <hi>Creature;</hi> not, till it come at <hi>God.</hi> And ſo much we find wittily inſinuated
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:112525:28"/>by a <hi>Spaniſh Author,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. Aleman. <hi>1</hi> Book. ch. 7.</note> in his <hi>Fable</hi> of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> who being offended with Men for worſhipping their <hi>Petty God, Content,</hi> to a neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of <hi>himſelfe,</hi> took <hi>Content</hi> away from them unto <hi>himſelfe,</hi> and clapt his Brother <hi>Diſcontent</hi> into his clothes, that ſo men finding no <hi>Content</hi> on <hi>Earth,</hi> might ſeek for it onely with him in <hi>Heaven.</hi> The <hi>Fable</hi> does <hi>Moralize</hi> it ſelfe, and ſignifies nor more nor leſſe unto us, then what is the <hi>Subject</hi> of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon's Eccleſiaſtes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>Vanity of Vanities, all is but Vanity:</hi> that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here we muſt not ſet down our ſtaffe, but ſeek <hi>further</hi> to that <hi>City in the Heavens, whoſe Maker and Builder is God.</hi> But now <hi>thither</hi> thoſe <hi>Meanes</hi> wee ſpake of would never lead us, for then our Saviour would never have bidden us <hi>forſake them,</hi> to <hi>follow Him:</hi> A plaine <hi>Argument,</hi> they are, not <hi>Meanes</hi> and <hi>Helpes</hi> but, <hi>Remoraes</hi> and <hi>Hindrances,</hi> rather from <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing</hi> Him and <hi>obtaining Happineſſe.</hi> And then, I hope, it cannot bee, but <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in beſtowing on us that <hi>Happineſſe</hi> we <hi>ſeek</hi> after, but being blinde and erring cannot <hi>arrive</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: and this too by making us <hi>forſake</hi> what, we <hi>miſtake</hi> for <hi>Happineſſe</hi> but, is indeed our <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Miſery,</hi> does beſtow on us the <hi>full worth</hi> of thoſe <hi>Meanes</hi> and an <hi>Hundred fold</hi> to boot.</p>
            <p>But now, to the <hi>maine Point,</hi> That <hi>Chriſt promiſes</hi> and <hi>beſtowes,</hi> even in <hi>this life, true,</hi> (though not <hi>full</hi>) <hi>Happineſſe</hi> on all thoſe that <hi>forſake</hi> all and <hi>Deny themſelves:</hi> This we think poſſible to make appeare, the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> out of the <hi>Text,</hi> the <hi>Performance,</hi> out of the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall.</hi> The Promiſe, we ſay, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in the Text, not in ſo many words indeed but, by moſt plaine and infallible <hi>Conſequence:</hi> For the <hi>Text</hi> ſayes, <hi>If any one will follow Chriſt,</hi> he muſt <hi>Deny himſelfe</hi> to doe it: I hope then, if he <hi>does</hi> ſo, if he does <hi>Deny himſelfe, He promiſes</hi> hee may and ſhall <hi>follow him.</hi> But now what is it to <hi>follow Chriſt?</hi> It is to be <hi>whereſoever Chriſt is;</hi> So <hi>He Himſelfe expounds</hi> it, <hi>John</hi> 12.26. But how does He meane that? by a <hi>locall Motion?</hi> Certainly, Nothing leſſe; for then all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> muſt get them <hi>wings,</hi> and <hi>flye</hi> up to <hi>Heaven,</hi> where now our Saviour is: But in <hi>Spirit,</hi> for <hi>He</hi> ſayes, they are to be <hi>with Him,</hi> to <hi>ſee His Glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.18.</note> John 17.24. That is, as <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> expounds it, to be <hi>transform'd from Glory to Glory, as by the Spirit of the Lord,</hi> which is nothing elſe but to be <hi>ſpiritually Happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:112525:28"/>
            <p>For the <hi>Performance</hi> of this <hi>Promiſe;</hi> that will bee evident in the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Selfe-denyall.</hi> Which that wee may ſee, you muſt know, that <hi>Happineſſe is the Fruition of and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with God Himſelfe:</hi> That that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> muſt be by <hi>Love,</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Now, if there be nothing in the whole world beſide <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Creature:</hi> If <hi>theſe two</hi> make up <hi>every thing,</hi> then certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he that <hi>Denyes</hi> and <hi>forſakes the Creature,</hi> muſt needs <hi>love God</hi> or not <hi>love at all.</hi> That the <hi>Will</hi> ſhould not <hi>love at all</hi> is impoſſible, for then it ſhould not be a <hi>Will,</hi> ſeeing to <hi>Will</hi> and to <hi>Love</hi> are both one: Therefore <hi>Denying the Creature,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 4.16.</note> it muſt needs <hi>love God,</hi> therefore be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited to Him,</hi> therefore <hi>be Happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>God</hi> being <hi>our Summum bonum</hi> (as we all grant) the <hi>Perfect Good;</hi> he muſt needs attract <hi>proportionable,</hi> that is, <hi>Perfect Love.</hi> If He does not attract <hi>ſuch love</hi> every where, as 'tis plaine He does not, very few <hi>loving God in Sincerity,</hi> there ſeemes to be no other <hi>Reaſon</hi> of it, but this, the <hi>defect of mens ſight,</hi> that they <hi>ſee Him</hi> not to be <hi>ſuch,</hi> that is, <hi>their Perfect Good.</hi> Now of this. <hi>Defect</hi> there can be no other <hi>Reaſon</hi> rendred but this, The <hi>interpoſition</hi> of the <hi>Creature</hi> betwixt <hi>us</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> and our <hi>beholding</hi> and <hi>loving</hi> of <hi>it</hi> more then <hi>Him.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>Clouds</hi> that hinder us from <hi>beholding</hi> and <hi>admiring</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Sunne of Righteouſneſſe;</hi> this that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb. 12.1.</hi> Aquin. Lect. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> in locum.</note> 
               <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> ſpeakes of, that ſinne, or (as <hi>Thomas</hi>) that <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſinne,</hi> that does ſo <hi>eaſily,</hi> ſo <hi>every way beſet us,</hi> and therefore muſt be <hi>put away</hi> before we can <hi>runne the race</hi> of <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe,</hi> that is <hi>ſet before us.</hi> So then, it muſt needs be, If wee ſhall <hi>put away</hi> that <hi>ſinne,</hi> if we ſhall <hi>doffe our Selves,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>look off the Creature,</hi> to <hi>look on Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Finiſher</hi> of our <hi>Faith,</hi> and ſo <hi>ſee God onely</hi> in every thing, then wee ſhall be <hi>united</hi> and <hi>one with Him,</hi> as <hi>He with us;</hi> then <hi>our Will</hi> ſhall no longer be <hi>ours,</hi> but <hi>ſwallow'd up of His,</hi> and we ſhall no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be <hi>rul'd</hi> by <hi>it,</hi> but <hi>His Will</hi> ſhall <hi>rule</hi> within us: In a word, we ſhall be in <hi>this World,</hi> as we were in <hi>Paradiſe;</hi> that is, <hi>enjoy true ſolid Happineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But (marke yee) with this difference it is; Our <hi>Happineſſe here</hi> is but <hi>Inchoate,</hi> not as <hi>hereafter</hi> it ſhall bee, <hi>Conſummate.</hi> Here our <hi>Paradiſe</hi> is beſet with <hi>Bryars</hi> and <hi>Thornes,</hi> not as the <hi>Firſt,</hi> where was nothing but what was <hi>profitable</hi> and <hi>delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:112525:29"/>Therefore though our Saviour <hi>promiſes a Hundred fold here,</hi> yet 'tis with <hi>Perſecution:</hi> and therefore <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> tells us, we muſt <hi>runne our Race with Patience;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.1. Heb. 10.36.</note> for in another place hee ſayes, We <hi>had need of Patience, that ſo we may attaine the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>need we have</hi> of this <hi>Patience</hi> ariſes hence, becauſe of that <hi>Croſſe</hi> we muſt <hi>beare,</hi> as ſoon as we begin to <hi>Deny our Selves;</hi> for ſo it followes in the <hi>Text, Let him Deny himſelfe, and take up his Croſſe.</hi> What <hi>Croſſe</hi> is that? it is no other but that which wicked, <hi>Selfe-will'd</hi> men will <hi>lay</hi> upon our <hi>backs.</hi> For, though we, for our parts, <hi>Deny our Selves</hi> never ſo much, yet, becauſe the <hi>World</hi> will not doe ſo too, ſo long as we remaine in the <hi>Body,</hi> that will <hi>hate</hi> and <hi>perſecute</hi> us, as thoſe that doe the <hi>Workes of Darkneſſe hate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 3.20.</note> and <hi>curſe</hi> the <hi>Diſcovery</hi> of the <hi>Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the <hi>Happineſſe</hi> of every <hi>Particular Man,</hi> that ſhall <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himſelfe.</hi> But now if <hi>every Man</hi> ſhould doe ſo, Good God! what a <hi>Happineſſe</hi> were that to all men! what an Alteration would that make in the World! What a <hi>Golden Age</hi> ſhould we have! <hi>All things</hi> then would become <hi>New,</hi> and theſe <hi>Old things, Old Principles,</hi> would <hi>paſſe away</hi> and vaniſh. For, whereas there was never more of <hi>Hell</hi> upon <hi>Earth,</hi> then <hi>now;</hi> the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill</hi> never <hi>looſer,</hi> never more <hi>raging</hi> then <hi>now,</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>generality</hi> of <hi>Self-love</hi> and <hi>Self-will,</hi> that would <hi>baniſh</hi> the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill</hi> out of the <hi>World,</hi> or at leaſt ſo <hi>binde</hi> his hands, hee ſhould not hurt us; that would make <hi>this Earth</hi> a <hi>true perfect Paradiſe,</hi> where no other <hi>Will</hi> ſhould rule but <hi>God's,</hi> and <hi>He onely</hi> ſhould be <hi>exalted,</hi> He ſhould be <hi>All in all.</hi> For then our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings</hi> being full of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and our <hi>Wills</hi> of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour</hi> and <hi>Ingenuity,</hi> and our <hi>Affections</hi> abſolutely commanded by them <hi>both,</hi> all <hi>Factions,</hi> and <hi>Fractions</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> would be <hi>ſalv'd</hi> and <hi>remov'd:</hi> Then all our <hi>actions</hi> being mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd by <hi>Temperance</hi> and <hi>Moderation,</hi> our <hi>Bodies</hi> ſhould not bee impair'd by <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> or <hi>Phyſick,</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> be, not an <hi>Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> but, a <hi>Period</hi> unto <hi>Nature:</hi> And then too all <hi>Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Malice,</hi> and <hi>Envy</hi> being exterminated the World, <hi>Charity</hi> ſhould be the ſole <hi>Proprietour</hi> of our <hi>Wealth,</hi> and our <hi>Goods.</hi> we ſhould then think beſt beſtow'd, when upon <hi>God</hi> and His <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> ſervice. Finally, then there ſhould be <hi>Pax perennis,</hi> a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:112525:29"/>
               <hi>Perpetuall Inviolable Peace,</hi> the <hi>Gates</hi> of <hi>Janus's Temple</hi> ſhould continually be <hi>ſhut,</hi> ſo faſt, that the <hi>Gates of Hell</hi> ſhould never <hi>open them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let this ſuffice to have ſhewn an <hi>Hundred fold of Happineſſe,</hi> in <hi>this Life,</hi> to follow, according to our Saviour's <hi>Promiſe,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Self-denyall.</hi> But He ſtaies not <hi>here,</hi> in this life, for Hee tells us moreover, this <hi>Precept</hi> hath the <hi>Promiſe</hi> of the <hi>Life to come,</hi> of <hi>Life everlaſting.</hi> For the <hi>Proofe</hi> of this, tomake ſhore worke, I ſhall onely uſe one <hi>Proſyllogiſme,</hi> and that is this: The <hi>Knowledge of God</hi> is <hi>Life Eternall;</hi> The <hi>Love of God</hi> is the <hi>Knowledge of God;</hi> And <hi>Self-denyall</hi> is the <hi>Love of God,</hi> therefore <hi>Self-denyall</hi> is <hi>Life eternall.</hi> The firſt <hi>Propoſition</hi> is our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">John 17.3. Jer. 22.16.</note>; The Second S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 8.3.</note> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Johns</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1 John 2.3, 4.</note>; The third is plaine by neceſſary <hi>conſequence</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">See Page 55. Mat 16.26.</note>: For hee that <hi>Denyes himſelf,</hi> muſt doe it for ſomewhat that is <hi>better</hi> to him then <hi>himſelfe:</hi> But now our Saviour tells us, <hi>The whole</hi> creaned <hi>World</hi> is not to be <hi>priz'd of equall value</hi> to any one <hi>with Himſelfe,</hi> therefore certainly hee that <hi>Denyes Himſelfe</hi> muſt doe is for the <hi>Love of Him</hi> onely who is the <hi>Creator of Himſelf and all things elſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And accordingly the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſhewes us, that there is a plain <hi>Identity</hi> in Nature of <hi>Charity</hi> with <hi>Self-Donyall,</hi> where,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.5.</note> amongſt other things, he ſayes, <hi>Charity ſeeks not his owns things.</hi> Hee ſpeakes of <hi>Charity</hi> thereas a <hi>Perſon,</hi> which yet, we know, is but a <hi>Habit;</hi> his meaning therefore is, by <hi>Charity</hi> we <hi>ſeek not our c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> May we not then by the ſame reaſon ſay, <hi>Self-denyall loves</hi> and <hi>adberes to God,</hi> that is, by <hi>Self-denyall</hi> we come to <hi>love God?</hi> Surely, we may. We <hi>conclude</hi> them, <hi>Self-denyall</hi> is, not onely the <hi>way</hi> but, the <hi>Life Eternall it ſelfe?</hi> But this we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, not of <hi>Self-denyall inchoate,</hi> but <hi>conſummate.</hi> Nor is this any marvaile; for, if that be our <hi>Happineſſe in this life,</hi> as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready prov'd; this muſt certainly be that of the <hi>Life to come,</hi> the <hi>Life eternall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this <hi>Life Eternall</hi> being a thing to us as yet <hi>future,</hi> and to <hi>come,</hi> during our abode in the <hi>Body,</hi> we have no <hi>tenure</hi> of it otherwiſe then by <hi>Hope,</hi> that <hi>Hope</hi> which, to uſe the <hi>Apoſtles Phraſe,</hi> is <hi>ſubſtantiated by Faith</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note>. But this <hi>Hope</hi> muſt not bee <hi>Abſurd,</hi> we muſt render a <hi>Reaſon</hi> of it<note n="b" place="margin">1 Per. 3.15.</note>: And that <hi>Faith</hi> muſt not be <hi>lifeleſſe</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">James 2.20.</note>, it muſt <hi>operate by Love</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note>, Then let us ſee
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:112525:30"/>whether we can render any <hi>ſenſible Reaſon,</hi> or make any <hi>evident Demonſtration</hi> of that <hi>Hope,</hi> without this <hi>act of Self-denyall.</hi> If we examine thoſe <hi>acts</hi> of ours, whereon we ground any <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Evidence</hi> to entitle us to <hi>that life,</hi> we ſhall finde them all to be <hi>weake,</hi> yea <hi>nothing at all,</hi> without it. What elſe is our <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> the maine <hi>Evidence</hi> of our <hi>Salvation,</hi> but this <hi>act of Selfe-denyall?</hi> Its <hi>Averſion from the Creature</hi> is <hi>formally</hi> the ſame with it; Its <hi>Converſion unto God</hi> is <hi>neceſſarily imply'd</hi> in it; for who, that ha's once put in practiſe the <hi>Denyall of Himſelf,</hi> can ſay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 6.68.</note> then <hi>Peter</hi> did to our <hi>Saviour, Whither ſhall I goe from Thee? Thou haſt the words of Eternall Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What elſe is our <hi>Faith,</hi> that <hi>univerſall Engine</hi> of all <hi>Goſpel-Righteouſneſſe,</hi> but this <hi>act of Self-denyall,</hi> as formerly I have ſhewn? Certainly without it 'tis no better then <hi>Preſumption,</hi> for then onely, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, <hi>We live by the Faith of the Son of God, when we no longer live, but Chriſt lives in us</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note>. What is our <hi>frequent</hi> and <hi>attentive Hearing?</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, it will not <hi>profit</hi> us, except the <hi>Word be mingled with Faith in our Hearts</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 4.2.</note>: I'm ſure, our Saviour tells us, that to relie upon it, without <hi>Practiſe,</hi> is but to <hi>build our Houſe upon the Sands</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mar. 7.26.</note>, a dangerous <hi>Paralogiſme</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">James 1.22</note> or <hi>Deceit of our ſelves.</hi> But <hi>practiſe the Word</hi> we cannot without the <hi>Denyall of our Selves,</hi> unleſſe we ſhall thinke it ſo <hi>Paraſiticall,</hi> as to <hi>ſew Pillowes under our El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ezek. 13.20.</note>.</p>
            <p>In a word, we can yield <hi>God</hi> no <hi>true Obedience,</hi> doe Him no <hi>ſincere Chriſtian ſervice,</hi> without this <hi>act of Self-denyall.</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a <hi>Self-wil'd lover of himſelfe</hi> practiſe <hi>ſome Vertues,</hi> they are ſuch as <hi>Naturally</hi> he is <hi>not averſe</hi> from, and ſo coſting him but <hi>little</hi> or <hi>nothing,</hi> they are the <hi>leſſe valued by God;</hi> yea, perhaps they are <hi>ſuch,</hi> as whereby he hopes to <hi>make amends</hi> for his <hi>darling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved ſins.</hi> But for one to <hi>ſtabbe and mortifie</hi> his <hi>peculiar boſome ſinnes</hi> and to <hi>practiſe</hi> their <hi>oppoſite Vertues,</hi> to <hi>ſacrifice his Iſaac,</hi> to <hi>pull out his Right eye, cut off his Right hand; hîc ſpecimen ſpecitur, hîc certamen cernitur;</hi> this, this is <hi>the Tryall of the Saints; by this at length God experimentally knowes that we feare Him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.12 16, 17.</note> this act of ours therefore He <hi>ſweares</hi> that in <hi>Bleſſing He will Bleſſe,</hi> that is, will <hi>Bleſſe</hi> with the <hi>Bleſſing of Bleſſings,</hi> even no other but that of <hi>Eternall Bleſſedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:112525:30"/>
            <p>AND now at length, to draw up all: What <hi>Arguments</hi> can you poſſibly expect more, then we have us'd to perſwade you to <hi>Self-denyall?</hi> The <hi>Poſſibility</hi> ye have ſeen, the <hi>Equity, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, Excellency,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility</hi> of it. Here we are even at a <hi>full Stop,</hi> and can ſay no more but this, <hi>Goe you and doe likewiſe.</hi> For this indeed will prove a further and more forcible <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,</hi> then any we have <hi>us'd</hi> yet, the <hi>Experience</hi> of this <hi>Truth</hi> by your <hi>Practiſe,</hi> which wee have <hi>taught</hi> you in the <hi>Precept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be that after this <hi>Change</hi> of life, divers <hi>alterations</hi> will ariſe in your hearts, and that this <hi>great</hi> and <hi>Generall fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> which you muſt bid to your owne <hi>Follies</hi> and the <hi>Vanities</hi> of the World, well ſtirre in you ſome <hi>diſcouragement.</hi> If it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſo, let me, or our <hi>Saviour</hi> rather, winne thus much at your hands, as to have a little <hi>Patience,</hi> for it will come to nothing; it is but a little <hi>Aſtoniſhment</hi> which the <hi>Novelty</hi> of another life brings unto you; let that once paſſe over, and you ſhall receive <hi>Millions</hi> of <hi>Conſolations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then perhaps ſome <hi>Cowardly,</hi> faint-hearted men will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright you with <hi>tales of Giants, the Sons of Anak,</hi> of <hi>Cities wall'd up to Heaven, that the Land EATS <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>P the Inhabitants,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Num. 13.32.</note> that 'tis <hi>impoſſible</hi> for you to <hi>Deny your Selves,</hi> to remove the <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Self-love;</hi> Or, if you doe, you ſhall but <hi>undoe your Selves,</hi> and therefore with <hi>Peter,</hi> they will rather perſwade you to <hi>make much</hi> of your <hi>Selves,</hi> and <hi>returne to the Fleſh-pots</hi> of <hi>Egypt.</hi> But believe it, theſe are but the <hi>Deluſions</hi> of the <hi>Devill</hi> and <hi>Devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men,</hi> that ſeduce themſelves and others into the <hi>Pitt of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> Therefore, with our <hi>Saviour,</hi> liſten not to them, no <hi>not for a moment,</hi> but <hi>reſiſt them,</hi> or the <hi>Devill</hi> in them, and hee will ſoon <hi>ſtye from you.</hi> But believe <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> rather, that tell you, and tell you truely, you may <hi>goe in</hi> and <hi>conquer</hi> them: that is, believe <hi>Him,</hi> who is the <hi>true Joſhua,</hi> our <hi>Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who tells us that,<note place="margin">Matth. 17.20.</note> 
               <hi>if wee have a true Self-denying Faith, though but as a ſmall graine of Muſtard-ſeed,</hi> in compariſon, <hi>we ſhall be able to remove thoſe Mountaines</hi> of <hi>Self-love, and caſt them into</hi> the bottomleſſe <hi>Sea</hi> of God's Mercies. <hi>Thoſe could not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:112525:31"/>enter in becauſe of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeliefe;</hi> but theſe <hi>two ſearchers</hi> did <hi>enter,</hi> and <hi>conducted</hi> the <hi>People of God</hi> into the <hi>Land of Promiſe.</hi> No more can theſe <hi>timerous Pſeudo-Chriſtians,</hi> that ſmell too ranke of the <hi>Servile Oeconomy of the Law,</hi> finde <hi>entrance;</hi> but the <hi>True Chriſtians</hi> indeed, <hi>believing,</hi> not in themſelves but, the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> the <hi>Power of God to their Salvation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> ſhall <hi>enter</hi> and <hi>enjoy the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doe you try and ſee, and believe your owne <hi>Experience;</hi> my life for yours, not any one that will buckle himſelfe <hi>ſincerely</hi> to this worke, whom God will <hi>ſend away empty,</hi> but He will make him <hi>taſte of His Salvation.</hi> Doe but begin once to make a ſtrict <hi>ſearch</hi> and <hi>ſurview</hi> of your <hi>Hearts;</hi> above all ſearch out thoſe ſame <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Strong Holds,</hi> that they talkt of, that is, thoſe <hi>high</hi> and <hi>haughty Thoughts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4, 5.</note> whether they be <hi>Principles</hi> you have laid in <hi>Speculaction</hi> or in <hi>Practice,</hi> apply to them theſe <hi>Heavenly-mighty Engines</hi> of <hi>Self-denyall, Faith</hi> and <hi>Charity;</hi> and, like the <hi>Walls of Jericho,</hi> at <hi>firſt hand</hi> they will <hi>ſtall ſlat</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, though <hi>after a while</hi> you muſt looke to put <hi>more ſtrength</hi> to't.</p>
            <p>But this when you have done, be ſure you <hi>ſearch diligently</hi> for that ſame <hi>Regulus,</hi> that <hi>Petit King,</hi> that <hi>domineer'd in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> that is,<note place="margin">1 Kings 8.38.</note> the <hi>Peculiar Plague</hi> of every mans <hi>owne heart,</hi> (for ſuch an one there is moſt certaine, if the Word of God <hi>deceive</hi> us not) and though he <hi>hide</hi> himſelfe as deep as <hi>Hell</hi> in the <hi>Cave of Hypocriſie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 10.22.23, 24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>pull him out, ſet your feet upon his necke, ſmite him, ſlay him, hang him up:</hi> that is, <hi>Deny</hi> that <hi>Luſt</hi> of yours, which you are by <hi>Nature</hi> moſt <hi>addicted to,</hi> your <hi>Preſumptuous ſinne, Deny</hi> it with <hi>all</hi> your <hi>might,</hi> ſpare it not, but <hi>mortifie</hi> it <hi>utterly:</hi> And <hi>fear not,</hi> but encourage your ſelves, that, having deſtroyed <hi>that, God will doe ſo</hi> and more alſo, <hi>to all your other enemies.</hi> It ſhall be no <hi>griefe</hi> to you (when <hi>Death</hi> ſhall foroe you to it, if you <hi>Deny</hi> not your <hi>Selves</hi> the ſooner) to recompt what <hi>Luſts</hi> you have <hi>quell'd,</hi> what <hi>Temptations</hi> you have <hi>reſiſted,</hi> what <hi>hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> you have <hi>endur'd</hi> for <hi>Chriſts ſake;</hi> No, all your <hi>Hearing, Praying,</hi> and <hi>Sighing</hi> will be nothing to the <hi>comfort</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>But, I told you (&amp; you muſt expect no leſſe; neither let it <hi>deter,</hi> but <hi>excite</hi> you to <hi>grapple</hi> with the <hi>Difficulty;</hi>) this will ſeem <hi>durus ſermo,</hi> a <hi>harſh crabbed Leſſon</hi> to you, 'twill be <hi>grievous</hi> at the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:112525:31"/>
               <hi>firſt hand,</hi> as it were <hi>ever-night</hi> but then <hi>Joy will come in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> Does not our Saviour tell us ſo?<note place="margin">John 16.21.</note> that a <hi>Woman both ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row indeed while ſhe is in Travail, becauſe her Houre is comne; but having brought forth, ſhe remembers her Sorrow no more for joy, that a Man is borne into the World.</hi> I'm ſure, the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us, <hi>He that ſowes in teares ſhall reap in joy,<note place="margin">Pſal. 126.5, 6.</note> and bring his ſheaves with him.</hi> His <hi>Joy,</hi> ſaies the <hi>Prophet, is like the joy of men in Harveſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 9.3.</note> 
               <hi>or them that divide the ſpoile,</hi> whoſe <hi>joy</hi> is ſweetned by the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of what <hi>paines they firſt took for it.</hi> For indeed we have no <hi>Satisfactory</hi> title, either to our <hi>Meat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.10.</note> the <hi>food</hi> of our <hi>Bodies,</hi> or to <hi>Joy,</hi> the <hi>food</hi> of our <hi>Soules,</hi> without our <hi>precedent labour</hi> for it. Therefore our Saviour tells us,<note place="margin">Matth. 11.12.</note> 
               <hi>The Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is <hi>forc'd, ſtorm'd</hi> or <hi>ſuffers</hi> an <hi>Onſlaught,</hi> as I may ſay, and the <hi>Violent muſt take it by force,</hi> if they meane to have it.</p>
            <p>Was ever any <hi>Crown'd in a Comhat,</hi> that did not <hi>combate</hi> for it <hi>lawfully?</hi> or did ever any <hi>Farmer</hi> gather in a <hi>Harveſt,</hi> for which he <hi>laboured</hi> not <hi>before-hand?</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> thought not ſo,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> and therefore exhorted <hi>Timothy, to ſuffer affliction patiently, as a good Souldier of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>not to entangle himſelf with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of this life, that ſo he might the better pleaſe his Generall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non eſi è terris mollis ad aſtra via:</hi> Our journey to <hi>Heaven</hi> lyes, not through a <hi>ſpacious, ſmooth way,</hi> but a <hi>ſtraight narrow one</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 7.14.</note>, leading us through ſuch a <hi>gate,</hi> as is compar'd to a <hi>needles eye</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Matth. 19.24</note>. If therefore thou beeſt a <hi>ſmall ſlender thread,</hi> that is, a <hi>Self-reſigned</hi> man, thou maiſt <hi>finde entrance,</hi> and <hi>unite</hi> thy <hi>Self</hi> to the <hi>Eternall Being;</hi> but, if thou beeſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>huge unweildy Cahle,</hi> that is, <hi>encombred</hi> with thy <hi>Selfe,</hi> and that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that we ſpake of,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.1.</note> either look to <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twiſt thy Selfe</hi> by <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> or elſe deſpaire of <hi>Entrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can you think this <hi>durus ſermo,</hi> if you will <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <hi>look upon our Saviour:</hi> For canſt thou <hi>part</hi> with more then He did for <hi>thy ſake?</hi> thou canſt not for ſhame thinke it. Why, He was <hi>equall to God His Father from all eternity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 26, 7, 8.</note> nor <hi>thought it any robbery to be ſo,</hi> and yet <hi>emptied Himſelf</hi> in becomming a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> for us: But thou canſt not ſo much as <hi>equall thy Self</hi> to <hi>any thing:</hi> therefore canſt not <hi>keep any thing</hi> to thy <hi>Self,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.3.</note> without <hi>Robbery from thy Maker,</hi> who is, and in deſpight of thee,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:112525:32"/>ſtill ſhall be <hi>All in all</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.28.</note>. Is the <hi>Diſciple above his Maſter?</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hee is not: nay, 'tis <hi>well if he may be like him</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 10.24, 25.</note>: Chriſt therefore, our <hi>Maſter,</hi> lookes for <hi>ſo much</hi> at leaſt at our hands.</p>
            <p>But,<note place="margin">John 14.12.</note> if we thinke <hi>His Example</hi> above our <hi>Reach,</hi> (though He ſeemes to tell us otherwiſe) look but upon <hi>meer Animals,</hi> yea <hi>Inanimate Creatures,</hi> and, they will tell you, they <hi>Deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe;</hi> then ſhall not <hi>we</hi> much more <hi>for God?</hi> Certainly, we ſhould, and ſo much the rather, by how much God ha's endu'd us with <hi>Reaſon above them,</hi> which tells us, we were made <hi>for Him,</hi> not for our <hi>Selves.</hi> The <hi>Chymiſts</hi> doe not ſo truely affirme, that <hi>Nature intended Gold</hi> in the compoſure of <hi>all Metalls,</hi> as the <hi>Scripture</hi> tells us, <hi>God intended His Glory</hi> in the <hi>Creation</hi> of <hi>all things;</hi> And yet they, preſuming upon that, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to <hi>decoct</hi> their <hi>whole Subſtance</hi> many times to finde out the <hi>Semen auri</hi> or <hi>Philoſophers Stone:</hi> And ſhall not we <hi>decoct our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Being</hi> to <hi>finde</hi> our <hi>God in Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> we have infinite more <hi>Reaſon</hi> for it. For they cannot promiſe to themſelves ſo great a <hi>Multiplication</hi> of their <hi>Wealth</hi> upon that <hi>Invention of theirs,</hi> were it <hi>feiſable,</hi> as wee may promiſe our ſelves the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement</hi> of our <hi>Being</hi> by our <hi>Conjunction</hi> with <hi>God</hi> upon our<note place="margin">☞</note> 
               <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> the <hi>truer Art of Multiplication.</hi> If you conſult with an <hi>Arithmetician,</hi> he will tell you, that an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit multiply'd by an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit,</hi> is but an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit</hi> ſtill, it gets <hi>nothing</hi> by the hand: Now our <hi>Metaphyſicks</hi> truely tell us, <hi>Every thing</hi> is an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit;</hi> and our <hi>Phyſicks</hi> and <hi>Scripture</hi> tell us, <hi>Every thing</hi> is made to be <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd,</hi> that is, <hi>advanc't</hi> to ſome <hi>further end,</hi> then it <hi>ſelfe:</hi> He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſhall <hi>ſeek that end</hi> by a <hi>Multiplication</hi> or <hi>Seeking of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi> ſhall get <hi>nothing</hi> by it. But he that, <hi>confeſſing God</hi> onely to to be that <hi>Monas</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit,</hi> (as He is) ſhall <hi>quit</hi> his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and reduce himſelfe to a <hi>Cyphar,</hi> he, being added to that <hi>Onely <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit,</hi> ſhall become a moſt <hi>Perfect Number,</hi> and be <hi>Multiply'd</hi> 10, yea, (which is the <hi>ſuperabundant</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 5.20.</note> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi>) 100<note n="a" place="margin">Mark 10.30.</note> for one.</p>
            <p>Take heed then, you neither <hi>act</hi> nor <hi>ſpeake</hi> with that <hi>ſlothfull Servant</hi> that,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.20, 21</note> in ſtead of <hi>Multiplying, wrapt up his Pound,</hi> that is, <hi>himſelfe, in a greazie Napkin, and buried</hi> himſelfe in the <hi>Earth</hi> all the time of his <hi>Life,</hi> the onely time of our <hi>Improvement</hi> and <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:112525:32"/>Take heed you <hi>ſpeake</hi> not as he did, who <hi>call'd his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter an Auſtere man,</hi> for <hi>reaping that which be never ſow'd.</hi> A moſt injurious <hi>Slander;</hi> his owne words plainly witneſſed as much; <hi>Here, Sir,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>is your Pound againe:</hi> Why then a <hi>Pound</hi> he had by <hi>confeſſion,</hi> therefore ſo much, at leaſt, was <hi>ſowne.</hi> Well, and what did his <hi>Maſter</hi> expect to <hi>reap from him?</hi> 'twas but his owne with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury;</hi> muſt he then be <hi>voic't an Auſtere man</hi> for this? I wonder, what leſſe could he look for? will any <hi>Dealer</hi> trade for leſſe then <hi>common Intereſt?</hi> any <hi>Farmer</hi> ſow for leſſe then a <hi>competent encreaſe?</hi> If they doe, they ſhould be <hi>loſers</hi> by the hand, and ſo ſhould his <hi>Maſter</hi> have been. Then take heed, I ſay, you <hi>blaſpheme</hi> not God in your hearts, for requiring <hi>Self-denyall</hi> of you. But above all take heed, you <hi>act</hi> not with that <hi>Servant,</hi> you <hi>bury</hi> not your precious <hi>Soule, wrapt up</hi> in your <hi>greazie Fleſh,</hi> in the Bowels of this <hi>Earthly World;</hi> for, as he ſo, you will gain <hi>nothing</hi> by it; No <hi>Improvement,</hi> no <hi>Multiplication</hi> can come of ſuch <hi>Beaſtly ſloath:</hi> No, but like him you will be <hi>loſers,</hi> even <hi>Bankrupted,</hi> by the Meanes. <hi>He loſt</hi> his <hi>Pound firſt,</hi> ſo ſhall you your <hi>Parts,</hi> your <hi>Naturall,</hi> yea and <hi>Spirituall Endowments.</hi> Then he <hi>loſt</hi> his <hi>Perſon,</hi> being <hi>caſt into utter darkneſſe,</hi> that is, into ſuch a <hi>Condition</hi> as <hi>is farre worſe then nothing.</hi> For <hi>Nothing</hi> is but a <hi>Negation:</hi> but <hi>Darkneſſe,</hi> wee know, is a <hi>Privation,</hi> that is, the <hi>Loſſe of a Habit:</hi> If then it be farre better, as it is, never to have had a <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> then having had, to <hi>loſe</hi> it, then farre better it is, never to have <hi>partaken of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 26.24.1 John 1.5.</note> who is <hi>Light,</hi> then <hi>partaking of Him</hi> to bee caſt into <hi>utter darkneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet ſuch ſhall be thy <hi>Condemnation,</hi> whoſoever thou art, that art a <hi>Theeviſh, Trayterous, Idolatrous Lover</hi> of thy <hi>Selfe:</hi> 'Tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, <hi>God</hi> muſt not be a <hi>loſer,</hi> whatſoever come of it: <hi>His Will</hi> muſt be <hi>done, His Glory</hi> muſt be <hi>ſhewne, vel à nobis, vel de nobis;</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>of us,</hi> or <hi>upon us.</hi> If then we would <hi>judge</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.31.</note> by the <hi>Denyall of our ſelves</hi> confeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>God</hi> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>onely</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Selfe-Beer</hi> of the world, we ſhould not be <hi>Judged</hi> of the Lord, not <hi>deprived</hi> of that <hi>Fountain</hi> of all <hi>Being;</hi> But, not <hi>Judging</hi> our <hi>ſelves</hi> at all, that is, <hi>ſeeking our owne things,</hi> and <hi>not the things of God,</hi> by endeavouring to eſtabliſh our <hi>Self-being,</hi> and ſo <hi>denying</hi> into be <hi>God's Prerogative,</hi> He <hi>condemnes</hi> us with the <hi>world,</hi> that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:112525:33"/>is, <hi>baniſhes</hi> us from his <hi>Gracious Preſence,</hi> ſo manifeſting <hi>Himſelfe</hi> to be the <hi>onely Selfe-Bëer</hi> of the world, but our <hi>ſelves,</hi> now by our own <hi>Default,</hi> to become more <hi>Vile</hi> then <hi>Nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, we ſee, God is no <hi>loſer</hi> in His <hi>Glory,</hi> if we ſhall <hi>ſeek</hi> our <hi>ſelves;</hi> and as certain it is, we ſhall be no <hi>loſers</hi> in our <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe,</hi> if we <hi>Deny our ſelves;</hi> becauſe wee have to doe with <hi>Him, who is the Lord God of Recompence</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Jerem 51.56.</note>; <hi>One</hi> that will not ſuffer us to <hi>loſe any thing,</hi> we lay out for <hi>His ſake,</hi> not ſo much as a <hi>Cup of cold water</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 10.42.</note>. For though, when we have done our <hi>beſt,</hi> we have done <hi>no more</hi> then was our <hi>Duty</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Luke 17.10.</note> yet, will God <hi>reward that Duty now;</hi> He deales with us, not upon tearms of <hi>ſtrict Juſtice,</hi> but of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>favour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matthew 6.4.</note> Doſt thou then <hi>quit</hi> thy <hi>Prayſe,</hi> by <hi>Praying, Faſting,</hi> and <hi>Almes-giving in Private?</hi> God will one day <hi>commend thee openly.</hi> Doſt thou <hi>quit</hi> thine <hi>Honour</hi> by <hi>Humility?</hi> God will one day <hi>exalt thee.</hi> Doſt thou then <hi>quit</hi> thy <hi>ſtrength</hi> by <hi>Patience?</hi> God will one day <hi>Revenge thee.</hi> Doſt thou <hi>quit</hi> thy <hi>Wiſdome</hi> by <hi>Simplicity?</hi> God will one day manifeſt <hi>that</hi> to be the <hi>only Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> I might be infinite in all <hi>Particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us heare the <hi>Concluſion</hi> of the whole matter: It is no more but what our Saviour tells us in the verſe behind our <hi>Text,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 25.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in ſo many words: He that <hi>ſeekes himſelfe,</hi> ſhall indeed <hi>finde himſelfe,</hi> but to his owne <hi>Deſtruction;</hi> But he that <hi>Denyes himſelfe,</hi> ſhall indeed be <hi>rid of himſelfe,</hi> but to his owne <hi>ſalvation.</hi> Then what <hi>profit</hi> will it bee to thee to <hi>gaine thy ſelfe,</hi> yea the <hi>whole world,</hi> if thou muſt <hi>looſe thine own ſoule?</hi> what <hi>Recompence</hi> canſt thou give for it? the <hi>whole World</hi> will not be <hi>ſufficient,</hi> nor any thing in the World, but <hi>Him that overcame the World</hi> for thee. If it be grievous to <hi>Deny thy Self,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 12.9. Matth. 7.23.</note> what will it be, to be <hi>Deny'd of Chriſt,</hi> when He ſhall ſay, <hi>I know you not?</hi> If thou canſt not finde in thine heart to ſay, <hi>Depart from me Iniquity;</hi> how ſhalt thou finde in thine heart to heare (that <hi>Thunder-clap</hi>) <hi>Depart from Me yee workers of Iniquity?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 33.14.</note> If thou art not able to <hi>abide with this conſuming fire,</hi> how wilt thou be able to <hi>Dwell with everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Burnings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may bee now, on the contrary, there will be found, to whom this duty of <hi>Self-denyall</hi> is ſo farre from being <hi>grievous,</hi> they are ſorry, they have not now (as thoſe in the <hi>Primitive</hi> times had) occaſion to expreſſe it <hi>fully.</hi> They could willingly
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:112525:33"/>
               <hi>reſiſt,</hi> that is, patiently yeeld themſelves, though it were <hi>to bloud,</hi> were it (as thoſe <hi>Martyrs</hi> did) for the <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt:</hi> But to ſuffer for the <hi>Circumſtantialls</hi> onely, not the <hi>Subſtantialls</hi> of <hi>Religion;</hi> yea to ſuffer for thoſe <hi>Morall Duties,</hi> which a <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> man would ſuffer for, this, they eſteeme not worth the while, not worth the <hi>Denying</hi> of their Eſtates, Honours, Eaſe, at leaſt their Lives; and therefore they eaſily perſwade themſelves, they are not hereunto obliged, or, if they be, to neglect ſuch Duties is but a <hi>Peccadillo,</hi> a ſmall ſinne, they can cry God mercy for it; and ſo gilding the <hi>Pill</hi> o're a little, they ſwallow it downe ſmoothly, without any Remorſe at all.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that others, to get the Reputation to themſelves of (no leſſe then) <hi>Martyrs</hi> for the <hi>Truth,</hi> ſtrongly flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they ſuffer <hi>for Chriſt,</hi> that they doe; when yet, even in their owne pretence, it is but for His <hi>Garment,</hi> but in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Humbler Men, is not for that neither, but their <hi>owne Wills,</hi> then which nothing can be more contrary to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or Suffering <hi>for Him,</hi> and therefore to <hi>Self-denyall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to the firſt, I anſ. That even in this it appears, they are not <hi>Self-denyed</hi> men, that they take upon them to <hi>preſcribe</hi> to God Almighty: As if he knew not, by calling them to what <hi>Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings,</hi> they ſhould glorifie Him, and benefit themſelves moſt. For in true <hi>Self-denyall</hi> we ever part with our own <hi>Election,</hi> our own <hi>Will,</hi> and ſubmit it to anothers: Now this he cannot do, that will beare no other <hi>Croſſe,</hi> but what is of his owne <hi>chooſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then eſpecially does this <hi>Election</hi> fight with our <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> when it pitches upon ſuch <hi>Croſſes</hi> onely, as are more <hi>Glorious,</hi> ſuch as were thoſe of the <hi>Primitive Martyrs;</hi> For in ſuch <hi>Sufferings</hi> we <hi>ſeek</hi> our <hi>owne Things,</hi> not the <hi>Things</hi> of God, wee ſeek our owne <hi>Repute,</hi> our owne <hi>Reward:</hi> not our owne <hi>Abjection, Vileneſſe, Contempt,</hi> and <hi>Nothing.</hi> But this, in ſome degree, muſt be done in the <hi>true Denyall of our Selves:</hi> and this, we muſt know, may be done <hi>as well,</hi> if not <hi>better,</hi> by Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for <hi>ſmall</hi> as <hi>greater</hi> matters. For the leſſe <hi>Motive our</hi> Sufferings have from <hi>without</hi> themſelves, 'tis a ſigne, they have the more from <hi>within,</hi> that they proceed meerly from a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> of our owne <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Abjection.</hi> But now, the <hi>Meaner</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:112525:34"/>that is we ſuffer for, if we ſuffer for it with <hi>equall Patience,</hi> as for a <hi>Greater</hi> matter, the leſſe is our <hi>Motive</hi> from <hi>without,</hi> and and ſo muſt argue the greater <hi>Conſcience</hi> of <hi>Duty</hi> from <hi>within,</hi> which is ſo farre from <hi>diſparaging,</hi> it ſets a <hi>Price</hi> upon our <hi>Self-denyal.</hi> Againe, <hi>what</hi> we ſhall ſuffer for, <hi>when</hi> and <hi>where,</hi> is not in our <hi>Election,</hi> but in God's <hi>Providence</hi> calling us thereunto: So is not our <hi>Willingneſſe</hi> and <hi>Cheerfulneſſe</hi> in ſuffering, for that, by the <hi>Grace</hi> of God, is; <hi>this</hi> therefore is to be reckoned to our <hi>Praiſe,</hi> that rather to our <hi>Recompence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it pleas'd the All-wiſe God to call the <hi>Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> to be <hi>Witneſſes</hi> to His more <hi>Fundamentall Truths</hi> that being done abundantly, it pleaſes Him now to call <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> to be <hi>Witneſſes</hi> to His <hi>Truthes of inferiour Nature.</hi> What then? ſhall we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe theſe <hi>Meaner</hi> ones, as not <hi>worth</hi> our <hi>Suffering</hi> for? let us take heed of that; None of them but are <hi>God's:</hi> None but in the <hi>Sequell</hi> are of <hi>infinite</hi> concernment: None but are <hi>more worth</hi> then <hi>all</hi> we are or have, yea then the <hi>whole World</hi> it ſelfe: None, but which in ſuffering for, we ſuffer <hi>for Chriſt Himſelf,</hi> who calls Himſelfe <hi>the Truth.</hi> If then we ſuffer <hi>for Chriſt</hi> in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for <hi>His Meaneſt Truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John. 14.6</note> we ought to be ſo far from <hi>excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> ourſelves, or <hi>declining</hi> ſuch ſuffering, as which were <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatively</hi> to <hi>Deny Chriſt,</hi> that we ought rather to <hi>comfort</hi> our ſelves <hi>in this behalfe,</hi> that we are thought worthy <hi>any wayes</hi> to ſuffer for Him.</p>
            <p>But much better it is wholly to wave the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of our Sufferings, leaving that to God's <hi>Providence,</hi> and, reflecting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Selves,</hi> look to the <hi>Quality</hi> of our ſuffering, take thought, not how <hi>great</hi> but, how <hi>good</hi> Sufferers we are, with what <hi>Willingneſſe,</hi> what <hi>Love</hi> of God and <hi>Reſignation</hi> of our Selves we ſuffer. For thus wee may <hi>equalize,</hi> if not <hi>out-goe</hi> thoſe <hi>Primitive Chriſtians.</hi> If they ſuffer'd for more <hi>weighty</hi> matters, we may ſuffer with more <hi>obedient</hi> Affections; if their Sufferings were more <hi>Glorious,</hi> ours may be more <hi>Vertuous;</hi> If they ſuffered for the <hi>juſtifying</hi> of our <hi>Faith,</hi> why may not we be call'd to ſuffer for the <hi>juſtifying</hi> of <hi>Suffering</hi> it ſelfe, of the <hi>Scandall</hi> of the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> of the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Self-Denyall?</hi> For my part, I judge, we are. <hi>Our</hi> Sufferings therefore ſeeme the more <hi>Arduous</hi> and <hi>Difficult</hi> of the two, by how much more
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:112525:34"/>difficult it is to conteſt with <hi>Ignominy</hi> then with <hi>Errour,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce our <hi>owne Wills,</hi> then our <hi>owne <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here, it may be, ſome will ſay, It cannot be deny'd though, but that the <hi>Sufferings</hi> of Chriſtians now are farre <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour</hi> to thoſe of the <hi>Primitive Martyrs,</hi> which were moſt <hi>hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid.</hi> I cannot tell, whether that alſo may be allow'd or no. For ſo it may be, that one may <hi>Deny himſelfe much</hi> by ſuffering in a <hi>ſmall matter,</hi> and on the contrary may <hi>Deny himſelf</hi> but <hi>little</hi> by ſuffering in a <hi>greater;</hi> for all goes as the <hi>Mind</hi> is &amp; ſets a <hi>price</hi> on that we ſuffer in. Our <hi>Self-denyal</hi> receives its <hi>value</hi> from our <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> in things; Now our <hi>Intereſt</hi> lyes in things, not ever according to their <hi>Worth</hi> but, moſt-what according to our <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> &amp; <hi>Love</hi> of them, which, by reaſon of our <hi>Blindneſſe</hi> ſince our <hi>Fall,</hi> is ſeldome proportioned to the <hi>juſt Worth</hi> of any thing. Hence it comes to paſſe that, as the <hi>Schooles</hi> tell us, we often <hi>ſtampe</hi> a <hi>high price</hi> on thoſe things <hi>amore intenſivo,</hi> by our <hi>affectionate love,</hi> which <hi>amore appreciativo,</hi> by a <hi>diſcreet judicious Love,</hi> we ſhould eſteem of <hi>little</hi> or <hi>no value:</hi> A Childe will not part with his <hi>Boble</hi> for his <hi>Dinner,</hi> not becauſe it is <hi>more worth</hi> but, becauſe he ha's not the <hi>Diſcretion</hi> to <hi>judge</hi> aright of <hi>either:</hi> So a man may <hi>preferre</hi> his <hi>owne Will,</hi> his <hi>owne Glory,</hi> before his <hi>Eſtate,</hi> yea and his <hi>Life</hi> too, as may eaſily be gather'd from the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. not becauſe they are <hi>more worth</hi> but, becauſe he is ſo <hi>mad</hi> to <hi>judge</hi> ſo. Now if this be ſo, as it is moſt plaine, then are we not to <hi>judge</hi> of mens <hi>Self-denyall</hi> by the <hi>Outward face</hi> of their <hi>Sufferings,</hi> but by that <hi>Private Intereſt,</hi> which by their <hi>Affections</hi> they have in the <hi>things</hi> they ſuffer in. For by reaſon of <hi>this</hi> it is, that a man may <hi>ſuffer more,</hi> that is, with more <hi>Reſignation</hi> of himſelfe, by the <hi>loſſe</hi> of a commodious <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſill,</hi> by a <hi>Frump</hi> from a <hi>Great Perſonage,</hi> or an <hi>open Diſgrace,</hi> then by <hi>empaling,</hi> or any <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>greater torture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then why ſhould any man judge e're the <hi>meanlier</hi> of his <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> becauſe he ſuffers not either <hi>for</hi> or <hi>in</hi> ſo <hi>great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> as others <hi>heretofore</hi> have done? Let him look onely to <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> that, through <hi>Pride of heart,</hi> he does not <hi>riſe up</hi> againſt that <hi>Croſſe,</hi> which it pleaſes God to <hi>lay</hi> upon him. Let him freely <hi>reſigne up</hi> the <hi>Triall</hi> of himſelfe to God, who knowes well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough how to deale with him and <hi>ſift</hi> him out. If it pleaſes
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:112525:35"/>God to <hi>prove</hi> him by that which is a <hi>Toy</hi> in it ſelfe, though ſuch an one as to which he is much <hi>affected,</hi> (for ſo uſually God deals with us <hi>at firſt</hi>) let him <hi>accept</hi> of the <hi>Croſſe, embrace</hi> and <hi>wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come</hi> it, God, who is well skill'd in the rule of <hi>Proportions,</hi> takes our <hi>Patience equally,</hi> at our hands, as if our <hi>Croſſe</hi> were <hi>greater.</hi> He layes not <hi>Afflictions</hi> upon us, thereby <hi>Envying</hi> us His <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings;</hi> No, He would have us enjoy them ſtill, could we but get the <hi>Art, to uſe them, as though we us'd them not.</hi> If we can (or rather will) not,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.75</note> then He, in <hi>very Faithfulneſſe, weanes</hi> us of them, to make us look after <hi>thoſe</hi> that are <hi>greater,</hi> but more <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall.</hi> Finally, let him conſider, that the <hi>leaſt Croſſe</hi> he ſuffers under is <hi>farre above</hi> what he is able to beare, were he left unto <hi>himſelfe</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">John 15.5.</note>; that by the <hi>Grace of God</hi> he is what he is<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10.</note>; that <hi>God workes in him both the Will</hi> to ſuffer, and the <hi>Performance,</hi> and that of <hi>His good will</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note>, but not <hi>againſt his own:</hi> That <hi>our Part</hi> onely is purely to <hi>Deny</hi> our <hi>owne Will</hi> and <hi>Reſigne</hi> up our <hi>Selves</hi> to Him, which yet we cannot doe <hi>of our Selves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>as of our Selves,</hi> that is, we cannot doe <hi>without Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, in the laſt place: If any <hi>tender Conſcience</hi> be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd, that he findes the <hi>Reliques</hi> of <hi>Self-love</hi> ſtruggle in him, let him comfort himſelfe in this, that the <hi>Raigning</hi> power of it is ſubdu'd, as for the taking away of the <hi>Remaining</hi> power, it is not to be expected in <hi>this life.</hi> Is he ſure, that ſame <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulus,</hi> we ſpake of,<note place="margin">Before Pag. 60.</note> is deſtroy'd, his <hi>old Habit</hi> reſiſted, his <hi>old Haunt</hi> broken off, that he ha's runne counter to the <hi>broad road,</hi> of the <hi>Epidemicall Vices</hi> of the <hi>Times?</hi> If it be ſo, then ha's he whereof to <hi>rejoyce.</hi> As for the <hi>Dead Body</hi> of that <hi>Regulus</hi> it muſt <hi>hang up</hi> till the <hi>Evening,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 10.27.</note> till our <hi>Death:</hi> but when our <hi>Sun ſets,</hi> that ſhall bee <hi>taken downe.</hi> Meane time, 'tis enough he is <hi>Dead</hi> and <hi>Mortifi'd,</hi> that the <hi>Canaanites</hi> which are left are <hi>Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour</hi> and not <hi>conſiderable</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that the <hi>Fleſh</hi> is kept under by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>love of our Selves,</hi> by the <hi>Love of God.</hi> What ſayes St. <hi>Paul?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.10.</note> he ſayes not, we ſhould be <hi>wholly free</hi> from all <hi>commerce</hi> with <hi>evill,</hi> becauſe then we muſt be out of the <hi>World,</hi> but that we ſhould not <hi>conſent</hi> to it. And therefore, he ſayes,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.23.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, even the very <hi>Saints themſelves groan in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, looking for the Adoption, the Redemption,</hi> that is, the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification, of their Bodies;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> to wit, then when their <hi>Mortall Bodies
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:112525:35"/>ſhall be ſwallowed up of Immortality, and made like to the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Body of the Sonne of God,</hi> the <hi>laſt,</hi> and <hi>greateſt</hi> of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is certaine; ſo long as we are <hi>in the Body,</hi> this vile, vain <hi>Body</hi> of ours will be as <hi>Thornes in our eyes, and Goads in our ſides,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 23.13. 2 Cor. 12.7.</note> that is, we ſhall be <hi>tempted</hi> of it. But then, we muſt know, it is not <hi>evill</hi> to be tempted, but to be <hi>overcome</hi> of a <hi>Temptation;</hi> Yea, our <hi>Temptation,</hi> if reſiſted, will redound to our <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage</hi> and God's <hi>Glory,</hi> which is <hi>perfected in our weakneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. Verſe 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Meane time, we had <hi>need of Patience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.36.</note> 
               <hi>to runne the Race that is ſet before us, that ſo we faint not and draw backe.</hi> And, though we ſee <hi>totum mundum jacere in Maligno,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.19.</note> as St. <hi>John</hi> ſaid of <hi>his time,</hi> and we may more juſtly of <hi>ours,</hi> yet are we bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> even in the midſt of <hi>Tempeſts</hi> and <hi>Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 21.28.</note> 
               <hi>to lift up our Heads becauſe then our Redemption drawes nigheſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo wee ſee indeed oft-times it comes to paſſe,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.6.</note> that <hi>God</hi> drawes the <hi>greateſt good</hi> out of the <hi>Extremity of evill,</hi> the moſt <hi>Glorious Light</hi> out of the <hi>thickeſt Darkneſſe.</hi> So <hi>cum dupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabantur lateres venit Moſes,</hi> when the <hi>Iſraelites taske</hi> was <hi>doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Moſes came:</hi> when the <hi>Government was taken from</hi> Judah, Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loh <hi>came:</hi> And ſo we may aſſuredly expect, after all <hi>theſe Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts</hi> and <hi>Garboyles</hi> are blowne over, a <hi>greater calme of Peace and Piety</hi> then ever. <hi>Such a thing</hi> ha's been foretold long ſince by the <hi>Prophets,</hi> but never was yet; never was <hi>leſſe</hi> then <hi>now,</hi> now that <hi>Self-love</hi> playes the <hi>Tyrant</hi> in the <hi>ſhape</hi> of <hi>Self-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> and therefore <hi>yet</hi> we may expect it. This is certaine; <hi>Chriſt muſt lay all His Enemies at his Feet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.25.</note> the <hi>greateſt</hi> of which is <hi>Selfe-love,</hi> and the <hi>laſt,</hi> its <hi>Wages, Death;</hi> theſe muſt be <hi>ſubdued under Him.</hi> And when, thinke we, ſhould this more likely be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, then when <hi>Chriſt ſhall come the Second time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9.28. Tit. 2.13.</note> not in <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility</hi> but, in <hi>Glory;</hi> when the <hi>Church</hi> ſhall <hi>triumph Victoriouſly over all her Enemies?</hi> In the meane while, that it be not now brought to paſſe, let us not be in fault; and therefore let every one in particular <hi>reforme</hi> and <hi>Deny Himſelfe:</hi> this will be a good forwarding of the <hi>Generall.</hi> Which though, no queſtion, wee ſhall faile of in <hi>this deplor'd, Selfe-flattering Age wee live in,</hi> yet, this wee may bee aſſur'd of, to our
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:112525:36"/>comfort, <hi>liberabimus animas noſtras, we ſhall free and ſave our owne ſoules.</hi> Which <hi>He</hi> grant unto us, Who by <hi>Denying Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe moſt perfectly</hi> hath left us an <hi>Example, that we ſhould follow in His ſteps.</hi> To whom be given all <hi>Honour, Glory,</hi> and <hi>Praiſe</hi> both now and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>I Should have proceeded to raiſe two <hi>Conſectaries</hi> from this <hi>Doctrine:</hi> One whereof is, That <hi>Adverſity</hi> is a <hi>ſafer Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> man, then <hi>Proſperity:</hi> Anſwerably whereunto, our Saviour bids us <hi>take up our Croſſe.</hi> The <hi>Other is like unto it:</hi> That <hi>Subjection</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> is a farre <hi>ſafer Condition</hi> for a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> man, then <hi>Soveraignty</hi> and command; Anſwerably where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, our Saviour bids us, <hi>Follow Him.</hi> But this <hi>Adventure</hi> muſt wait another <hi>Tide.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 3. 1646. <hi>Imprimatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>JOHN DOWNAME.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Corrigenda.</head>
            <p>PAGE 8. line 17. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 10. l. 23. for, <hi>is not,</hi> r. <hi>is it not.</hi> p. 27. l. 1. for, <hi>He bids,</hi> r. <hi>He bids us.</hi> Ib. l. 38. <hi>place this figure</hi> II. <hi>in the Marg.</hi> p. 30. l. 1. for, <hi>alſo that,</hi> r. <hi>alſo of that.</hi> p. 34. l. 29. for, <hi>Precept,</hi> r. <hi>precepts.</hi> p, 36. l. 29. <hi>blot out the ſemicol. after Him, and place it after God's.</hi> p. 43. <hi>refer the</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>quot. in the Marg. to</hi> l. 24. <hi>the</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>to</hi> l. 26. p. 64. l. 7. <hi>recompence,</hi> r. <hi>recompences.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:112525:36"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
